Proem

Without all fear, without presumption, he
Who wrote this work would speak respecting it
A few brief words, and face his friend the world;
Revising, not reversing, what hath been.

Poetry is itself a thing of God;
He made His prophets poets; and the more
We feel of poesie do we become
Like God in love and power—under-makers.
All great lays, equals to the minds of men,
Deal more or less with the Divine, and have
For end some good of mind or soul of man.
The mind is this world’s, but the soul is God’s;
The wise man joins them here all in his power.
The high and holy works, amid lesser lays,
Stand up like churches among village cots;
And it is joy to think that in every age,
However much the world was wrong therein,
The greatest works of mind or hand have been
Done unto God. So may they ever be!
It shows the strength of wish we have to be great,
And the sublime humility of might.

True fiction hath in it a higher end
Than fact; it is the possible compared
With what is merely positive, and gives
To the conceptive soul an inner world,
A higher, ampler, Heaven than that wherein
The nations sun themselves. In that bright state
Are met the mental creatures of the men
Whose names are writ highest on the rounded crown
Of Fame’s triumphal arch; the shining shapes
Which star the skies of that invisible land,
Which, whosoe’er would enter, let him learn;—
’Tis not enough to draw forms fair and lively,
Their conduct likewise must be beautiful;
A hearty holiness must crown the work,
As a gold cross the minster-dome, and show,
Like that instonement of divinity,
That the whole building doth belong to God.
And for the book before us, though it were,
What it is not, supremely little, like
The needled angle of a high church spire,
Its sole end points to God the Father’s glory,
From all eternity seen; making clear
His might and love in saving sinful man.
One bard shows God as He deals with states and kings;
Another, as He dealt with the first man;
Another, as with Heaven and earth and hell;
Ours, as He loves to order a chance soul
Chosen out of the world, from first to last.
And all along it is the heart of man
Emblemed, created and creative mind.
It is a statued mind and naked heart
Which is struck out. Other bards draw men dressed
In manners, customs, forms, appearances,
Laws, places, times, and countless accidents
Of peace or polity: to him these are not;
He makes no mention, takes no compt of them:—
But shows, however great his doubts, sins, trials,
Whatever earthborn pleasures soil man’s soul,
What power soever he may gain of evil,
That still, till death, time is; that God’s great Heaven
Stands open day and night to man and spirit;
For all are of the race of God, and have
In themselves good. The life-writ of a heart,
Whose firmest prop and highest meaning was
The hope of serving God as poet-priest,
And the belief that He would not put back
Love-offerings, though brought to Him by hands
Unclean and earthy, e’en as fallen man’s
Must be; and most of all, the thankful show
Of His high power and goodness in redeeming
And blessing souls that love Him, spite of sin
And their old earthy strain—these are the aims,
The doctrines, truths, and staple of the story.
What theme sublimer than soul being, saved?
’Tis the bard’s aim to show the mind-made world
Without, within; how the soul stands with God,
And the unseen realities about us.
It is a view of life spiritual
And earthly. Let all look upon it, then,
In the same light it was drawn and colored in;
In faith, in that the writer too hath faith,
Albeit an effect, and not a cause.
Faith is a higher faculty than reason,
Though of the brightest power of revelation;
As the snow-headed mountain rises o’er
The lightning, and applies itself to Heaven.
We know in day-time there are stars about us,
Just as at night, and name them what and where
By sight of science; so by faith we know,
Although we may not see them till our night,
That spirits are about us, and believe,
That, to a spirit’s eye, all Heaven may be
As full of angels as a beam of light
Of motes. As spiritual, it shows all
Classes of life, perhaps, above our kind,
Known to tradition, reason, or God’s word,
Whose bright foundations are the heights of Heaven.
As earthly, it embodies most the life
Of youth, its powers, its aims, its deeds, its failings;
And, as a sketch of world-life, it begins
And ends, and rightly, in Heaven and with God;
While Heaven is also in the midst thereof.

God, or all good, the evil of the world,
And man, wherein are both, are each displayed.
The mortal is the model of all men.
The foibles, follies, trials, sufferings—
And manifest and manifold are they—
Of a young, hot, unworld-schooled heart that has
Had its own way in life, and wherein all
May see some likeness of their own—’tis these
Attract, unite, and, sunlike, concentrate
The ever-moving system of our feelings.
The hero is the world-man, in whose heart
One passion stands for all, the most indulged.
The scenes wherein he plays his part are life,
A sphere whose centre is co-heavenly
With its divine original and end.
Like life, too, as a whole, the story hath
A moral, and each scene one, as in life—
One universal and peculiar truth—
Shining upon it like the quiet moon,
Illustrating the obscure unequal earth;—
And though these scenes may seem to careless eyes
Irregular and rough and unconnected,
Like to the stones at Stonehenge—though convolved,
And in primeval mystery—still an use,
A meaning, and a purpose may be marked
Among them of a temple reared to God:—
The meaning alway dwelling in the word,
In secret sanctity, like a golden toy
Mid Beauty’s orbed bosom. Scenes of earth
And Heaven are mixed, as flesh and soul in man.

Now, the religion of the book is this,
Followed out from the book God writ of old.
All creatures being faulty by their nature,
And by God made all liable to sin,
God only could atone—and unto none
Except Himself—for universal sin.
It is thus that God did sacrifice to God,
Himself unto Himself, in the great way
Of Triune mystery. His death, as man,
Was real as our own; and as, except
In the destruction of all life, there could
Be no atonement for its sin, while life
Doth necessarily result from God,
As thought and outward action from ourselves,
So the atonement must be to and by Him;
Which makes it justice equally with love;
For all His powers and attributes are equal,
And must make one in any act of His;
And every act of God is infinite.
He acts through all in all: the truth we know,
He doth Himself inbreathe; the ill we do,
He hath atoned for; and the scriptures show
That God doth suffer for the sins of those
Whom He hath made, that are liable to sin.
In all of us He hath His agony;
We are the cross, and death of God, and grave.
Him love then all the more, and worship Him
Who lived and died, and rose from death for us,
And is and reigns forever God in all.
Let each man think himself an act of God,
His mind a thought, his life a breath of God;
And let each try, by great thoughts and good deeds,
To show the most of Heaven he hath in him.

Many who read the word of life, much doubt
Whether salvation be of grace or faith,
Election, or repentance, or good works,
Or God’s high will: reconcile all of them.
Each of the persons of the Triune God
Hath had His dispensation, hath it now;
The Father by His prophets, and the Son
In His own days, by His own deeds; and now
The Spirit, by the ministry of Christ;
And thus, by law, by gospel, and by grace,
The scheme of God’s salvation is complete.
Salvation, then, is God-like, threefold; so
That under one or other, all may come;
By will of God alone, by faith in Christ,
And by repentance, and good works, and grace.
So there is one salvation of the Father,
One of the Son, another of the Spirit;
Each, the salvation of the Three in One.
The mortal in this lay is saved of will,
In manner as this hymn unfolds, which hath
Just warranty for every word from God’s.

O God! Thou wondrous One in Three,
As mortals must Thee deem;
Thou only canst be said to be,
We but at best to seem.
For Thou dost save, and Thou may’st slay,
Const make a mortal soul
In Thee eternal; in a day
Wilt bring to nought the whole.

Thou hardenest, and Thou openest hearts,
As in Thy Word is shown;
Thou safest and destroyest parts,
By Thy right will alone.
Let down Thy grace, then, Lord! on all
Whom Thou wilt save to live;
Oh! if they stumble, stop their fall!
Oh! if they fall, forgive!

They are forgiven from the first,
They are predestined Thine;
And though in sin they were the worst,
In Thee they are divine.
They are, and were, and will be, Lord!
In one, in Heaven, in Thee,
Yea with the Spirit, and the Word,
One God in Trinity.

These principles and doctrines pending not
Upon the action of the poem here,
But over and above it, influencing
Nevertheless the story, as the course
Of stars enwoven with our system, earth,
Vary the view of this life’s hemisphere,
And mingle it more palpably with Heaven,
And with its changeless, ceaseless, boundless God.
It is thus that by creating to and from
Eternity, and multiplying ever
His own one Being through the universe,
He doth eternize happiness, and make
Good infinite by making all in Him.
There is but one great right and good; and ill
And wrong are shades thereof, not substances.
Nothing can be antagonist to God.

Necessity, like electricity,
Is in ourselves and all things, and no more
Without us than within us; and we live,
We of this mortal mixture, in the same law
As the pure colourless intelligence
Which dwells in Heaven, and the dead Hadëan shades.
We will and act and talk of liberty;
And all our wills and all our doings both
Are limited within this little life.
Free will is but necessity in play—
The clattering of the golden reins which guide
The thunder-footed coursers of the sun.
The ship which goes to sea informed with fire—
Obeying only its own iron force,
Reckless of adverse tide, breeze dead, or weak
As infant’s parting breath, too faint to stir
The feather held before it—is as much
The appointed thrall of all the elements,
As the white-bosomed bark which wooes the wind,
And when it dies desists. And thus with man;
However contrary he set his heart
To God, he is but working out His will;
And, at an infinite angle, more or less
Obeying his own soul’s necessity.
He only hath freewill whose will is fate.

Evil and good are God’s right hand and left.
By ministry of evil good is clear,
And by temptation virtue; as of yore
Out of the grave rose God. Let this be deemed
Enough to justify the portion weighed
To the great spirit Evil, named herein.
If evil seem the most, yet good most is:
As water may be deep and pure below
Although the face be filmy for a time.
And if the spirit of evil seem more in
The work than God, it is but to work His will,
Who therefore is all that the, other seems.
And evil is in almost every scene
Of life more or less forward. Above all
The mystery of the Trinity is held,
Whose mystery is its reasonableness.
All that is said of Deity is said
In love and reverence. Be it so conceived.
What comes before and after the great world—
Deep in the secretest abyss of Light,
And Being’s most reserved immensity—
God alone knows eternally, who rends
The mantling Heavens with his hands; but with
The present is communion creatural:
He liveth in the sacrament of life.
And for the soul of man delineate here—
The outline half invisible—is shown
The self-sought grace, the self-aspiring truth
And natural religion of the heart
Contrasting Godhood with humanity
Ever; whereas the Spirit aye unites.
Temptation, and its workings in the heart
Whose faint and false resistance but assists—
Ambition, thirst of secret lore, joy, love—
Riverlike, doubling sometimes on itself—
Adventure, pleasure, travel heavenly
And earthly, friendship, passion, poesie,
Viewed ever in their spiritual end—
And power, celestial happiness and earth’s
Millenial foretaste, ill annihilate,
The restoration of the angels lost,
And one salvation universal given
To all create—all these, related, form,
With much beside, the body of the work:—
The islands, seas, and mainland of its orb.

Thus much then for this book. It aims to mark
The various belief as well as doubts
Which hold or search by turns the mind of youth
Unresting anywhere. Its heresies,
If such they be, are charitable ones;—
For they who read not in the blest belief
That all souls may be saved, read to no end.
We were made to be saved. We are of God.
Nor bates the book one tittle of the truth,
To smoothe its way to favour with the fearful.

All rests with those who read. A work or thought
Is what each makes it to himself, and may
Be full of great dark meanings, like the sea,
With shoals of life rushing; or like the air,
Benighted with the wing of the wild dove,
Sweepng miles broad o’er the far western woods,
With mighty glimpses of the central light—
Or may be nothing—bodiless, spiritless.

Now therefore to his work and to the world
The writer bids, God speed! It matters not
If they agree or differ. Each perchance
May bear true witness to another end.
Let then what hath been, be. It boots not here
To palliate misdoings. ’Twere less toil
To build Colossus than to hew a hill
Into a statue. Hail and farewell, all!

I

Scene—Heaven.

God |

Eternity hath snowed its years upon them;
And the white winter of their age is come,
The World and all its worlds; and all shall end.

Seraphim |

God! God! God!
As flames in skies
We burn and rise
And lose ourselves in Thee!
Years on years!
And nought appears
Save God to be.
God! God! God!
To us no thought
Hath Being brought
Toward Thee that doth not move!
Years on years!
And what appears
Save God to love?
God! God! God!
All Thou dost make
Lies like a lake
Below Thine infinite eye:
Years on years!
And all appears
Save God to die.

Cherubim |

As sun and star,
How high or far,
Show but a boundless sky;
So creature mind
Is all confined
To show Thee, God, most High!
The sun still burns,
The sun still turns
Bound, round himself and round;
So creature mind
To self’s confined,
But Thou God hast no bound!
Systems arise.
Or a world dies,
Each constant hour in air;
But creature mind,
In Heaven confined,
Lives on like Thee, God! there.

Seraphim
Cherubim |

God! God! God!
Thou fill’st our eyes
A were the skies
One burning, boundless sun!
While creature mind,
In path confined,
Passeth a spot thereon.
God! God! God!

Lucifer |

Ye thrones of Heaven, how bright, how pure ye are!
How have ye brightened since I saw ye first!
How have I darkened since ye saw me last!
What is the dark abyss of fire, and what
The ravenous heights of air, o’er which I reign,
In agony of glory, to these seats?
The loathsome cavern of the oracle,
O’er which ye rise in templed majesty,
Filled with the incense of all worshippers,
And echoing with the eloquence of God,
Which rolls in sunny clouds around the heavens.
Yet must I work through world and life my fate;
And winding through the wards of human hearts,
Steal their incarnate strength. Death does his work
In secret and in joy intense, untold,
As though an earthquake smacked its mumbling lips
O’er some thick peopled city. But for me,
Exists nor peace nor pleasure, even here,
Where all beside, the very faintest thought,
Is rapture. I will speak to God as erst.
Father of spirit, as the sun of air!
Beginning of all ends, and end of all
Beginnings, throughout whole Eternity;
From whom Eternity and every power
Perfect, and pure cause, is and emanates!
Originator without origin!
End without end! Creator of all ages,
And sabbath of all Being; who hast made
All numbers sacred, who art all and one!
At whose right hand the wisdom of all worlds
Combined, is only fearful foolishness
Or inarticulate madness—and Thou, Lord!
Maker and Perfecter of all, the one!
Being above all Being, God the Life!
Who art the way whereon the world proceeds
From God, all-making, and whereby returns
The ever generated universe!—
Who rulest all worlds in the law of light,
Thy nature and their own; who art before
All ages, angels, blessed, times and worlds!
Word that in every world art safe to save
All souls, impregned with spirit, God-begot!
And Thou eternal spirit-Deity!
The sanctifier of the universe!
Being, and Life, and spirit, who dost make,
Destroyest, recreatest, makest God!
God one and Trine! Thou seest me here again;
Still, sunlike, though eclipsed, of blinding power
And fiery cause, and everness of ill;
Behold I bow before Thee; hear Thou me!

God |

What wouldst thou, Lucifer?

Lucifer |

There is a youth
Among the sons of men I fain would have
Given up wholly to me.

God |

He is thine,
To tempt

Lucifer |

I thank Thee, Lord!

God |

Upon his soul
Thou hast no power. All souls are mine for aye.
And I do give thee leave to this that he
May know my love is more than all his sin,
And prove unto himself that nought but God
Can satisfy the soul He maketh great.

Lucifer |

Thou God art all in one! Thy infinite
Bounds Being. Thou hast said the world shall end.
The world is perfect, as concerns itself,
And all its parts and ends; not as towards Thee.
So man is Likest and unlikest God,
Of all existence; therefore doth as much
Resemble Thee as any act a mind.
In him of whom I ask, I seek once more
To tempt the living world, and then depart.

The Holy Ghost |

And I will hallow him to the ends of Heaven,
That though he plunge his soul in sin like a sword
In water, it shall nowise ding to him.
He is of Heaven. All things are known in Heaven,
Ere aimed at upon earth. The child is chosen.

Saints |

Another soul
The Holy one
Hath chosen out of earth;
And there is none
Throughout the whole
Like worthy of his birth.

Guardian Angel |

Oh! who hath joy like mine? was I not here
When from Thy boundless bosom, as a star
Out of the air, that soul was kindled, Lord!
And given to me to guard and guide—while both,
Mid starry strains out of the depths of Heaven,
Fell at Thy feet in worship?—joy of joys!
To you, ye saints and angels, let me speak;
For ye I see rejoice with me. Ye know
What ’tis to triumph o’er temptation, what
To fall before it; how the young spirit faints—
The virgin tremor, the heart’s ebb and flow,
When first some vast temptation calmly comes
And states itself before it, like the sun
Low looming in the west, above the wave
Of wimpling streamlet, ere its waters grow
To size aortal. Than the Fiend himself
There is no greater evil. Less the shame
Of yielding, more the glory of conquering,
In him, to whom he goes, this soul elect.
From infancy through childhood, up to youth,
Have I this soul attended; marked him blest
With all the sweet and sacred ties of life;—
The prayerful love of parents, pride of friends,
Prosperity, and health and ease, the aids
Of learning, social converse with the good
And gifted, and his heart all-lit with love,
Like to the rolling sea with living light;—
Hopeful and generous and earnest; rich
In commune with high spirits, loving truth
And wisdom for their own divinest selves:
Tracking the deeds of the world’s glory, or
Conning the words of wisdom, Heaven-inspired,
As on the soul, in pure effectual ray,
The bright, transparent atoms, thought by thought,
Fall fixed for evermore. And thus his days,
Through sunny noon, or mooned eve, or night
Star-armied, shining through the deathless air,
All radiantly elapsed, in good or joy.
All this, for long, I marked. There grew, at length,
A change within his spirit; and I feared
A fatal and a final fall from good.
God’s love seemed lost upon him. He became
Heart-deadened. Watching, warning, vain, I fled
Hither to intercede with God our Lord,
To bless him with salvation. We may plead
Alway for those we love, by leave divine.
Nor knew I till this moment, with all Heaven,
That, in the righteous providence of God,
That soul was saved. Thou knowest, Lord! the mould
Of mortals, and the infinite end whereto
The souls Thou savest are predestinate;
Oh! be Thy mercy mighty to this soul,
Fiend-threatened; nor permit him who presides
O’er Hell’s eternal holocaust, too far
To tempt or tamper with the heart of man!—

God |

My mercy doth outstretch the universe;
Shall it not be sufficient for one soul?

Lucifer |

I am the wrath of God unto myself,
And made by Him to do my part Do thou
Thine! they are far enough apart I ween.

Guardian Angel |

The heaven-strung chords of man’s immortal soul
Are not for thee to wither at thy will.
Bear witness, all ye blessed, to the word;—
Angels, intelligences, sons of God!
Ye who know nought but truth, feel nought but love,
Will nought but bliss, do nought but righteousness!
Whose life was ere the Heavens were conceived,
The stars begotten, or the ages born;
Ye many ordered hierarchies, which are
The love, truth, justice, majesty and might,
Dominion, glory, wisdom, bliss of God;
Ye through whose ministry of mercy—His
Immediate, ever instant, active, all
Spirits and worlds are governed—age by age
Gazing and gaining glory; ye who stand,
Stirless, before the throne, entranced in joy;
Or ye, whose life is to present all souls
Reborn to their Creator; or to search
The golden globed skies for deeds of grace;
And ye who move all Heavens, in whose names
The name of God is, as in angels’ all;
The crown, the wisdom, the intelligence,
Kindness, and strength and beauty, splendour, worth,
Original and rule; and ye who move
Restless around the throne, the burning seven,
The virtue, power, salvation, fire and rest,
Blessing and praise of God; and ye who rule
Regions or kingdoms, states, tribes, families,
Ages and times, and seasons, and events;
Systems and elements, material powers,
Mental and spiritual; or ye who bear
Souls from the heaven to earth, from earth to heaven;
Ye tenants of the archetypal worlds
And spiritual spheres; and you, ye saints!
Freed once on earth into the liberty
Of the necessity which is of God;
Yours are the many multitudes of stars,
And bliss and power for ever, ye are gods!
And live an endless life, bespoken here;
Bear witness, all, that happiness succeeds
To godliness; and that, despite of sin,
The world may recognise in all time’s scenes,
Though belts of clouds bar half its burning disk,
The overruling, overthrowing power,
Which by our creature purposes works out
Its deeds, and by our deeds its purposes.

Lucifer |

God! for thy glory only can I act,
And for thy creatures’ good. When creatures stray
Farthest from Thee, then warmest towards them burns
Thy love, even as yon sun beams hotliest on
The earth when distant most.

God |

The earth whereon
He dwells, this grain selected from the sands
Of life, dies with him.

Lucifer |

God! I go to do
Thy will.

God |

Thou, too, who watchest o’er the world
Whose end I fix, prepare to have it judged.

Angel of Earth |

Let me not then have watched o’er it in vain.
From age to age, from hour to hour I still
Have hoped it would grow better—hope so now;
’Tis better than it once was, and hath more
Of mind and freedom than it ever had.
I love it more than ever. Thou didst give
It to me as a child. To me earth is
Even as the boundless universe to Thee;
Nay, more! for Thou couldst make another. It is
My world. Take it not from me Lord! Thou, Christ!
Mad’st it the altar where thou offeredst up
Thyself for the creation. Let it be
Immortal as Thy love. And altars are
Holy; and sister angels, sister orbs
Hail it afar as such. Oh! I have heard
World question world and answer; seen them weep
Each other if eclipsed for one red hour,
And of all worlds most generous was mine,
The tenderest and the fairest.

Lucifer |

Knowest thou not
God’s son to be the brother and the friend
Of spirit everywhere? Or hath thy soul
Been bound for ever to thy foolish world?

Angel |

Star unto star speaks light, and world to world
Repeats the password of the universe
To God; the name of Chrifet—the one great word
Well worth all languages in earth or Heaven.

Son of God |

Think not I lived and died for thine alone,
And that no other sphere hath hailed me Christ.
My life is ever suffering for love.
In judging and redeeming worlds is spent
Mine everlasting being.

Lucifer |

Earth he next
Will judge; for so saith God.

Angel of Earth |

Be it not, Lord!
Thou art a God of goodness and of love;
He is the evil of the universe,
And loveth not the earth, Thy Son, nor Thee.
Thou knowest best.

Lucifer |

Behold now all yon worlds!
The space each fills shall be its successor.
Accept the consolation!

Angel of Earth |

Earth! oh, Earth!

Lucifer |

’Tis earth shall lead destruction; she shall end.
The stars shall wonder why she comes no more
On her accustomed orbit, and the sun
Miss one of his eleven of light; the moon,
An orphan orb, shall seek for earth for aye,
Through time’s untrodden depths and find her not;
No more shall morn, out of the holy east,
Stream o’er the amber air her level light;
Nor evening, with the spectral fingers, draw
Her tar-sprent curtain round the head of earth;
Her footsteps never thence again shall grace
The blue sublime of heaven. Her grave is dug.
I see the stars, night-clad, all gathering
In long and dark procession. Death’s at work.
And, one by one, shall all yon wandering worlds,
Whether in orbed path they roll, or trail,
In an inestimable length of light,
Their golden train of tresses after them,
Cease; and the sun, centre and sire of light,
The keystone of the world-built arch of heaven
Be left in burning solitude. The stars,
Which stand as thick as dewdrops on the fields
Of heaven, and all they comprehend, shall pass.
The spirits of all worlds shall all depart
To their great destinies; and thou and I,
Greater in grief than worlds, shall live as now.
In hell’s dark annals there is something writ,
Which shall amaze man yet There! to thy earth!

Angel of Earth |

There is a blind world, yet unlit by God,
Rolling around the extremest edge of light;
Where all things are disaster and decay,
The outcast of all being; no one thing
Fitting another: that is fit for thee.
Be that thy world I but not the living earth.
Stretch forth Thy shining shield, oh God! the heavens,
Over the prostrate earth, an armed friend,
And save her from the swift and violent hell
Her beauty hath enchanted! from the wrath
Of love like his, oh save her, though by death!

God |

Destruction and salvation are the hands
Upon the face of time. When both unite,
The day of death dawns. Every orb exists
Unto its preappointed end: and earth,
My creature, the elect of worlds, ere all
Is saved. The world shall perish as a worm
Upon destruction’s path; the universe
Evanish like a ghost before the sun,
Yea like a doubt before the truth of God,
Yet nothing more than death shall perish. Then,
Rejoice ye souls of God, regenerate,
Ye indwellers divine of Deity;
In Him ye are immortal as Himself!

Son of God |

O’er all things are eternity and change,
And special predilection of our God.
Thou who createst souls, as the sun clouds,
Out of the sea of spirit, sire of both
The first and second natures of Thy Son,
In whom the maker and the made make one,
Deific spirit! who in every world
Payeth creation’s penalties; in all,
Is heir of God and nature, and in Thee,
And in self-worship, Deifies himself!
And you blest spirits for whom I died, for whom,
Forefated, fore-atoned for from the first,
All heaven reserves the fullness of its bliss;
Creator and created! witness, both,
How I have loved ye, as God-natured life
Alone can love and suffer! Let the earth
And every orb, the offspring of all air,
Perish; but all I die for, live for me.

God |

The earth shall not be when her sabbath ends,
In the high close of order.

Lucifer |

Heaven, farewell!
Hell is more bearable than nothingness.

Thrones |

Thou, God, art Lord of mercy! and Thy thoughts
Are high above the star-dust of the world!

Dominations |

Yet o’er the meanest atom reignest Thou
Omnipotent, as o’er the universe!

Powers |

Thy might is self-creative, and Thy works,
Immortal, temporal, destructible,
Are ever in Thy sight and blessed there!
The heavens are Thy bosom, and Thine eye
Is high o’er all existence; yea the worlds
Are but Thy shining foot-prints upon space!

Princedoms |

Eternal Lord! Thy strength compels the worlds,
And bows the heads of ages; at Thy voice
Their unsubstantial essence wears away.

Virtues |

All-favouring God! we glory but in Thee.
Ye Heavens exalt, expand yourselves! they come,
The infinite generations, all Divine,
Of Deity, our brethren and our friends!

Archangels |

Thou who hast thousand names, as night hath stars,
Which light Thee up to eye create, yet not
One thousandth part illumine Thy boundlessness,
Nor that abyss of Being ’midst of which
Thy countless wonders constellate themselves;
Thy light, the light we dwell in shall at last
Fulfil the universe, and all be bliss;
The consummation of all ages come.
We praise Thee for Thy mercies, and for this,
The first, and last, and greatest of all boons.

Angels |

Thee God! we praise
Through our ne’er sunsetting days,
And Thy just ways,
Divine:
In Thy hand is every spirit,
And the meed the same may merit;
All which all the worlds inherit
Are Thine!
It is not unto creatures given
To scale the purposes of Heaven,
Alway just and kind;
But before Thy mighty breath,
Life and spirit, dust and death,
The boundless All is driven,
Like clouds by wind.

Angel of Earth |

Woe! woe at last in Heaven!
Earth to death is given;
The ends of things hang still
Over them as a sky;
Do what we will,
All’s for eternity!

II

Scene—Wood and water—Sunset.

Festus, alone.
Festus |

This is to be a mortal and immortal!
To live within a circle—and to be
That dark point where the shades of all things around
Meet, mix and deepen. All things unto me
Shew their dark sides! somewhere there must be light.
Oh! I feel like a seed in the cold earth;
Quickening at heart, and pining for the air!
Passion is destiny. The heart is its own
Fate. It is well youth’s gold rubs off so soon.
The heart gets dizzy with its drunken dance,
And the voluptuous vanities of life
Enchain, enchant, and cheat my soul no more.
My spirit is on edge. I can enjoy
Nought which has not the honied sting of sin;
That soothing fret which makes the young untried,
Longing to be beforehand with their nature,
In dreams and loneness cry, they die to live;
That wanton whetting of the soul, which while
It gives a finer, keener edge for pleasure,
Wastes more and dulls the sooner. Rouse thee, heart;
Bow of my life thou yet art full of spring!
My quiver still hath many purposes.
Yet what is worth a thought of all things here?
How mean, how miserable every care!
How doubtful, too, the system of the mind!
And then the ceaseless, changeless, hopeless round
Of weariness and heartlessness and woe
And vice and vanity! Yet these make life;
The life at least I witness if not feel.
No matter! we are immortal. How I wish
I could love men! for amid all life’s quests
There seems but worthy one—to do men good.
It matters not how long we live but how.
For as the parts of one manhood while here
We live in every age: we think and feel
And feed upon the coming and the gone
As much as on the now time. Man is one:
And he hath one great heart. It is thus we feel,
With a gigantic throb athwart the sea,
Each others’ rights and wrongs; thus are we men.
Let us think less of men and more of God!
Sometimes the thought comes swiftening over us,
Like a small bird winging the still blue air;
And then again, at other times, it rises
Slow, like a cloud which scales the skies all breathless,
And just over head lets itself down on us.
Sometimes we feel the wish across the mind
Rush, like a rocket tearing up the sky,
That we should join with God and give the world
The slip: but while we wish, the world turns round,
And peeps us in the face—the wanton world;
We feel it gently pressing down our arm—
The arm we had raised to do for truth such wonders;
We feel it softly bearing on our side—
We feel it touch and thrill us through the body—
And we are fools and there’s an end of us.
’Tis a fine thought that sometime end we must.
There sets the sun of suns! dies in all fire,
Like Asher’s death-great monarch. God of might!
We love and live on power. It is spirit’s end.
Mind must subdue. To conquer is its life.
Why mad’st Thou not one spirit, like the sun,
To king the world? And oh! might I have been
That sun-mind, how I would have warmed the world
To love and worship and bright life!

Lucifer |

Suddenly appearing.

Not thou!
Hadst thou more power die more wouldst thou misuse.

Festus |

Who art thou, pray? I saw thee not before.
It seems as thou hadst grown out of the air.

Lucifer |

Thou knowest me well. Though stranger to thine eye,
I am not to thy heart.

Festus |

I know thee not.

Lucifer |

Come nearer! Look on me! I am above thee;
Beneath thee, and around thee, and before thee.

Festus |

Why, art thou all things, or dost go through all?
A spirit, or embodied blast of air?
I feel thou art a spirit.

Lucifer |

Yea I am.

Festus |

I knew it! I am glad, yet tremble so.
What hours upon hours have I longed for this,
And hoped that thought or prayer might produce!
I have besought the stars, with tears, to send
A power unto me; and have set the clouds
Until I thought I saw one coming: but
The shadowy giant alway thinned away,
And I was fated unimmortalized.
What shall I do? Oh! let me kneel to thee!

Lucifer |

Nay, rise! and I’ll not say, for thine own sake,
That thou dost pray in private to the Devil.

Festus |

Father of lies thou liest!

Lucifer |

I am he!
It is enough to make the Devil merry,
To think that men call on me momently,
Deeming me ever dungeoned fast in Hell;
Swearers and swaggerers jeer at my name;
And oft indeed it is a special jest
With witling gallants. Let me once appear!
Woe’s me! they faint and shudder—pale and pray;
The burning oath which quivered on the lip,
Starts back and sears and blisters up the tongue;
Confusion ransacks the abandoned heart,
Quells the bold blood, and o’er the vaulted brow
Slips the white woman-hand. To judgment, ho!
The very pivot of the earth seems snapped;
And down they drop like ruins to repent.
Such be the bravery of mighty man!

Festus |

I must be mad; or mine eye cheats my brain;
And this strange phantom comes from overthought,
Like the white lightning from a day too hot.
It must be so. But I will pass it.

Lucifer |

Stay!

Festus |

Oh save me God! He is reality!

Lucifer |

And now thou kneel’st to Heaven. Fye, graceless boy!
Mocking thy Maker with a cast-off prayer;
For had not I the first fruits of thy faith?

Festus |

Tempter, away! From all the crowds of life
Why single me? Why score the young green bole
For fellage? Go! Am I the youngest, worst?
No! Light the fires of hell with other souls;
Mine shall not burn with thee.

Lucifer |

Thou judgest harshly.
Can I not touch thee without slaying thee?

Festus |

Why art thou here? What wouldst thou have with me?

Lucifer |

’Fore all I would have gentle words and looks.

Festus |

I pray thee, go!

Lucifer |

I cannot quit thee yet.
But why so sad? Wilt kneel to me again?
This leafy closet is most apt for prayer.

Festus |

Yes; I will pray for thee and for myself.

Lucifer |

Waste not thy prayers! I scatter them: they reach
No further than thy breath—a yard or so.
And as for me, I heed them, need them not.
My nature God knows and hath fixed; and He
Recks little of the manners of the world;
Wicked He holdeth it and unrepentant.

Festus |

Therefore the more some ought to pray.

Lucifer |

To blow
A kiss, a bubble and a prayer hath like
Effect and satisfaction.

Festus |

Let me hence!
Go tell thy blasphemies and lies elsewhere.
Thou scatter prayer! Make me Thy minister
One moment God! that I may rid the world
For ever of its evil. Oh! Thine arm!

Lucifer |

Canst rid thyself?

Festus |

Alas no. Get thee gone!
Can nought insult thee nor provoke thy flight?

Lucifer |

I laugh alike at ruin and redemption.
I am the one which knows nor hope nor fear;
Which ne’er knew good nor e’er can know the worst.
What thinkest thou can anger me, or harm?

Festus |

Wherefore didst thou quit Hell? To drag me there?

Lucifer |

Thou wilt not guess mine errand. Deem’st thou aught
Which God hath made all evil? Me He made.
Oft I do good; and thee to serve I come.

Festus |

Did I not hear thee boast with thy last breath
Not to have known what good was?

Lucifer |

From myself
I know it not; yet God’s will I must work.
I come I say to serve thee.

Festus |

Well! I would
Thou never hadst: but speak thy purpose straight.

Lucifer |

I heard thy prayer at sunset. I was here.
I saw, thy secret longings, unsaid thoughts,
Which prey upon the breast like night-fires on
A heath. I know thy heart by heart. I read
The tongue when still as well as when it moves.
And thou didst pray to God. Did He attend?
Or turn His eye from the great glass of things,
Wherein He worshippeth eternally
Himself, to thee one moment? He did not.
I tell thee nought He cares for men. I came
And come to proffer thee the earth; to set
Thee on a throne—the throne of will unbound—
To crown thy life with liberty and joy,
And make thee free and mighty even as I am!

Festus |

I would not be as thou art for Hell’s throne;
Add Earth’s—add Heaven’s!

Lucifer |

I knew thy proud high heart.
To test its worth and mark I held it brave,
In shape and being thus myself I came;
Not in disguise of opportunity—
Not as some silly toy which serves for most—
Not in the mask of lucre, lust nor power—
Not in a goblin size nor cherub form—
But as the soul of Hell and evil came I
With leave to give the kingdom of the world—
Hie freedom of thyself.

Festus |

Good; prove thy powers.

Lucifer |

Do I not prove them? Who but I, that have
Immortal might o’er mine own mind, and o’er
All hearts and spirits of the living world,
Would share it with another, or forgo,
One hour, the great enjoyment of the whole?
And who but I give men what each loves best?

Festus |

Open the Heavens and let me look on God!
Open my heart and let me see myself!
Then I’ll believe thee.

Lucifer |

Thou shalt not believe
For that I give thee, hut for that I am.
Believe me first; then I will prove myself.
Though sick I know thee of the joys of sense,
Yet those thou lovest most I will make pure,
And render worthy of thy love; unfilm them,
That so thou mayst not dally with the blind.
Thou shalt possess them to their very souls.
Pleasure and love and unimagined beauty;
All, all that be delicious, brilliant, great,
Of worldly things are mine, and mine to give.

Festus |

What can be counted pleasure after love?
Like the young lion which hath once lapped blood,
The heart can ne’er be coaxed back to aught else.

Lucifer |

I will sublime it for thee all to bliss:
As yet it hath but made thee wretched.

Festus |

Spirit,
It is not bliss I seek; I care not for it.
I am above the low delights of life.
The life I live is in a dark cold cavern,
Where I wander up and down, feeling for something
Which is to be—and must be—what, I know not;
But the incarnation of my destiny
Is nigh.

Lucifer |

It is thy fate which weighs upon thee
Necessity sits on humanity,
Like to the world on Atlas neck. ’Tis this,
And the sultry sense of overdrawn life.

Festus |

True;
The worm of the world hath eaten out my heart.

Lucifer |

I will renew it in thee. It shall be
The bosom favourite of every beauty,
Even like a rosebud. Thou shalt render happy,
By naming who may love thee. Come with me.

Festus |

I have a love on earth, and one in Heaven.

Lucifer |

Thou shalt love ten as others love but one!

Festus |

Oh! I was glad when something in me said
Come, let us worship beauty! and I bowed;
And went about to find a shrine; but found
None that my soul, when seeing, said enough, to.
Many I met with where I put up prayers,
And had them more than answered; and at such
I worshipped, partly because others did;
Partly because I could not help myself.
But none of these were for me; and away
I went champing and choking in proud pain;
In a burning wrath that not a sea could slake.
So I betook me to the sounding sea;
And overheard its slumberous mutterings
Of a revenge on man; whereat almost
I gladdened, for I felt savage as the sea.
I had only one thing to behold, the sea;
I had only one thing to believe, I loved;
Until that lonesome sameness grew sublime
And darkly beautiful as death, when some
Bright soul regains its star-home, or as Heaven
Just when the stars falter forth, one by one,
Like the first words of love from a maiden’s lips.
There are points from which we can command our life;
When the soul sweeps the future like a glass;
And coming things, full freighted with our fate,
Jut out, dark, on the offing of the mind.
Let them come! Many will go down in sight;
In the billow’s joyous dash of death go down.
At last came love; not whence I sought nor thought it;
As on a ruined and bewildered wight
Rises the roof he meant to have lost for ever.
On came the living vessel of all love;
Terrible in its beauty as a serpent,
Rode down upon me like a ship full sail
And bearing me before it, kept me up
Spite of the drowning speed at which we drave
On, on, until we sank both. Was not this love?

Lucifer |

Why, how can I tell? I am not in love;
But I have oft times heard mine angels call
Most piteously on their lost loves in Heaven;
And, as I suffer, I have seen them come;
Seen starlike faces peep between the clouds,
And Hell become a tolerable torment.
Some souls lose all things but the love of beauty;
And by that love they are redeemable;
For in love and beauty they acknowledge good;
And good is God—the great Necessity.
I have not told thee half I will do for thee.
All secrets thou shalt ken—all mysteries construe;
At nothing marvel. All the veins which stretch,
Unsearchable by human eyes, of lore
Most precious, most profound, to thine shall bare
And vulgar lie like dust. The world within,
The world above thee, and the dark domain,
Mine own thou shalt o’er rule; and he alone
Who rightly can esteem such high delights,
He only merits—he alone shall have.

Festus |

And if I have shall I be happier?
What is pleasure? What, happiness?

Lucifer |

It is that
I vouchsafe to thee.

Festus |

Am I tempted thus
Unto my fall?

Lucifer |

God wills or lets it be.
How thinkest thou?

Festus |

That I will go with thee.

Lucifer |

From God I come.

Festus |

I do believe thee, spirit.
He will not let thee harm me. Him I love,
And thee I fear not. I Obey Him.

Lucifer |

Good.
Both time and case are urgent. Come away!

Festus |

Give me a breathing-time to fortify,
Within myself, the promise I have made.

Lucifer |

Expect me, then, at midnight, here. Remember,
That thou canst any time repent.

Festus |

Ay, true. Goes.

Lucifer |

Repentance never yet did aught on earth;
It undoes many good things. Of all men,
Heaven shield me from the wretch who can repent!

III

Scene—Water and wood—Midnight;

Festus, alone.
Festus |

All things are calm, and fair, and passive. Earth
Looks as if lulled upon an angel’s lap
Into a breathless dewy sleep: so still,
That we can only say of things, they be!
The lakelet now, no longer vexed with gusts,
Replaces on her breast the pictured moon
Pearled round with stars. Sweet imaged scene of time
To come, perchance, when this vain life o’erspent,
Earth may some purer beings’ presence bear;
Mayhap even God may walk among His saints,
In eminence and brightness like yon moon,
Mildly outbeaming all the beads of light
Strung o’er night’s proud dark brow. How strangely fair
Yon round still star, which looks half suffering from,
And half rejoicing in its own strong fire;
Making itself a lonelihood of light,
Like Deity, where’er in Heaven it dwells.
How can the beauty of material things
So win the heart and work upon the mind,
Unless like-natured with them? Are great things
And thoughts of the same blood? They have like effect.

Lucifer |

Why doubt on mind? What matter how we call
That which all feel to be their noblest part?
Even spirits have a better and a worse:
For every thing created must have form.
Passions they have, somewhat like thine; but less
Of grossness and that downwardness of soul
Which men have. It is true they have no earth;
For what they live on is above themselves.

Festus |

There seems a sameness among things; for mind
And matter speak, in causes, of one God.
The inward and the outward worlds are like;
The pure and gross but differ in degree.
Tears, feeling’s bright embodied form, are not
More pure than dewdrops, Nature’s tears, which she
Sheds in her own breast for the fair which die.
The sun insists on gladness; but at night,
When he is gone, poor Nature loves to weep.

Lucifer |

There is less real difference among things
Than men imagine. They overlook the mass,
But fasten each on some particular crumb,
Because they feel that they can equal that,
Of doctrine, or belief, or party cause.

Festus |

That is the madness of the world—and that
Would I remove.

Lucifer |

It is imbecility,
Not madness.

Festus |

Oh! the brave and good who serve
A worthy cause can only one way fail;
By perishing therein. Is it to fail?
No; every great or good man’s death is a step
Firm set towards their end—the end of being;
Which is the good of all and love of God.
The world must have great minds, even as great spheres
Or suns, to govern lesser restless minds,
While they stand still and burn with life; to keep
Them in their places, and to light and heat them.
If I desire immortal life for aught,
It is to learn the mystery of mind
And somewhat more of God. Let others rule
Systems or succour saints, if such things please;
To live like light or die in light like dew,
Either! I should be blest.

Lucifer |

It may not be.
For as we do not see the sun himself,
It is but the light about him, like a ring
Of glory round the forehead of a saint, so
God thou wilt never see. His unveiled love
Were terrible, too mud for man to meet.

Festus |

Men have a claim on God; and none who hath
A heart of kindness, reverence and love,
But dare look God in the face and ask His smile.
He dwells in no fierce light—no cloud of flame;
And if it were, Faith’s eye can look through Hell,
And through the solid world. We must all think
On God. Yon water must reflect the sky.
Midnight! Day hath too much light for us,
To see things spiritually. Mind and Night
Will meet, though in silence, like forbidden lovers,
With whom to see each other’s sacred form
Must satisfy. The stillness of deep bliss,
Sound as the silence of the high hill-top
Where thunder finds no echo—like God’s voice
Upon the worldling’s proud, cold, rocky heart—
Fills full the sky; and the eye shares with Heaven
That look, so like to feeling, which the bright
And glorious things of Nature ever wear.
There is much to think and feel of things beyond
This earth; which lie, as we deem, upwards—far
From the day’s glare and riot—they are Night’s!
Oh! could we lift the future’s sable shroud!

Lucifer |

Behind a shroud what shouldst thou see but death?

Festus |

Spirit is like the thread whereon are strung
The beads or worlds of life. It may be here,
It may be there that I shall live again;
In yon strange world whose long nights know no star,
But seven fair maidlike moons attending him
Perfect his sky—perchance in one of those—
But live again I shall wherever it be.
We long to learn the future—love to guess.

Lucifer |

The science of the future is to man,
But what the shadow of the wind might be.
Such thoughts are vain and useless.

Festus |

Forced oh us.

Lucifer |

All things are of necessity.

Festus |

Then best.
But the good are never fatalists. The bad
Alone act by necessity, they say.

Lucifer |

It matters not what men assume to be;
Or good, or bad, they are but what they are.

Festus |

What is necessity? Are we, and thou,
And all the worlds, and the whole infinite
We cannot see, but working out God’s thoughts?
And have we no self-action? Are all God?

Lucifer |

Then hath He sin and all absurdity.

Festus |

Yet, if created Being have free-will,
Is it not wrong to judge it may traverse
God’s own high will, and yet impossible
To think on’t otherwise?

Lucifer |

It may be so.
All creature wills, and all their ends and powers
Must come within the boundless scope of God’s.

Festus |

And all our powers are but weaknesses
To what we shall have, and to that God hath.
Doth not the wish, too, point the likelihood
Of life to come?

Lucifer |

Boys wish that they were kings.
And so with thee. A deathless spirit’s state,
Freed from gross form and bodily weightiness,
Seems kingly by the side of souk like thine.
And boys and men will likely both be balked.
What if it be, that spirit, after death,
Is loosed like flesh into its elements?
The worlds which man hath constellated, hold
No fellowship in nature; nor perchance
As he hath systematised life, mind and soul.
But sooth to say, I know not aught of this.
I have no kind. No nature like to me
Exists. And human spirits must at least
Sleep till the day of doom, if it ever be.

Festus |

Hast never known one free from body?

Lucifer |

None.

Festus |

Why seek then to destroy them?

Lucifer |

It is my part.
Let ruin bury ruin. Let it be
Woe here, woe there, woe, woe, be everywhere!
It is not for me to know, nor thee, the end
Of evil. I inflict and thou must bear.
The arrow knoweth not its end and aim.
And I keep rushing, ruining along
Like a great river rich with dead men’s souls.
For if I knew, I might rejoice; and that
To me by Nature is forbidden. I know
Nor joy nor sorrow; but a changeless tone
Of sadness like the nightwind’s is the strain
Of what I have of feeling. I am not
As other spirits—but a solitude
Even to myself; I the sole spirit sole.

Festus |

Can none of thine immortals answer me?

Lucifer |

None, mortal!

Festus |

Where then is thy vaunted power?

Lucifer |

It is better seen as thus I stand apart
From all. Mortality is mine—the green
Unripened universe. But as the fruit
Matures, and world by world drops mellowed off
The wrinkling stalk of Time, as thine own race
Hath seen of stars now vanished—all is hid
From me. My part is done. What after comes
I know not more than thou.

Festus |

Raise me a spirit!
Awake ye dead! out with the secret, death!
The grave hath no pride nor the rise-again.
Let each one bring the bane whereof he died.
Bring the man his, the maiden hers! Oh! half
Mankind are murderers of themselves or souls.
Yea, what is life but lingering suicide?
Wake, dead! Ye know the truth; yet there ye lie
All mingling, mouldering, perishing together
Like, run sand in the hour-glass of old Time.
Death is the mad world’s asylum. There is peace;
Destruction’s quiet and equality.
Night brings out stars as sorrow shows as truths:
Though many, yet they help not; bright, they light not.
They are too late to serve us: and sad things
Are aye too true. We never see the stars
Till we can see nought but them. So with truth.
And yet if one would look down a deep well,
Even at noon, we might see those same stars
Far fairer than the blinding blue—the truth;
Probe the profound of thine own nature, man!
And thou may’st see reflected, e’en in life,
The worlds, the Heavens, the ages; by and by,
The coming come. Then welcome, world-eyed Truth!
But there are other eyes men better love
Than Truth’s: for when we have her she is so cold,
And proud, we know not what to do with her.
We cannot understand her, cannot teach;
She makes us love her, but she loves not us;
And quits us as she came and looks back never.
Wherefore we fly to Fiction’s warm embrace,
With her to relax and bask ourselves at ease;
And, in her loving and unhindering lap
Voluptuously lulled, we dream at most
On death and truth: she knows them, loves them not;
Therefore we hate them and deny them both.
Call up the dead!

Lucifer |

Let rest while rest they may!
For free from pain and from this world’s wear and tear
It may be a relief to them to rot;
And it must be that at the day of doom,
If mortals should take up immortal life,
They will curse me with a thunder which shall shake
The sun from out the socket of his sphere.
The curse of all created. Think on it!

Festus |

Those souls thou mean’st whom thou hast ruined, damned.

Lucifer |

Nor only those; when once the virgin bloom
Of soul is soiled—and rudely hath my hand
Swept o’er the swelling clusters of all life—
Little it matters whether crushed or touched
Scarcely: each speaks the spoiler hath been there.
The saved, the lost, shall curse me both alike:
God too shall curse me, and I, I, myself.
That curse is ever greatening—quick with hell;
The coming consummation of all woe.

Festus |

O man, be happy! Die and cease for ever!
Why wear we not the shroud alway, that robe
Which speaks our rank on earth, our privilege?
To know I have a deathless soul I would lose it

Lucifer |

Believest thou all I tell thee?

Festus |

All, I do.
Stringing the stars at random round her head,
Like a pearl network, there she sits—bright night!
I love night more than day—she is so lovely.
But I love night the most because she brings
My love to me in dreams which scarcely lie;
Oh! all but truth and lovelier oft than truth!
Let me have dreams like these, sweet Night, for ever,
When I shall wake no more; an endless dream
Of love and holy beauty ’mid the stars.

Lucifer |

I see thy heart and I will grant thy wish.
I have lied to thee. I have command over spirits.
Whom wilt thou that I call?

Festus |

Mine Angela!

Lucifer |

There is an Angel ever by thine hand.
What seest thou?

Festus |

It is my love! It is she!
My glory! spirit! beauty, let me touch thee.
Nay, do not shrink back: well then I am wrong:
Thou didst not use to shrink from me, my love.
Angela! dost thou hear me? Speak to me.
And thou art there—looking alive and dead.
Thy beauty is then incorruptible.
I thought so, oft as I have looked on thee.
Thou art too much even now for me as once.
I cannot gather what I raved to say;
Nor why I had thee hither. Stay, sweet sprite!
Dear art thou to me now, as in that hour
When first Love’s wave of feeling, spray-like broke
Into bright utterance, and we said we loved.
Yea, but I must come to thee. Move no more!
Art thou in death or Heaven or from the stars?
Have I done wrong in calling for thee thus?
What art thou? Speak, love; whisper me as wont
In the dear times gone bye; or durst thou not
Unfold the mystery of thine and mine
Own being? Was it Death who hushed thy lips?
Is his cold finger there still? Let me come!
She is not!

Lucifer |

And thou canst not bring her back.

Festus |

I will not, cannot be without her. Call her!

Lucifer |

I call on spirits and I make them come:
But they depart according to their own will.
Another time and she shall speak with thee—
Ere long—and she shall show thee where she dwells,
And how doth pass her immortality;—
If lengthening decay can so be called.
Can lines finite one way be infinite
Another? And yet such is deathlessness.

Festus |

It is hard to deem that spirits cease, that thought
And feeling flesh-like perish in the dust.
Shall we know those again in a future state
Whom we have known and loved on earth? Say yes!

Lucifer |

The mind hath features as the body hath.

Festus |

But is it mind which shall rerise?

Lucifer |

Man were
Not man without the mind be had in life.

Festus |

Shall all defects of mind and fallacies
Of feeling be immortalized? all needs,
All joys, all sorrows, be again gone through,
Before the final crisis be imposed?
Shall Heaven but be old earth created new?
Or earth, treelike, transplanted into Heaven,
To flourish by the waters of all life,
And we within its shade, as heretofore,
Cropping its fruit, with life-seeds cored at heart?

Lucifer |

Man’s nature, physical and psychical,
Will be together raised, changed, glorified;
And all shall be alike, like God; and all
Unlike each other, and themselves. The earth
Shall vanish from the thoughts of those she bore,
As have the idols of the olden time
From men’s hearts of the present. All delight
And all desire, shall be with Heavenly things,
And the new nature God bestowed on man.

Festus |

Then man shall be no more man but an Angel.

Lucifer |

When he is dead and buried. What remains—
That such an obscure, contradictory, thing
Should be perpetuated anywhere?

Festus |

Oh! if God hates the flesh, why made He it
So beautiful that e’en its semblance maddens?
Am I to credit what I think I have seen?
Or am I suffering some deceit of thine?

Lucifer |

I am explaining, not deluding.

Festus |

True.
Defining night by darkness, death by dust.
I run the gauntlet of a file of doubts,
Each one of which down hurls me to the ground.
I ask a hundred reasons what they mean,
And every one points gravely to the ground,
With one hand, and to Heaven with the other.
In vain I shut mine eyes. Truth’s burning beam
Forces them open, and when open, blinds them.

Lucifer |

Doubly unhappy!

Festus |

I am too unhappy
To die; as some too way-worn cannot sleep.
Planets and suns, that set themselves on fire
By their own rapid self-revolvements, are
But like some hearts. Existence I despise.
The shape of man is wearisome; a bird’s,
A worm’s—a whirlwind’s, I would change with aught.
Time! dash thine hour-glass down. Have done with this!
The course of Nature seems a course of Death,
And nothingness the sole substantial thing.

Lucifer |

Corruption springs from Light: ’tis the same power
Creates, preserves, destroys: the matter which
It works on, being one ever-changing form—
The living and the dying and the dead.

Festus |

I’ll not believe a thing which I have known.
Hell was made hell for me, and I am mad.

Lucifer |

True venom churns the froth out of the lips;
It works, and works like any waterwheel.
And she then was the maiden of thy heart.
Well, I have promised. Ye shall meet again.

Festus |

I loved her for that she was beautiful;
And that to me she seemed to be all nature
And all varieties of things in one:
Would set at night in clouds of tears, and rise
All light and laughter in the morning: yea,
And that she never schooled within her breast
One thought or feeling, but gave holiday
To all; and that she made all even mine
In the communion of love: and we
Grew like each other for we loved each other—
She, mild and generous as the sun in spring;
And I, like earth all budding out with love.

Lucifer |

And then, love’s old end, falsehood: nothing worse
I hope?

Festus |

What’s worse than falsehood? to deny
The god which is within us, and in all
Is love? Love hath as many vanities
As charms; and this, perchance, the chief of both:
To make our young heart’s track upon the first,
And snowlike fall of feeling which overspreads
The bosom of the youthful maiden’s mind,
More pure and fair than even its outward type.
If one did thus, was it from vanity?
Or thoughtlessness, or worse? Nay, let it pass.
The beautiful are never desolate;
But some one alway loves them—God or man.
If man abandons, God himself takes them.
And thus it was. She whom I once loved died.
The lightning loathes its cloud—the soul its clay.
Can I forget that hand I took in mine,
Pale as pale violets; that eye, where mind
And matter met alike divine? ah, no!
May God that moment judge me when I do!
Oh! she was fair: her nature once all spring,
And deadly beauty like a maiden sword;
Startlingly beautiful. I see her now!
Whatever thou art thy soul is in my mind;
Thy shadow hourly lengthens o’er my brain,
And peoples all its pictures with thyself.
Gone, not forgot—passed, not lost—thou shalt shine
In Heaven like a bright spot in the sun!
She said she wished to die, and so she died;
For, cloudlike, she poured out her love, which was
Her life, to freshen this parched heart. It was thus:
I said we were to part, but she said nothing.
There was no discord—it was music ceased—
Life’s thrilling, bounding, bursting joy. She sat
Like a house-god, her hands fixed on her knee;
And her dark hair lay loose and long around her,
Through which her wild bright eye flashed like flint.
She spake not, moved not, but she looked the more,
As if her eye were action, speech and feeling.
I felt it all; and came and knelt beside her.
The electric touch solved both our souls together.
Then comes the feeling which unmakes, undoes;
Which tears the sealike soul up by the roots
And lashes it in scorn against the skies.
Twice did I madly swear to God, hand clenched,
That not even He nor death should tear her from me.
It is the saddest and the sorest sight
One’s own love weeping;—but why call on God,
But that the feeling of the boundless bounds
All feeling, as the welkin doth the world?
It is this which ones us with the whole and God.
Then first we wept; then closed and clung together;
And my heart shook this building of my breast,
Like a live engine booming up and down.
She fell upon me like a snow-wreath thawing.
Never were bliss and beauty, love and woe,
Ravelled and twined together into madness,
As in that one wild hour; to which all else,
The past, is but a picture—that alone
Is real, and for ever there in front;
Making a black blank on one side of life
Like a blind eye. But after that I left her:
And only saw her once ogain alive.

Lucifer |

Well, shall we go?

Festus |

This moment. I am ready.
Farewell ye dear old walks and trees! farewell
Ye waters! I have loved ye well. In youth
And childhood it hath been my life to drift
Across ye lightly as a leaf; or skim
Your waves in yon skiff, swallowlike; or lie
Like a loved locket on your sunny bosom.
Could I, like you, by looking in myself
Find mine own Heaven—farewell! Immortal, come!
The morning peeps her blue eye on the east.

Lucifer |

Think not so fondly as thy foolish race,
Imagining a Heaven from things without;
The picture on the passing wave call Heaven—
The wavelet, life—the sands beneath it, death;
Daily more seen till, lo! the bed is bare.
This fancy fools the world.

Festus |

Let us away!

IV

Scene—A mountain—Sunrise.

Festus and Lucifer.
Festus |

Hail beauteous Earth! Gazing o’er thee, I all
Forget the bounds of beings; and I long
To fill thee, as a lover pines to blend
Soul, passion, yea existence, with the fair
Creature he calls his own. I ask for nought
Before or after death but this—to lie,
And look, and live, and bask, and bless myself
Upon thy broad bright bosom. From thee I
Sprang, and to thee I turn, heart, arm and brain.
Yes, I am all thine own. Thou art the sole
Parent. To rock and river, plain and wood
I cry, ye are my kin. While I, O Earth!
Am but an atom of thee, and a breath,
Passing unseen and unrecorded like
The tiny throb here in my temple’s pulse.
Thou art for ever and the sacred bride
Of heaven—worthy the passion of our God.
O! full of lights love, grace!—the grace of all
Who owe to thee their life; thy Maker’s love;
His face’s light. All thine rejoice in thee;
Thou in thyself for aye; rolling through air
As seraphs’ song out of their trumpet lips
Rolls round the skies of Heaven. See the sun!
God’s crest upon His azure shield the Heavens.
Canst thou, a spirit, look upon him?

Lucifer |

Ay.
I led him from the void, where he was wrought,
By this right hand, up to the glorious seat
His brightness overshadows; built his throne
On piles of gold; and laid his chambers on
Beams of gold: wrapped a veil of fire around
His face; and bade him reign and burn like me.
There, ever since, sat warming into life
These worlds as in a nest, he has and is.
But fall he must. I have done, do, nought else
From my first thought to this and to my last.
No matter; it is beneath this mind of mine
To reck of aught. I bear, have borne the ill
Of ages, of eternities—and must.
I care not. I shall sway the world as now,
Which worse and worse sinks with me as I sink,
Till finite souls evanish as a vapour;
Till immortality, the proud thing, perish;
And God alone be and eternity.
Then will I clap my hands and cry to Him,
I have done! Have Thy will now! There is none but Thee.
I am the first created being. I
Will be the last to perish and to die.

Festus |

Thou art a fit monitor, methinks, of pleasure.

Lucifer |

To the high air sunshine and cloud are one;
Pleasure and pain to me. Thou and the earth
Alone feel these as different—for Ye
Are under them—the Heavens and I above.

Festus |

But tell me, have ye scenes like this in Hell?

Lucifer |

Nay, not in Heaven.

Festus |

What is Heaven? not the toys
Of singing, love and music? such a place
Were fit for women only.

Lucifer |

Heaven is no place;
Unless it be a place with God, allwhere.
It is the being good—the knowing God—
The consciousness of happiness and power;
With knowledge which no spirit e’er can lose
But doth increase in every state; and aught
It most delights in the full leave to do.
But why consume me with such questions? Why
Add earth to Hell, in the great chain of worlds
Which God in wrath hath bound about me?

Festus |

Why!
’Twas therefore that I closed with thee, great Fiend!
That thou mightst answer all things I proposed,
Or bring me those who would do.

Lucifer |

All these things
Thou wilt know sometime, when to see and know
Are one; to see a thing and comprehend
The nature of it essentially; perceive
The reason and the science of its being,
And the relations with the universe
Of all things actual or possible,
Mortal, immortal, spiritual, gross.
This, when the spirit is made free of Heaven,
Is the divine result; proportioned still
To the intelligence as human; for
There are degrees in Heaven as everything,
By God’s will. Unimaginable space
As full of suns as is earth’s sun of atoms,
Faileth to match His boundless variousness;
And ever must do, though a thousand worlds,
As diverse from each other as is thine
From any of thy system’s, were elanced
Each minute into life unendingly.
All of yon worlds, and all who dwell in them,
Stand in diverse degrees of bliss and being.
Through the ten thousand times ten thousandth grade
Of blessedness, above this world’s and man’s
Ability to feel or to conceive,
The soul may pass and yet know nought of Heaven,
More than a dim and miniature reflection
Of its most bright infinity;—for God
Makes to each spirit its peculiar Heaven;—
And yet is Heaven a bright reality,
As this or any of yon worlds; a state
Where all is loveliness and power and love;
Where all sublimest qualities of mind,
Not infinite, are limited alone
By the surrounding Godhood, and where nought
But what produceth glory and delight,
To creature and Creator is; where all
Enjoy entire dominion o’er themselves,
Acts, feelings, thoughts, conditions, qualities,
Spirit and soul and mind; all under God,
For spirit is soul Deified;—while earth,
To the immortal vast, God-natured Spirit,
Is but a spell, which having served to light,
A lamp, is cast into consuming fire.

Festus |

And Hell? Is it nought but pits and chains and flames?

Lucifer |

An ever greatening sense of ill and woe,
Aye crushing down the soul, but filling never
Its infinite capacity of pain.

Festus |

But human nature is not infinite,
And therefore cannot suffer endlessly.

Lucifer |

God may create in time what shall endure
Unto Eternity. With Him is no
Distinction, nor in that which is of Him.

Festus |

Then is not soul of God, but man and earth.
Soul when made spirit is of earth no more,
Nor time, but of Eternity and Heaven.
’Tis but when in the body, and bent down
To worldly ends, that human souls become
Objects of time, as most are, till the hour
Comes when the soul of man shall be made one
With God’s spirit; and where shall woe be then?
Where, sin? where, suffering? when the mortal soul
Shall be Divinised and eternised by
God’s very spirit put upon it?

Lucifer |

How
Can souls begotten to predestined doom,
From and before all worlds, be deemed of earth;

Festus |

Things spiritual, as belonging God,
Are known unto Him, and predestined from
Eternity, nor these alone; but Flesh
Forms not nor does it need the care of Fate.

Lucifer |

The object of eternal knowledge must
Have like existence.

Festus |

Then it cannot be
Bound unto torment; that would be to bring
Torture on godlike essence.

Lucifer |

Hast not heard,
How thine existence here, on earth, is but
The dark and narrow section of a life
Which was with God, long ere the sun was lit,
And shall be yet, when all the bold bright stars
Are dark as death-dust—Immortality
And Wisdom tending thee on either hand,
Thy divine sisters? But do thou believe
E’en what thou wilt. It matters not to me.

Festus |

Is it the nature or the deed of God
To render finite follies infinite,
Or to eternise sin and death in fire?
For so long as the punishment endures,
The crime lasts. Were it not for thy presence,
Spirit! I would not deem Hell were.

Lucifer |

Let not
My presence pass for more than it is worth,
I pray, nor yet my absence. Trust me, I
Could wish, with thee, that Hell were blotted out
Of utmost space. ’Tis man himself aye makes
His own God and his hell. But this is truth.

Festus |

The truth is perilous never to the true,
Nor knowledge to the wise; and to the fool,
And to the false, error and truth alike.
Error is worse than ignorance. But say:—
How can eternal punishment be due
To temporal offences, to a pulse
Of momentary madness?

Lucifer |

Pardon me.
Sin is not temporary. Nothing is,
Of spiritual nature, but hath cause
Immortal and immortal end in all,
As spirits. Therefore till the soul shall be
By grace redeified, as is the soul,
So is the sin, for ever before God.

Festus |

Sin is not of the spirit, but of that
Which blindeth spirit, heart and brain.

Lucifer |

Believe so.
The law of all the worlds is retribution.

Festus |

But is it so of God?

Lucifer |

The laws of Heaven
Are not of earth; there law is liberty.

Festus |

Thou thundercloud of spirits, darkning
The skies and wrecking earth! Could I hate men
How I should joy with thee, even as an eagle,
Nigh famished, in the fellowship of storms;
But I still love them. What will come of men?

Lucifer |

Whatever may, perdition is their meed.
Were Heaven dispeopled for a ministry
To warn them of their ways; were thou and I
To monish them; were Heaven, and Earth, and Hell
To preach at once, they still would mock and jeer
As now; but never repent until too late;
Until the everlasting hour had struck.

Festus |

Men might be better if we better deemed
Of them. The worst way to improve the world
Is to condemn it. Men may overget
Delusion—not despair.

Lucifer |

Why love mankind?
The affections are thy systems weaknesses;
The wasteful outlets of self-maintenance.

Festus |

The wild flower’s tendril, proof of feebleness,
Proves strength; and so we fling our feelings out,
The tendrils of the heart, to bear us up.
O Earth! how drear to think to tear oneself,
Even for an hour, from looks like this of thine;
From features, oh! so fair; to quit for aye
The luxury of thy side. Why, why art thou
Thus glorious, and ’twere not to sate the soul,
And chide us for the senseless dream of Heaven?
The still strong stream sweeps onward to its end,
Like one of the great purposes of God;
Or like, may be, a soul like mine to Him.
Along yon deep blue vein upon thy bosom,
Earth? I could float for ever. See it there—
Winding among its green and smiling isles,
Like Charity amidst her children dear;
Or Peace, rejoicing in her olive wreaths,
And gladdening as she glides along the lands.

Lucifer |

And yet all this must end—must pass; drop down
Oblivion like a pebble in a pit:
For God shall lay His hand upon the earth,
And crush it up like a red leaf.

Festus |

Not be?
I cannot root the thought, nor hold it firm.

Lucifer |

This same sweet world which thou wouldst fondly deem
Eternal, may be; which I soon shall see
Destruction suck back as the tide a shell.

Festus |

It will not be yet. I’ll woo thee, world, again,
And revel in thy loveliness and love.
I have a heart with room for every joy:
And since we must part sometime, while I may,
I’ll quaff the nectar in thy flowers, and press
The richest clusters of thy luscious fruit
Into the cup of my desires. I know
My years are numbered not in units yet.
But I cannot live unless I love and am loved;
Unless I have the young and beautiful
Bound up like pictures in my book of life.
It is the intensest vanity alone
Which makes us bear with life. Some seem to live,
Whose hearts are like those unenlightened stars
Of the first darkness—lifeless, timeless, useless—
With nothing but a cold night air about them;
Not suns—not planets—darkness organized:
Orbs of a desert darkness: with no soul
To light its watchfire in the wilderness,
And civilize the solitude one moment.
There are such seemingly; but how or why
They live I know not. This to me is life;
That if life be a burden, I will join
To make it but the burden of a song:
I hate the world’s coarse thought. And this is life;
To watch young beauty’s budlike feelings burst
And load the soul with love;—as that pale flower,
Which opes at eve, spreads sudden on the dark
Its yellow bloom, and sinks the air down with sweets.
Let Heaven take all that’s good—Hell all that’s foul;
Leave us the lovely! and we will ask no more.

Lucifer |

To me it seems time all should end. The sky
Grows gray. It is not so bright nor blue as once.
Well I remember, as it were yesterday,
When earth and Heaven went happy, hand in hand,
With all the morning dew of youth about them;
With the bright unworldly hearts of youth and truth
And the maiden bosoms of the beautiful:—
Ere earth sinned, or the pure indignant Heavens
Retreated high, nigh God; when earth was all
A creeping mass alive with shapeless things:
And when there were but three things in the world—
Monsters, mountains and water: before age
Had thickened the eyes of stars; and while the sea,
Rejoicing like a ring of saints round God,
Or Heaven on Heaven about some newborn sun,
In its sublime samesoundingness, laughed out
And cried not I! Like God I never rest.

Festus |

God hath his rest; earth hers. Let me have mine.
Yet must I look on thee, fair scene, again,
Ere I depart. The glory of the world
Is on all hands. In one encircling ken,
I gaze on river, sea, isle, continent,
Mountain, and wood, and wild, and fire-lipped hill,
And lake, and golden plain, and sun, and Heaven,
Where the stars brightly die, whose death is day;
City and port and palace, ships and tents,
Lie massed and mapped before me. All is here.
The elements of the world are at my feet,
Above me and about me. Now would I
Be and do somewhat beside that I am.
Canst thou not give me some ethereal slave,
Of the pure essence of an element—
Such as my bondless brain hath oft times drawn
In the divine insanity of dreams—
To stand before me and obey me, spirit?

Lucifer |

Call out, and see if aught arise to thee.

Festus |

Green dewy Earth, who standest at my feet,
Singing and pouring sunshine on thy head,
As näiad native water, speak to me!
I am thy son. Canst thou not now, as once,
Bring forth some being dearer, liker to thee
Than is my race—Titan or tiny fay,
Stream-nymph or wood-nymph? She hath ceased to speak,
Like God, except in thunder, or to look
Unless in lightning. Miracles, with earth,
Are out of fashion as with Heaven.

Lucifer |

More’s
The pity. Call elsewhere! Old Earth is hard
Of hearing, maybe.

Festus |

I beseech thee, Sea!
Tossing thy wavy locks in sparkling play,
Like to a child awakening with the light
To laughter. Canst not thou disgulph for me,
From thy deep bosom, deep as Heaven is high,
Of all thy sea-gods one, or sea-maids?

Lucifer |

None!

Festus |

I half despair. Fire! that art slumbering there,
Like some stern warrior in his rocky fort,
After the vast invasion of the world,
Hast not some flaming imp, or messenger
Of empyrean element, to whom,
In virtue of his nature, are both known
The secrets of the burning, central, void below,
And yon bright Heaven, out of whose aëry fire
Are wrought the forms of angels and the thrones?
Hast none at hand to do my bidding? Come!
Breathe out a spirit for me! One I ask
That shall be with me always, as a friend,
And not like thee, who despotisest o’er
The heart thou seek’st to serve. I must be free.

Lucifer |

All finite souls must serve; their widest sway
Is but the rule of service. This fair earth
Which thou dost boast so much of, why, thou see’st
’Tis but the particoloured, scummy dross
Of the original element wherefrom
The fiery worlds were framed.

Festus |

Air! and thou, Wind!
Which art the unseen similitude of God
The Spirit, His most meet and mightiest sign;
The earth with all her steadfastness and strength,
Sustaining all, and bound about with chains
Of mountains, as is life with mercies, ranging round
With all her sister orbs the whole of Heaven,
Is not so like the unlikenable One
As thou. Ocean is less divine than thee;
For although all but limitless, it is yet
Visible, many a land not visiting.
But thou art, Lovelike, everywhere; o’er earth,
O’er ocean triumphing, and aye with clouds,
That like the ghost of ocean’s billows roll,
Decking or darkening Heaven. The sun’s light
Floweth and ebbeth daily like the tides;
The moon’s doth grow or lessen, night by night;
The stirless stars shine forth by fits and hide,
And our companion planets come and go;—
And all are known, their laws and liberties.
But no man can foreset thy coming, none
Reason against thy going; thou art free,
The type impalpable of Spirit, thou.
Thunder is but a momentary thing,
Like a world’s deathrattle, and is like death;
And lightning, like the blaze of sin, can blind
Only and slay. But what are these to thee,
In thine all-present variousness? Now,
So light as not to wake the snowiest down
Upon the dove’s breast, winning her bright way
Calm and sublime as Grace unto the soul,
Towards her far native grove; now, stern and strong
As ordnance, overturning tree and tower;
Cooling the white brows of the peaks of fire—
Turning the sea’s broad furrows like a plough—
Fanning the fruitening plains, breathing the sweets
Of meadows, wandering o’er blinding snows,
And sands like sea-beds and the streets of cities,
Where men as garnered grain lie heaped together;
Freshening the cheeks, and mingling oft the locks
Of youth and beauty ’neath star-speaking eve;
Swelling the pride of canvas, or, in wrath,
Scattering the fleets of nations like dead leaves:
In all, the same o’ermastering sightless force,
Bowing the highest things of earth to earth,
And lifting up the dust unto the stars;
Fatelike, confounding reason, and like God’s
Spirit, conferring life upon the world—
Midst all corruption incorruptible;
Monarch of all the elements! hast thou
No soft Eolian sylph, with sightless wing,
To spare a mortal for an hour?

Lucifer |

Peace, peace!
All nature knows that I am with thee here,
And that thou need’st no minor minister.
To thee I personate the world—its powers,
Beliefs, and doubts and practices.

Festus |

Are all
Mine invocations fruitless, then?

Lucifer |

They are.
Let us enjoy the world!

Festus |

If ’twas God’s will
That thou shouldst visit me He shall not send
Temptation to my heart in vain. Sweet world!
We all still cling to thee. Though thou thyself
Passest away, yet men will hanker about thee,
Like mad ones by their moping haunts. Men pass,
Cleaving to things themselves which pass away,
Like leaves on waves. Thus all things pass for ever,
Save mind and the mind’s meed.

Lucifer |

Let us too pass!

V

Scene—Alcove and garden.

Festus and Clara.
Festus |

What happy things are youth and love and sunshine!
How sweet to feel the sun upon the heart!
To know it is lighting up the rosy blood,
And with all joyous feelings, prism-hued,
Making the dark breast shine like a spar grot.
We walk among the sunbeams as with angels.

Clara |

Yes, there are feelings so serene and sweet,
Coming and going with a musical lightness,
That they can make amends for their passingness,
And balance God’s condition to decay;
As yon light fleecy cloudlet floating along,
Like golden down from some high angel’s wing,
Breaks but relieves and beautifies the blue.
I wonder if ever I could love another.
How I should start to see upon the sward
A shadow not thine own armlinked with mine!
See, here is a garland I have bound for thee.

Festus |

Nay, crown thyself; it will suit thee better, love.
Place wreaths of everlasting flowers on tombs,
And deck with fading beauties forms that fade.
Put it away—I will no crown save this:
And could the line of dust which here I trace
Upon my brow but warrant dust beneath—
And nothing more—or could this bubble frame,
Informed with soul, lashed from the stream of life
By its own impetus, but burst at once,
And vanish part on high and part below,
I would be happy, nor would envy death.
Could I, like Heaven’s bolt, earthing quench myself,
This moment would I burn me out a grave.
Might I but be as many years in dying
As I have lived—that might be some relief.

Clara |

What canst thou mean?

Festus |

Mean? Is there not a future?
The past, the present and the coming, curse each!
The future, curse it!

Clara |

Shall we not ever live
And love as now?

Festus |

Ay, live I fear we must.

Clara |

And love: because we then are happiest.
We shall lack nothing having love: and we,
We must be happy everywhere—we two!
For spiritual life is great and clear,
And self-continuous as the changeless sea,
Rolling the same in every age as now;
Whether o’er mountain tops, where only snow
Dwells, and the sunbeam hurries coldly by;
Or o’er the vales, as now, of some old world
Older than ancient man’s. As is the sea’s,
So is the life of spirit, and the kind.
And then with natures raised, refined and freed
From these poor forms, our days shall pass in peace
And love; no thought of human littleness
Shall cross our high calm souls, shining and pure
As the gold gates of Heaven. Like some deep lake
Upon a mountain summit they shall rest,
High above cloud and storm of life like this,
All peace and power, and passionless purity;
Or if a thought of other troubled times
Ruffle it for a moment, it shall pass
Like a chance raindrop on its heavenward face.
I love to meditate on bliss to come.
Not that I am unhappy here; but that
The hope of higher bliss may rectify
The lower feeling which we now enjoy.
This life, this world is not enough for us;
They are nothing to the measure of our mind.
For place we must have space; for time we must have
Eternity; and for a spirit godhood.

Festus |

Mind means not happiness: power is not good.

Clara |

True bliss is to be found in holy life;
In charity to man—in love to God:
Why should such duties cease, such powers decay?
Are they not worthy of a deathless state—
A boundless scope—a high uplifted life?
Man, like the air-born eagle who remains
On earth only to feed and sleep and die;
But whose delight is on his lonely wing,
Wide sweeping as a mind, to force the skies
High as the lightfall ere, begirt with clouds,
It dash this, nether world—immortal man
Rushes aloft, right upwards, into Heaven.
O faith of Christ, sole honour of the world!

Festus |

What know men of religion, save its forms?

Clara |

True faith nor biddeth nor abideth form.
The bended knee, the eye uplift is all
Which man need render; all which God can bear.
What to the faith are forms? A passing speck,
A crow upon the sky. God’s worship is
That only He inspires; and His bright words,
Writ in the red-leaved volume of the heart,
Return to him in prayer, as dew to Heaven.
Our proper good we rarely seek or make;
Mindless of our immortal powers and their
Immortal end, as is the pearl of its worth,
The rose its scent, the wave its purity.

Festus |

Come, we will quit these saddening themes. Wilt sing
To me? for I am gloomy; and I love
Thy singing, sacred as the sound of hymns,
On some bright Sabbath morning, on the moor,
Where all is still save praise; and where hard by
The ripe grain shakes its bright beard in the sun;
The wild bee hums more solemnly; the deep sky,
The fresh green grass, the sun, and sunny brook,
All look as if they knew the day, the hour;
And felt with man the need and joy of thanks.

Clara |

I cannot sing the lightsome lays of love.
Many thou know’st who can; but none that can
Love thee as I do—for I love thy soul;
And I would save it, Festus! Listen then:

Is Heaven a place where pearly streams
Glide over silver sand?
Like childhood’s rosy dazzling dreams
Of some far faery land?
Is Heaven a clime where diamond dews
Glitter on fadeless flowers?
And mirth and music ring aloud
From amaranthine bowers?

Ah no; not such, not such is Heaven!
Surpassing far all these;
Such cannot be the guerdon given
Man’s wearied soul to please.
For saint and sinner here below
Such vain to be have proved:
And the pure spirit will despise
Whate’er the sense hath loved.

There we shall dwell with Sire and Son,
And with the mother-maid,
And with the Holy Spirit, one:
In glory like arrayed:
And not to one created thing
Shall our embrace be given;
But all our joy shall be in God;
For only God is Heaven.

Festus |

I know that thou dost love me. I in vain
Strive to love aught of earth or Heaven but thee.
Thou art my first, last, only love; nor shall
Another even tempt my heart. Like stars,
A thousand sweet and bright and wondrous fair,
A thousand deathless miracles of beauty,
They shall ever pass at all but eyeless distance,
And never mix with thy love; but be lost
All, meanly in its moonlike lustrousness.

Clara |

How still the air is! the tree tops stir not:
But stand and peer on Heaven’s bright face as though
It slept and they were loving it: they would not
Have the skies see them move for summers; would they?
See that sweet cloud! It is watching us, I am certain.
What have we here to make thee stay one second?
Away! thy sisters wait thee in the west,
The blushing bridemaids of the sun and sea.
I would I were like thee, thou little cloud,
Ever to live in Heaven: or seeking earth
To let my spirit down in drops of love:
To sleep with night upon her dewy lap;
And, the next dawn, back with the sun to Heaven;
And so on through eternity, sweet cloud!
I cannot but think that some senseless things
Are happy. Often and often have I watched
A gossamer line sighing itself along
The air, as it seemed; and so thin, thin and bright,
Looking as woven in a loom of light,
That I have envied it, I have, and followed;—
Oft watched the sea-bird’s down blown o’er the wave,
Now touching it, now spirited aloft,
Now out of sight, now seen—till in some bright fringe
Of streamy foam, as in a cage, at last
A playful death it dies, and mourned its death.

Festus |

But thinkest thou the future is a state
More positive than this; or that it can be
Aught but another present, full of cares,
And toils, perhaps, and duties; that the soul
Will ever be more nigh to God than now,
Save as may seem from mind’s debility:
Just as the sun, from weakness of the eye,
And the illusions made by matter’s forms,
Seems hot and wearied resting on the hill?
It would be well, I think, to live as though
No more were to be looked for; to be good
Because it is best, here; and leave hope and fear
For lives below ourselves. If earth persuades not
That I owe prayer and praise and love to God,
While all I have He gives, will Heaven? will Hell?
No; neither, never!

Clara |

I think not all with thee.
Have I not heard thee hint of spirit-friends?
Where are they now?

Festus |

Ah! close at hand, mayhap.
I have a might immortal; and can ken
With angels. Neither sky nor night nor earth
Hinder me. Through the forms of things I see
Their essences; and thus, even now, behold—
But where I cannot show to thee—far round,
Nature herself—the whole effect of God.
Mind, matter, motion, heat, time, love, and life,
And death and immortality; those chief
And first-born giants all are there; all parts,
All limbs of her their mother; she is all.

Clara |

And what does she?

Festus |

Produce: it is her life.
The three named last, life, death, deathlessness,
Glide in elliptic path round all things made—
For none save God can fill the perfect whole:
And are but to eternity as is
The horizon to the world. At certain points
Each seems the other; now, the three are one;
Now, all invisible; and now, as first,
Moving in measured round.

Clara |

How look these beings?

Festus |

Ah! Life looks gaily and gloomily in turns;
With a brow chequered like the sward, by leaves
Between which the light glints; and she, careless, wears
A wreath of flowers—part faded and part fresh.
And Death is beautiful and sad and still:
She seems too happy; happier far than life—
In but one feeling, apathy: and on
Her chill white brow frosts bright, a braid of snow.

Clara |

And Immortality?

Festus |

She looks alone;
As though she would not know her sisterhood.
And on her brow a diadem of fire,
Matched by the conflagration of her eye,
Outflaming even that eye which in my sleep
Beams close upon me till it bursts from sheer
O’erstrainedness of sight, burns.

Clara |

What do they?

Festus |

Each strives to win me to herself.

Clara |

How?

Festus |

Death
Opens her sweet white arms and whispers, peace!
Come say thy sorrows in this bosom! This
Will never close against thee; and my heart,
Though cold, cannot be colder much than man’s.
Come! All this soon must end; and soon the world
Shall perish leaf by leaf, and land by land;
Flower by flower—flood by flood—and hill
By hill, away; Oh! come, come! Let us die.

Clara |

Say that thou wilt not die!

Festus |

Nay, I love Death.
But Immortality, with finger spired,
Points to a distant, giant world—and says
There, there is my home! Live along with me!

Clara |

Canst see that world?

Festus |

Just—a huge shadowy shape;
It looks a disembodied orb—the ghost
Of some great sphere which God hath stricken dead:
Or like a world which God hath thought—not made.

Clara |

Follow her Festus! Does she speak again?

Festus |

She never speaks but once; and now, in scorn,
Points to this dim, dwarfed, misbegotten sphere.

Clara |

Why let her pass?

Festus |

That is the great world-question.
Life would not part with me; and from her brow
Tearing her wreath of passion-flowers, she flung
It round my neck and dared me struggle then.
I never could destroy a flower: and none
But fairest hands like thine can grace with me
The plucking of a rose. And Life, sweet Life!
Vowed she would crop the world for me and lay it
Herself before my feet even as a flower.
And when I felt that flower contained thyself—
One drop within its nectary kept for me,
I lost all count of those strange sisters three;
And where they be I know not. But I see
One who is more to me.

Clara |

I know not how
Thou hast this power and knowledge. I but hope
It comes from good hands; if it be not thine
Own force of mind. It is much less what we do
Than what we think, which fits us for the future.
I wish we had a little world to ourselves;
With none but we two on it.

Festus |

And if God
Gave us a star, what could we do with it
But that we could without it? Wish it not!

Clara |

I’ll not wish then for stars; but I could love
Some peaceful spot where we might dwell unknown,
Where home-born joys might nestle round our hearts
As swallows round our roofs—and blend their sweets
Like dewy-tangled flowerets in one bed.

Festus |

The sweetest joy, the widest woe is love;
The taint of earth, the odour of the skies,
Is in it. Would that I were aught but man!
The death of brutes, the immortality
Of fiend or angel, better seems than all
The doubtful prospects of our painted dust.
And all Morality can teach is—Bear!
And all Religion can inspire is—Hope!

Clara |

It is enough. Fruition of the fruit
Of the great Tree of Life, is not for earth.
Stars are its fruit, its lightest leaf is life.
The heart hath many sorrows beside love,
Yea many as the veins which visit it.
The love of aught on earth is not its chief
Nor ought to be. Inclusive of them all
There is the one main sorrow, life;—for what
Can spirit, severed from the great one, God,
Feel but a grievous longing to rejoin
Its infinite—its author—and its end?
And yet is life a thing to be beloved,
And honored holily, and bravely borne.
A man’s life may be all ease, and his death
By some dark chance, unthought of agony:—
Or life may be all suffering, and decease
A flower-like sleep;—or both be full of woe,
Or each comparatively painless. Blame
Not God for inequalities like these!
They may be justified. How canst thou know?
They may be only seeming. Canst thou judge?
They may be done away with utterly
By loving, fearing, knowing God the Truth.
In all distress of spirit, grief of heart,
Bodily agony, or mental woe,
Rebuffs and vain assumptions of the world,
Or the poor spite of weak and wicked souls,
Think thou on God! Think what he underwent
And did for us as man. Weigh thou thy cross
With Christs, and judge which were the heavier.
Joy even in thine anguish!—such was His,
But measurelessly more. Thy suffering
Assimilateth thee to Him. Rejoice!
Think upon what thou shalt be! Think on God!
Then ask thyself, what is the world, and all
Its mountainous inequalities? Ah, what!
Are not all equal as dust-atomies?

Festus |

My soul’s orb darkens as a sudden star,
Which having for a time exhausted earth
And half the Heavens of wonder, mortally
Passes for ever, not eclipsed, consumed;—
All but a cloudy vapour darkening there,
The very spot in space it once illumed.
Once to myself I seemed a mount of light;
But now, a pit of night.—No more of this!
Here have I lain all day in this green nook,
Shaded by larch and hornbeam, ash and yew;
A living well and runnel at my feet,
And wild flowers, dancing to some delicate air;
An urn-topped column and its ivy wreath
Skirting my sight as thus I lie and look
Upon the blue, unchanging, sacred skies:
And thou, too, gentle Clara by my side,
With lightsome brow and beaming eye, and bright
Long glorious locks, which drop upon thy cheek
Like goldhued cloudflakes on the rosy morn.
Oh! when the heart is full of sweets to o’erflowing,
And ringing to the music of its love,
Who but an angel or an hyprocrite
Could speak or think of happier states?

Clara |

Farewell!
Remember what thou saidst about the stars. Goes.

Festus |

Oh! why was woman made so fair? or man
So weak as to see that more than one had beaaty?
It is impossible to love but one.
And yet I dare not love thee as I could;
For all that the heart most longs for and deserves,
Passes the soonest and most utterly.
The moral of the world’s great fable, life.
All we enjoy seems given to deceive,
Or may be, undeceive us; who cares which?
And when the sum is done, and we have proved it,
Why work it over and over still again?
I am not what I would be. Hear me, God!
And speak to me in thine invisible likeness
The wind, as once of yore. Let me be pure!
Oh! I wish I was a pure child again,
As ere the clear could trouble me: when life
Was sweet and calm as is a sister’s kiss;
And not the wild and whirlwind touch of passion,
Which though it hardly light upon the lip,
With breathless swiftness sucks the soul out of sight
So that we lose it, and all thought of it.
What is this life wherein Thou hast founded me,
But a bright wheel which burns itself away,
Benighting even night with its grim limbs,
When it hath done and fainted into darkness?
Flesh is but fiction, and it flies away;
The gaunt and ghastly thing we bear about us
And which we hate and fear to look upon
Is truth; in death’s dark likeness limned—no more.

VII

Scene—A country town—Marketplace—Noon.

Lucifer and Festus.
Lucifer |

These be the toils and cares of mighty men!
Earth’s vermin are as fit to fill her thrones
As these high Heaven’s bright seats.

Festus |

Men’s callings all
Are mean and vain; their wishes more so: oft
The man is bettered by his part or place.
How slight a chance may raise or sink a soul!

Lucifer |

What men call accident is God’s own part.
He lets ye work your will—it is His own:
But that ye mean not, know not, do not, He doth.

Festus |

What is life worth without a heart to feel
The great and lovely, and the poetry
And sacredness of things? for all things are
Sacred—the eye of God is on them all.
And hallows all unto it. It is fine
To stand upon some lofty mountain-thought
And feel the spirit stretch into a view;
To joy in what might be if will and power
For good would work together but one hour.
Yet millions never think a noble thought:
But with brute hate of brightness bay a mind
Which drives the darkness out of them, like hounds.
Throw but a false glare round them, and in shoals
They rush upon perdition: that’s the race.
What charm is in this world-scene to such minds
Blinded by dust? What can they do in Heaven,
A state of spiritual means and ends?
Thus must I doubt—perpetually doubt.

Lucifer |

Who never doubted never half believed.
Where doubt there truth is—’tis her shadow. I
Declare unto thee that the past is not.
I have looked over all life, yet never seen
The age that had been. Why then fear or dream
About the future? Nothing but what is, is;
Else God were not the Maker that He seems,
As constant in creating as in being.
Embrace the present! Let the future pass.
Plague not thyself about a future. That
Only which comes direct from God, His spirit,
Is deathless. Nature gravitates without
Effort; and so all mortal natures fall
Deathwards. All aspiration is a toil;
But inspiration cometh from above,
And is no labour. The earth’s inborn strength
Could never lift her up to yon stars, whence
She fell; nor human soul, by native worth,
Claim Heaven as birthright, more than man may call
Cloudland his home. The soul’s inheritance,
Its birth-place, and its death-place, is of earth,
Until God maketh earth and soul anew;
The one like Heaven, the other like Himself.
So shall the new Creation come at once;
Sin, the dead branch upon the tree of Life,
Shall be cut off for ever; and all souls
Concluded in God’s boundless amnesty.

Festus |

Thou windest and unwindest faith at will.
What am I to believe?

Lucifer |

Thou mayst believe
But that which thou art forced to.

Festus |

Then I feel
That instinct of immortal life in me,
Which prompts me to provide for it.

Lucifer |

Perhaps.

Festus |

Man hath a knowledge of a time to come—
His most important knowledge: the weight lies
Nearest the short end; and the world depends
Upon what is to be. I would deny
The present, if the future. Oh! there is
A life to come, or all’s a dream.

Lucifer |

And all
May be a dream. Thou seest in thine, men, deeds,
Clear, moving, full of speech and order; then
Why may not all this world be but a dream
Of God’s? Fear not! Some morning God may waken.

Festus |

I would it were. This life’s a mystery.
The value of a thought cannot be told;
But it is clearly worth a thousand lives
Like many men’s. And yet men love to live
As if mere life were worth their living for.
What but perdition will it be to most?
Life’s more than breath and the quick round of blood
It is a great spirit and a busy heart.
The coward and the small in soul scarce do live.
One generous feeling—one great thought—one deed
Of good, ere night, would make life longer seem
Than if each year might number a thousand days—
Spent as is this by nations of mankind.
We live in deeds, not years; in thoughts, not breaths;
In feelings, not in figures on a dial.
We should count time by heart-throbs. He most lives
Who thinks most—feels the noblest—acts the best
Life’s but a means unto an end—that end,
Beginning, mean and end to all things—God.
The dead have all the glory of the world.
Why will we live and not be glorious?
We never can be deathless till we die.
It is the dead win battles. And the breath
Of those who through the world drive like a wedge,
Tearing earth’s empires up, nears death so close
It dims his well-worn scythe. But no? the brave
Die never. Being deathless, they but change
Their country’s arms for more—their country’s heart.
Give then the dead their due; it is they who saved us.
The rapid and the deep—the fall, the gulf
Have likenesses in feeling and in life.
And life, so varied, hath more loveliness
In one day than a creeping century
Of sameness. But youth loves and lives on change
Till the soul sighs for sameness; which at last
Becomes variety, and takes its place.
Yet some will last to die out thought by thought,
And power by power, and limb of mind by limb,
Like lambs upon a gay device of glass,
Till all of soul that’s left be dry and dark;
Till even the burden of some ninety years
Hath crashed into them like a rock; shattered
Their system as if ninety suns had rushed
To ruin earth—or Heaven had rained its stars;
Till they become, like scrolls, unreadable
Throught dust and mould. Can they be cleaned and read?
Do human spirits wax and wane like moons!

Lucifer |

The eye dims and the heart gets old and slow;
The lithe limb stiffens, and the sun-hued locks
Thin themselves off, or whitely wither;—still
Ages not spirit, even in one point,
Immeasurably small; from orb to orb,
In ever rising radiance, shining like
The sun upon the thousand lands of earth.
Look at the medley, motley throng we meet!
Some smiling—frowing some; their cares and joys
Alike not worth a thought—some sauntering slowly
As if destruction never could o’ertake them;
Some hurrying on as fearing judgment swift
Should trip the heels of Death and seize them living.

Festus |

Grief hallows hearts even while it ages
And much hot grief, in youth, forces up life
With power which too soon ripens and which drops. A funeral passes.
Whose funeral is this ye follow, friends?

Lucifer |

Would ye have grief, let me come! I am woe.

Mourner |

We want no grief: Festus! she died of grief.

Festus |

Did ye say she died? oh! I knew her then.
Set down the body; let toe look upon her!
Now, Son of God! what dost Thou now in heaven
While one so beautiful lies earthening here?
I will give up the future for the past;
The winged spirit and the starry home
If Thou wilt let her live, and make me love.

Mourner |

She was a lock of Heaven which Heaven gave earth,
And took again, because unworthy of her.

Festus |

Her air was an immortal’s; I have seen
Stars look on it with feeling; and her eye,
Wherever she went, it won her way like wine.
Men bowed to it as to the lifted Host.
How could I be so cruel? Who but I?
And now, corruption, come; sit; feast thyself!
This is the choicest banquet thou hast been at.
Thou art my happier, only rival: thou
Who takest love from the living—life from beauty—
Beauty from death—whole robber of the world!

Mourner |

The moment after thou desertedst her
A cloud came over the prospect of her life;
And I foresaw how evening would set in,
Early and dark and deadly. She was true.

Festus |

Did I not love thee too? pure! perfect thing!
This is a soul I see and not a body.
Go, beauty, Test for aye; go, starry eyes,
And lips like rosebuds peeping out of snow;
Go, breast love-filled as a boat’s sail with wind,
Leaping from wave to wave as leaps a child
Thoughtless o’er grassy graves; go, locks, which have
The golden embrownment of a lion’s eye!
Yet one more look; farewell, thou well and fair!
All who but loved thee shall be deathless. Nought
Named but with thee can perish. Thou and Death
Have made each other purer, lovelier, seem,
Like snow and moonlight. Never more for thee
Let eyes be swollen like streams with latter rains!
To die were rapture having lived with thee.
Thy soul hath passed out of a bodily Heaven
Into a spiritual. Rest for aye!—
Pure as the dead, in life; the dead are holy.
I would I were among them. Let us pass!
Living is but a habit; and I mean
To break myself of it soon.

Lucifer |

Too soon thou canst not.
Men heed not of the day, how nigh none knows,
Which brings the consummation of the world.
But in my ear the old machine already
Begins to grate. They would not credit warning,
Or I would up and cry, Repent! I will.
Here is a fair gathering and I feel moved.
Mortals, Repent! the world is nigh to its end;
On its last legs and desperately sick.
See ye not how it reels round all day long?

Boys |

Oh! here’s a ranter. Come, here’s fun. Amen!
I know the church service by heart.

Bystander |

Be off!
You’ll serve the church by keeping out of it.

Lucifer |

I am a preacher come to tell ye truth.
I tell ye too there is no time to be lost;
So fold your souls up neatly, while ye may;
Direct to God in Heaven; or some one else
May seize them, seal them, send them—you know where.
The world must end. I weep to think of it.
But you, you laugh! I knew ye would. I know
Men never will be wise till they are fools
For ever. Laugh away! The time will come,
When tears of fire are trickling from your eyes,
Ye will blame yourselves for having laughed at me.
I warn ye, men: prepare! repent! be saved!
I warn ye, not because I love, but know ye.
God will dissolve the world, as she of old
Her pearl, within His cup and swallow ye
In wrath: although to taste ye would be poison,
And death and suicide to aught but God.
Again I warn ye. Save himself who can!
Do ye not oft begin to seek salvation?
You? you? and fail, as oft, to find? Sink? Cease?
And shall I tell ye, brethren, why ye fail
Once and for ever? why, there is no past;
And the future is the fiction of a fiction;
The present moment is eternity;
It is that ye have sucked corruption from the world
Like milk from your own mothers: it is in
Your soul-blood and your soul-bones. Earth does not
Wean one out of a thousand sons to Heaven.
Beginnings are alike: it is ends which differ.
One drop falls, lasts, and dries up—but a drop;
Another begins a river: and one thought
Settles a life, an immortality:
And that one thought ye will not take to good.
Now I will tell ye just one other truth:
Ye hate the truth as snails salt—it dissolves ye,
Body and soul—but I don’t mind. So, now:
Up to this moment ye are all, each, damned.
What are ye now? still damned! It will be the same
To-morrow—and the next day—and the next:
Till some fine morning ye will wake in fire.
Ye see I do not mince the truth for ye.
Belike ye think your lives will dribble out
As brooks in summer dry up. Let us see!
Try: dike them up: they stagnate—thicken—scum.
That would make life worse than death. Well, let go!
Where are ye then? for life, like water, will
Find its last level: what level? The grave.
It is but a fall of five feet after all;
That cannot hurt ye; it is but just enough
To work the wheel of life; so work away!
Ye may think that I do not know the terms
And treasures whereupon ye live so high.
But I know more than most men, modestly
Speaking. I know I am lost, and ye too. God
Could only save me by destroying me;
So that I have no advantage over you.
And therefore think ye will the rather bear
One of your own state to advise for ye
Now don’t you envy me, good folks, I pray—
Envy’s a coal comes hissing hot from hell.
’Twill be such coals will burn ye by the way.
Your other preachers first think they are safe.
Now I say, broadly, I am the worst among ye;
And God knows I have no need to wrong myself,
Nor you. I boast not of it, but as truth:
It is little to be proud of, credit me.
What is salvation? What is safety? Think!
Who wants to know? Does any?

The Crowd |

All of us.

Lucifer |

Then I will not tell ye. You shall wait until
Some angel come and stir your stagnant souls:
Then plunge into yourselves and rise redeemed.
Come, I’ll unroll your hearts and read them to ye.
To say ye live is but to say ye have souls,
That ye have paid for them and mean to play them,
Till some brave pleasure wins the golden stake,
And rakes it up to death as to a bank.
Ye live and die on what your souls will fetch;
And all are of different prices: therefore Hell
Cannot well bargain for mankind in gross;
But each soul must be purchased, one by one.
This it is makes men rate themselves so high:
While truly ye are worth little: but to God
Ye are worth more than to yourselves. By sin
Ye wreak your spite against God—that ye know:
And knowing, will it. But I pray, I beg,
Act with some smack of justice to your Maker,
If not unto yourselves. Do! It is enough
To make the very Devil chide mankind—
Such baseness, such unthankfulness! Why he
Thanks God he is no worse. You don’t do that.
I say be just to God. Leave off these airs
Know your place—speak to God—and say, for once,
Go first, Lord! Take your finger off your eye!
It blocks the universe and God from sight.
Think ye your souls are worth nothing to God?
Are they so small? What can be great with God?
What will ye weigh against the Lord? Yourselves?
Bring out your balance: get in, man by man:
Add earth, heaven, hell, the universe; that’s all.
God puts his finger in the other scale,
And up we bounce, a bubble. Nought is great
Nor small with God—for none but He can make
The atom indivisible, and none
But He can make a world: He counts the orbs,
He counts the atoms of the universe,
And makes both equal—both are infinite.
Giving God honor, never underrate
Yourselves: after Him ye are everything
But mind! God’s more than everything; He is God.
And what of me? No, us? no! I mean the Devil?
Why see ye not he goes before both you
And God? Men say—as proud as Lucifer—
Pray who would not be proud with such a train?
Hath he not all the honor of the earth?
Why Mammon sits before a million hearths
Where God is bolted out from every house.
Well might He say He cometh as a thief;
For He will break your bars and burst your doors
Which slammed against Him once, and turn ye out
Roofless and shivering, ’neath the doom-storm; Heaven
Shall crack above ye like a bell in fire,
And bury all beneath its shining shards.
He calls: ye hear not. Lo! he comes—ye see not.
No; ye are deaf as a dead adder’s ear:
No; ye are blind as never bat was blind,
With a burning bloodshot blindness of the heart;
A swimming, swollen senselessness of soul.
Listen! Whom love ye most? Why him to whom
Ye in your turn are dearest. Need I name?
Oh no! But all are devils to themselves;
And every man his own great foe. Hell gets
Only the gleanings; earth hath the full wain;
And hell is merry at its harvest home.
But ye are generous to sin and grudge
The gleaners nothing; ask them, push them in.
Let not an ear, a grain of sin be lost;
Gather it, grind it up; it is our bread:
We should be ashamed to waste the gifts of God.
Why is the world so mad? Why runs it thus
Having and howling round the universe?
Because the Devil bit it from the birth!
The fault is all with him. Fear nothing, friends!
It is fear which beds the far to-come with fire
As the sun does the west: but the sun sets;
Well; still ye tremble—tremble, first at light,
Then darkness. Tremble! ye dare not believe.
No, cowards! sooner than believe ye would die;
Die with the black lie flapping on your lips
Like the soot-flake upon a burning bar.
Be merry, happy if ye can: think never
Of him who slays your souls, nor Him who saves.
There is, time enough for that when ye are a-dying.
Keep your old ways! It matters not this once.
Be brave! Ye are not men whom meat and wine
Serve to remind but of the sacrament;
To whom sweet shapes, and tantalizing smiles
Bring up the Devil and the ten commandments—
And so on—but I said the world must end.
I am sorry; it is such a pleasant world:
With all it faults it is perfect—to a fault:
And you, of course, end with it. Now how long
Will the world take to die? I know ye place
Great faith upon death-bed repentances;
The saddener the better. I know ye often
Begin to think of praying and repenting;
But second thoughts come and ye are worse than ever;
As over new white snow a filthy thaw.
Ye do amaze me verily. How long
Will ye take heart on your own wickedness,
And God’s forbearance? Have ye cast it up?
Come now; the year and month, day, hour and minute,
Sin’s golden cycle. Do ye know how long
Exactly Heaven will grant ye? how long God—
Who when he had slain the world and wasted it,
Hung up His bow in Heaven, as in his hall
A warrior after battle—will yet bear
Tour contumely and scorn of His best gifts—
Man’s mockery of man? But never mind!
Some of us are magnificently good,
And hold the head up high like a giraffe;
You, in particular, and you—and you.
Good men are here and there, I know; but then—
You must excuse me if I mention this—
My duty is to tell it you—the world,
Like a black block of marble, jagged with white,
As with a vein of lightning petrified,
Looks blacker than without such; looks in truth,
So gross the heathen, gross the Christian too—
Like the original darkness of void space,
Hardened. Instead of justice, love and grace,
Each worth to man the mission of a God,
Injustice, hate, uncharitableness,
Triequal reign round earth, a Trinity of Hell.
Ye think ye never can be bad enough:
And as ye sink in sin, ye rise in hope.
And let the worst come to the worst, you say,
There always will be time to turn ourselves,
And cry for half an hour or so to God:
Salvation, sure, is not so very hard—
It need not take one long; and half an hour
Is quite as much as we can spare for it.
We have no time for pleasures. Business! business!
No! ye she perish sudden and unsaved.
The priest shall, dipping, die. Can man save man?
Is water God? The counsellor, wise fool!
Drop down amid his quirks and sacred lies—
The judge, while dooming unto death some wretch,
Shall meet at once his own death, doom, and judge.
The doctor, watch in hand, and patient’s pulse,
Shall feel his own heart cease its beats—and fall:
Professors shall spin out, and students strain
Their brains no more; art, science, toil shall cease.
The world shall stand still with a rending jar,
As though it struck at sea. The halls where sit
The heads of nations shall be dumb with death.
The ship shall after her own plummet sink,
And sound the sea herself and depths, of death.
At the first turn Death shall cut off the thief,
And dash the gold bag in his yellow brain.
The gambler, reckoning gains, shall drop a piece;
Stoop down and there see death;—look up, there God.
The wanton, temporizing with decay,
And qualifying every line which vice
Writes bluntly on the brow, inviting scorn,
Shall pale through plastered red: and the loose, low sot
See clear, for once, through his misty, o’erbrimmed eye.
The just, if there be any, die in prayer.
Death shall be every where among your marts,
And giving bills which no man may decline—
Drafts upon Hell one moment after date.
Then shall your outcries tremble amid the stars:
Terrors shall be about ye like a wind:
And fears come down upon ye like a house.

Festus |

Yon man looks frightened.

Lucifer |

Then it is time to stop.
I hope I have done no good. He will soon forget
His soul. Flesh soaks it up as sponge does water.
Now wait! I will rub them backwards like a cat;
And you shall see them spit and sparkle up.
Let us suppose a case, friends! You are men;
And there is God! and I will be the Devil.
Very well. I am the Devil.

One |

Says.

I think you are.
You look as if you lived on buttered thunder.

Lucifer |

Nay, be not wroth. Ye would crucify the Devil,
I do believe, if he a moment vexed you.
I know well which ye choose: but choose again!
Time or eternity? Speak, Hell or Heaven?

The Crowd |

He’s a mad ranter: down with him!—

Festus |

Let him be!

Lucifer |

Stand by me, Festus, and I will by thee.
Why, God and man! this is the second time
That I have run for my life.

Festus |

Nay, nay, come back!
They will not harm thee: they would chair thee round
The market-place, knew they but whom thou art.
Peace, there my friends! one minute; let us pray!
Grant us, oh God! that in thy holy love
The universal people of the world
May grow more great and happy every day;
Mightier, wiser, humbler, too, towards Thee.
And that all ranks, all classes, callings, states
Of life, so far as such seem right to Thee,
May mingle into one, like sister trees,
And so in one stem flourish:—that all laws
And powers of government be based and used
In good and for the people’s sake;—that each
May feel himself of consequence to all,
And act as though all saw him;—that the whole,
The mass of every nation may so do
As is most worthy of the next to God;
For a whole people’s souls, each one worth more
Than a mere world of matter, make combined,
A something godlike—something like to Thee.
We pray thee for the welfare of all men.
Let monarchs who love truth and freedom feel
The happiness of safety and respect
From those they rule, and guardianship from Thee.
Let them remember they are set on thrones
As representatives, not substitutes
Of nations, to implead with God and man.
Let tyrants who hate truth, or fear the free,
Know that to rule in slavery and error,
For the mere ends of personal pomp and power,
Is such a sin as doth deserve a hell
To itself sole. Let both remember, Lord!
They are but things like-natured with all nations;
That mountains issue out of plains, and not
Plains out of mountains, and so likewise kings
Are of the people, not the people of kings.
And let all feel, the rulers and the ruled,
All classes and all countries, that the world
Is Thy great halidom; that Thou art King,
Lord! only owner and possessor. Grant
That nations may now see, it is not kings,
Nor priests they need fear so much as themselves;
That if they keep but true to themselves, and free,
Sober, enlightened, godly—mortal men
Become impassible as air, one great
And indestructible substance as the sea.
Let all on thrones and judgment-seats reflect
How dreadful Thy revenge through nations is
On those who wrong them; but do Thou grant, Lord!
That when wrongs are to be redressed, such may
Be done with mildness, speed, and firmness, not
With violence or hate, whereby one wrong
Translates another—both to Thee abhorrent.
The bells of time are ringing changes fast.
Grant, Lord! that each fresh peal may usher in
An era of advancement, that each change
Prove an effectual, lasting, happy gain.
And we beseech Thee, overrule, oh God!
All civil contests to the good of all;
All party and religious difference
To honourable ends, whether secured
Or lost; and let all strife, political
Or social, spring from conscientious aims,
And have a generous self-ennobling end,
Man’s good and Thine own glory in view always!
The best may then fail and the worst succeed
Alike with honour. We beseech Thee, Lord!
For bodily strength, but more especially
For the soul’s health and safety. We entreat Thee
In thy great mercy to decrease our wants,
And add autumnal increase to the comforts
Which tend to keep men innocent, and load
Their hearts with thanks to Thee as trees in bearing:—
The blessings of friends, families, and homes,
And kindnesses of kindred. And we pray
That men may rule themselves in faith in God,
In charity to each other, and in hope
Of their own souls’ salvation:—that the mass,
The millions in all nations may be trained,
From their youth upwards, in a nobler mode,
To loftier and more liberal ends. We pray
Above all things, Lord! that all men be free
From bondage, whether of the mind or body;—
The bondage of religious bigotry,
And bald antiquity, servility
Of thought or speech to rank and power; be all
Free as they ought to be in mind and soul
As well as by state-birthright;—and that Mind,
Time’s giant pupil, may right soon attain
Majority, and speak and act for himself!
Incline Thou to our prayers, and grant, oh Lord!
That all may have enough, and some safe mean
Of worldly goods and honours, by degrees,
Take place, if practicable, in the fitness
And fullness of Thy time. And we beseech Thee,
That Truth no more be gagged, nor conscience dungeoned,
Nor science be impeached of godlessness,
Nor faith be circumscribed, which as to Thee,
And the soul’s self affairs is infinite;
But that all men may have due liberty
To speak an honest mind, in every land,
Encouragement to study, leave to act
As conscience orders. We entreat Thee, Lord!
For Thy Son’s sake to take away reproach
Of all kinds from Thy church, and all temptation
Of pomp or power political, that none
May err in the end for which they were appointed
To any of its orders, low or high;
And no ambition, of a worldly cast,
Leaven the love of souls unto whose care
They feel propelled by Thy most holy spirit.
Be every church established, Lord! in truth.
Let all who preach the word, live by the word,
In moderate estate; and in Thy church—
One, universal, and invisible
World-wards, yet manifest unto itself,
May it seem good, dear Saviour, in Thy sight,
That orders be distinguished, not by wealth,
But piety and power of teaching souls.
Equalise labour, Lord! and recompence.
Let not a hundred humble pastors starve,
In this or any land of Christendom,
While one or two, impalaced, mitred, throned
And banqueted, burlesque if not blaspheme
The holy penury of the Son of God;
The fastings, the footwanderings, and the preachings
Of Christ and His first followers. Oh that the Son
Might come again! There should be no more war,
No more want, no more sickness; with a touch,
He should cure all disease, and with a word,
All sin; and with a look to Heaven, a prayer,
Provide bread for a million at a time.
But till that perfect advent grant us, Lord!
That all good institutions, orders, claims,
Charitably proposed, or in the aid
Of Thy divine foundation, may much prosper,
And more of them be raised and nobly filled;—
That Thy word may be taught throughout all lands,
And save souls daily to the thrones of Heaven!—
And we entreat Thee, that all men whom Thou
Hast gifted with great minds may love Thee well,
And praise Thee for their powers, and use them most
Humbly and holily, and, lever-like,
Act but in lifting up the mass of mind
About them; knowing well that they shall be
Questioned by Thee of deeds the pen hath done,
Or caused, or glozed; inspire them with delight
And power to treat of noble themes and things,
Worthily, and to leave the low and mean—
Things born of vice or day-lived fashion, in
Their naked native folly:—make them know
Fine thoughts are wealth, for the right use of which
Men are and ought to be accountable—
If not to Thee, to those they influence:
Grant this we pray Thee, and that all who read,
Or utter noble thoughts, may make them theirs,
And thank God for them, to the betterment
Of their succeeding life;—that all who lead
The general sense and taste, too apt, perchance,
To be led, keep in mind the mighty good
They may achieve, and are in conscience, bound,
And duty, to attempt unceasingly
To compass. Grant us, All-maintaining Sire!
That all the great mechanic aids to toil
Man’s skill hath formed, found, rendered—whether used
In multiplying works of mind, or aught
To obviate the thousand wants of life,
May much avail to human welfare now
And in all ages, henceforth and for ever!
Let their effect be, Lord! to lighten labour,
And give more room to mind, and leave the poor
Some time for self-improvement. Let them not
Be forced to grind the bones out of their arms
For bread, but have some space to think and feel
Like moral and immortal creatures. God!
Have mercy on them till such time shall come;
Look Thou with pity on all lesser crimes,
Thrust on men almost when devoured by want,
Wretchedness, ignorance and outcast life!
Have mercy on the rich, too, who pass by
The means they have at hand to fill their minds
With serviceable knowledge for themselves,
And fellows, and support not the good cause
Of the world’s better future! Oh, reward
All such who do, with peace of heart and power
For greater good. Have mercy, Lord! on each
And all, for all men need it equally.
May peace and industry and commerce weld
Into one land all nations of the world,
Rewedding those the Deluge once divorced.
Oh! may all help each other in good things,
Mentally, morally, and bodily!
Vouchsafe, kind God! Thy blessing to this isle,
Specially! May our country ever lead
The world, for she is worthiest; and may all
Profit by her example, and adopt
Her course, wherever great, or free, or just.
May all her subject colonies and powers
Have of her freedom freely, as a child
Receiveth of its parents. Let not rights
Be wrested from us to our own reproach,
But granted. We may make the whole world free,
And be as free ourselves as ever, more!
If policy or self-defence call forth
Our forces to the field, let us in Thee
Place, first, our trust, and in Thy name we shall
O’ercome, for we will only wage the right.
Let us not conquer nations for ourselves,
But for Thee, Lord! who hast predestined us
To fight the battles of the future now,
And so have done with war before Thou comest.
Till then, Lord God of armies, let our foes
Have their swords broken and their cannon burst,
And their strong cities levelled; and while we
War faithfully and righteously, improve,
Civilize, christianize the lands we win
From savage or from nature, Thou, oh God!
Wilt aid and hallow conquest, as of old,
Thine own immediate nation’s. But we pray
That all mankind may make one brotherhood,
And love and serve each other; that all wars
And feuds die out of nations, whether those
Whom the sun’s hot light darkens, or ourselves
Whom he treats fairly, or the northern tribes
Whom ceaseless snows and starry winters blench,
Savage or civilized—let every race,
Bed, black or white, olive, or tawny-skinned,
Settle in peace and swell the gathering hosts
Of the great Prince of Peace! Oh! may the hour
Soon come when all false gods, false creeds, false prophets—
Allowed in Thy good purpose for a time—
Demolished, the great world shall be at last,
The mercy-seat of God, the heritage
Of Christ, and the possession of the Spirit,
The comforter, the wisdom! shall all be
One land, one home, one friend, one faith, one law,
Its ruler God, its practice righteousness,
Its life peace! For the one true faith we pray
There is but one in Heaven and there shall be
But one on earth, the same which is in Heaven.
Prophecy is more true than history.
Grant us our prayers, we pray, Lord! in the name
And for the sake of Thy Son Jesus Christ,
Our Saviour and Redeemer, who with Thee,
And with the Holy Spirit, reigneth God
Over all worlds, one blessed Trinity!⸺

The Crowd |

Amen!

Lucifer |

Well, friends, we’ll sing a hymn; then part.
I give it out, and you sing—all of you.

Oh! Earth is cheating Earth
From age to age for ever;
She laughs at faith and worth,
And dreams she shall die never;
Never, never, never!
And dreams she shall die never.

And Hell is cursing Hell
From age to age for ever;
Its groans ring out the knell
Of souls that may die never;
Never, never, never!
Of souls that may die never.

But Heaven is blessing Heaven
From age to age for ever;
And its thanks to Qod are given
For bliss that can die never;
Never, never, never!
For bliss that can die never.

My blessing be upon ye all; now go!

Festus |

I wonder what these people make of thee.

Lucifer |

Ay, manner’s a great matter.

Festus |

They deserve
All the rebuke thou gavest them and more.
What mountains of delusion men have reared!
How every age hath bustled on to build
Its shadowy mole—its monumental dream!
How faith and faney, in the mind of man,
Have spuriously mingled, and how much
Shall pass away for aye, as pass before
Yon son, the Lord of steadfastness and change,
The visionary landscapes of the skies;—
The golden capes far stretching into Heaven,
The snow-piled cloud-crags, the bright winged isles
Which dot the deep, impassive, ocean air
Like a disbanded rainbow, of all hues,
Fit for translated fairy’s Paradise;—
Or as before the eye of musing child,
The faces Fancy forms in clouds and fire
Of glowing angel or of darkening fiend.
Arts, superstition, arms, philosophy,
Have each in turn possessed, betrayed, and mocked us,
Yes, vain philosophy, thine hour is come!
Thy lips were lined with the immortal lie,
And dyed with all the look of truth. Men saw,
Believed, embraced, detested, cast thee off.
Those lights, the morn of Truth’s immortal day,
As thou didst falsely swear them, have they not
Vanished, the mere auroras of the mind?
And thou didst vow to gather clear again
The fallen waters of humanity;
To smooth the flaw from out an eye; to piece
A pounded pearl. Thank God! I am a man;
Not a philosopher! Rivers may rot,
Never revive the root of oak firebolted.
Come, let us to the hills! where none but God
Can overlook us; for I hate to breathe
The breaths and think the thoughts of other men,
In close and clouded cities, where the sky
Frowns like an angry Father mournfully.
I love the hills and I love loneliness.
And oh! I love the woods, those natural fanes
Whose very air is holy; and we breathe
Of God; for He doth come in special place,
And, while we worship, He is there for us!

Lucifer |

It is time that something should be done for the poor.
The sole equality on earth is death;
Now, rich and poor are both dissatisfied.
I am for judgment: that will settle both.
Nothing is to be done without destruction.
Death is the universal salt of states;
Blood is tbe base of all things—law and war,
I could tame this lion age to follow me.
I should like to macadamize the world;
The road to Hell wants mending.

Festus |

Come away!

IX

Scene—A village feast. Evening.

Festus, Lucifer and others.
Festus |

It is getting dark. One has to walk quite close,
To see the pretty faces that we meet.

Lucifer |

A disagreeable necessity,
Truly.

Festus |

We’ll rest upon this bridge. I am tired.
Yon tall slim tree! does it not seem as made
For its place there, a kind of natural maypole?—
Beyond, the lighted stalls stored with the good
Things of our childhood’s world, and behind them,
The shouting showman and the clashing cymbal;
The open doored cottages and blazing hearth—
The little ones running up with naked feet,
And cake in either hand, to their mother’s lap—
Old and young laughing, schoolboys with their play-things,
Clowns cracking jokes, and lasses with sly eyes,
And the smile settling in their sunflecked cheeks,
Like noon upon the mellow apricot;—
Make up a scene I can for once give in to.
It must please all, the social and the selfish.
Are they not happy?

Lucifer |

Why, it matters not.
They seem so: that’s enough.

Festus |

But not the same.

Lucifer |

Yet truth and falsehood meet in seeming, like
The falling leaf and shadow on the pool’s face.
And these are joys, like beauty, but skin deep.

Festus |

Remove all such and what’s the joy of earth?
’Tis they create the appetite of life—
Give zest and relish to the lot of millions.
And take the taste for them away—what’s left?
A dry ungainly skeleton of soul.

Lucifer |

Power is aye above the soul and joy
Below it. Pleasure men prefer to power.

Children at play.
Festus |

Play away, good ones!

Old Man |

Pity the poor blind man!

Festus |

Here is substantial pity.

Old Man |

Heaven reward you!

Festus |

Blind as the blue skies after sunset. Blind!
And I am tired of looking on what is.
One might as well see beauty never more,
As look upon it with an empty eye.
I would this, world were over. I am tired.
Nought happens but what happens to one’s self;
And all hath happened I have wished, and more.
Our pleasures all pass from us, one by one,
With that relief which sighing gives the heart,
Though each sigh leaves it lower. It is sad
To think how few our pleasures really are:
And for the which we risk eternal good.
There’s nothing that can satisfy one’s self,
Except one’s self. Well, it is very sad,
And by the time we come of age we have felt
In one degree or other all that age
Can offer. We have reaped our field ere noon.
The rest is reproduction; sowing—reaping—
Losing again. Toil and gain tire alike.
We cannot live too slowly to be good
And happy, nor too much by line and square.
But youth is burning to forestall its nature,
And will not wait for time to ferry it
Over the stream, but flings itself into
The flood, and perishes. And yet, why not?
There is no charm in time as time, nor good.
The long days are no happier than the short ones.
’Tis sometime now since I was here. We leave
Our home in youth—no matter to what end;—
Study—or strife—or pleasure, or what not:
And coming back in few short years, we find
All as we left it, outside; the old elms,
The house, grass, gates, and latchet’s selfsame click:
But lift that latchet—all is changed as doom:
The servants have forgotten our step, and more
Than half of those who knew us know us not.
Adversity, prosperity, the grave,
Play a round game With friends. On some the world
Hath shot its evil eye, and they are passed
From honour and remembrance, and a stare
Is all the mention of their names receives;
And people know no more of them than of
The shapes of clouds at midnight, a year back.

Lucifer |

Let us move on to where the dancing is;
We soon shall see how happy they all are.
Here is a loving couple quarrelling.
And there, another. It is quite distressing.
See yonder. Two men fighting!

Festus |

What avail
These vile exceptions to the rule of joy?

Lucifer |

Behold the happiness of which thou spakest!
The highest hills are miles below the sky,
And so far is the lightest heart below
True happiness.

Festus |

This is a snakelike world,
And always hath its tail within its mouth,
As if it ate itself, and moralled time.
The world is like yon children’s merry-go-round;
What men admire are carriages and hobbies,
Which the exalted manikins enjoy.
There is a noisy ragged crowd below
Of urchins drives it round, who only get
The excitement for their pains—best gain perhaps:
For it is not they who labour that grow dizzy
Nor sick—that’s for the idle, proud above,
Who soon dismount, more weary of enjoying
Than those below of working; and but fair.
It is wretchedness or recklessness alone
Keeps us alive. Were we happy we should die.
Yet what is death? I like to think on death:
It is but the appearance of an apparition.
One ought to tremble; but oughts stand for nothing.
I hate the thought of wrinkling up to rest;
The toothlike aching ruin of the body,
With the heart all out, and nothing left but edge.
Give me the long high bounding feel of life,
Which cries, let me but leap unto my grave,
And I’ll not mind the when nor where. We never
Care less for life than when enjoying it.
Oh! I should love to die. What is to die?
I cannot hold the meaning more than can
An oak’s arms clasp the blast that blows on it.
There is an air-like something which must be.
And yet not to be seen, nor to be touched.
I am made up to die; for having been
Every thing, there is nothing left but nothing
To be again.

Lucifer |

Hark! here is a ballad-singer.

Ballad-Singer |

All of my own composing!

Festus |

Yes, Yes—we know.

Ballad-Singer |

My gipsy maid! my gipsy maid!
I bless and curse the day
I lost the light of life, and caught
The grief which maketh gray.
Would that the light which blinded me
Had saved me on my way!

My night-haired love! so sweet she was,
So fair and blithe was she;
Her smile was brighter than the moon’s,
Her eyes the stars might see.

I met her by her lane-spread tent,
Beside a moss-green stone,
And bade her make, not mock, my fate,
My fortune was her own.
Thou art but yet a boy, she said,
And I a woman grown.

I am a man in love, I cried;
My heart was early manned:
She smiled, and only drooped her eyes,
And then let go my hand.
We stood a minute: neither spake
What each must understand.

I told her, so she would be mine
And follow where I went,
She straight should have a bridal bower
Instead of gipsy tent.

Or would she have me wend with her,
The world between should fall;
For her I would fling up faith and friends,
And name, and fame, and all.

Her smile so bright froze while I spake,
And ice was in her eye;
So near, it seemed ere touch her heart
I might have kissed the sky.

I said that if she loved to rule,
Or if she longed to reign,
I would make her Queen of every race
Which tearhke trode the world’s sad face,
Or bleed at every vein.

She laid her finger on her lip,
And pointed to the sky;
There is no God to come, she said:
Dost thou not fear to die?

And what is God, I said, to thee?
Thy people worship not.
The good, the happy, and the free,
She said, they need no God.

I looked until I lost mine eyes;
I felt as though I were
In a dark cave, with one weak light—
The light of life—with her;
And that was wasting fast away;
I watched but would not stir.

Again she took my hand in hers,
And read it o’er and o’er;
Ah! eyes so young, so sweet, I said,
Make as they read love’s lore.

She held my hand—I trembled whilst—
For sorely soon I felt
She made the love-cross she foretold
And all the woe she dealt.

Unhappy I should be she said,
And young to death be given;
I told her I believed in her,
Not in the stars of Heaven.

Hush! we breathe Heaven, she said, and bowed;
And the stars speak through me.
Let Heaven, I cried, take care of Heaven!
I only care for thee.

She shrank: I looked, and begged a kiss:
I knew she had one for me;
She would deny me none, she said,
But give me none would she.

My gipsy mind! my gipsy maid!
’Tis three long years like this,
Since there I gave and got from thee
That meeting, parting kiss.

I saw the tears start in her eye,
And trickle down her cheek,
Like falling stars across the sky,
Escaping from their Maker’s eye:
I saw, but spared to speak.

Go, and forget! she said, and slid
Below her lowly tent.
I will not, cannot—hear me, girl!
She heard not, and I went.

At eve, by sunset, I was there,
The tent was there no more;
The fire which warmed her flickered still—
The fire she sat before.

I stood by it, till through the dark
I saw not where it lay;
And then like that my heart went out
In ashy grief and gray.

My gipsy maid! my gipsy maid!
Oh! let me bless this day;
This day it was I met thee first,
And yet it shall be and is cursed,
For thou hast gone away.

Lucifer |

Another, please—not quite so gloomy, friend.

Girl |

I wonder if the tale it tells be true.

Ballad-Singer |

I dare say—but you want a merrier.
Every man’s life has its apocrypha;
Mine has, at least. I have said more than need be.
It happened, too, when I was very young.
We never meet such gipsies when we are old;
And yet we more complain of youth than age.
Now, make a ring, good people. Let me breathe! Sings.

Oh! the wee green neuk, the sly green neuk,
The wee sly neuk for me!
Whare the wheat is wavin’ bright and brown,
And the wind is fresh and free.
Whare I weave wild weeds, and out o’ reeds
Kerve whissles as I lay;
And a douce low voice is murmurin’ by
Through the lee-lang simmer day.
Oh! the wee green neuk, etc.

And whare a’ things luik as though they lo’ed
To languish in the sun;
And that if they feed the fire they dree,
They wadna ae pang were gone.
Whare the lift aboon is still as death,
And bright as life can be;
While the douce low voice says, na, na, na!
But ye mauna luik sae at me.
Oh! the wee green neuk, etc.

Whare the lang rank bent is saft and cule,
And freshenin’ till the feet;
And the spot is sly, and the spinnie high,
Whare my luve and I mak seat:
And I teaze her till she rins, and then
I catch her roun’ the tree;
While the poppies shak’ their heids and blush:
Let ’em blush till they drap, for me!
Oh! the wee green neuk, etc.

Festus |

And all who know such feelings and such scenes
Will, I am sure, reward you. Here—take this.

Others |

And this, and this—too!

Ballad-Singer |

Thank ye all, good friends!

Festus |

There’s much that hath no merit but its truth,
And no excuse but nature. Nature does
Never wrong: ’tis society which sins.
Look on the bee upon the wing among flowers;
How brave, how bright his life! Then mark him hived,
Cramped, cringing in his self built, social cell.
Thus is it in the world-hive: most where men
Lie deep in cities as in drifts—death drifts,
Nosing each other like a flock of sheep;
Not knowing and not caring whence nor whither
They come or go, so that they fool together.

Lucifer |

It is quite fair to halve these lives and say
This side is nature’s, that society’s,
When both are side-views only of one thing.

Farmer |

I am glad to see you come among us, sir.

Parson |

Why, I have but little comfort in these pastimes;
And any heart, turned Godwards, feels more joy
In one short hour of prayer, than e’er was raised
By all the feasts on earth since their foundation.
But no one will believe us; as if we
Had never known the vain things of the world,
Nor lain and slept in sin’s seducing shade,
Listless, until God woke us; made us feel
We should be up and stirring in the sun;
For every thing had to be done ere night.
What is all this joy and jollity about?
Grant there may be no sin. What good is it?

Farmer |

I can’t defend these feasts, Sir, and can’t blame.

Parson |

Good evening, friends! Why, Festus! I rejoice
We meet again. I have a young friend here,
A student—who hath staid with us of late.
You would be glad, I know, to know each other.
Therefore be known so.

Festus |

You are a student, Sir.

Student |

I profess little; but it is a title
A man may claim perhaps with modesty.

Festus |

True. All mankind are students. How to live
And how to die forms the great lesson still.
I know what study is: it is to toil
Hard, through the hours of the sad midnight watch,
At tasks which seem a systematic curse,
And course of bootless penance. Night by night,
To trace one’s thought as if on iron leaves;
And sorrowful as though it were the mode
And date of death we wrote on our own tombs:
Wring a slight sleep out of the couch, and see
The self-same moon, which lit us to our rest,
Her place scarce changed perceptibly in Heaven.
Now light us to renewal of our toils.—
This, to the young mind, wild and all in leaf,
Which knowledge, grafting, paineth. Fruit soon comes,
And more than all our troubles pays us powers;
So that we joy to have endured so much:
That not for nothing have we slaved and slain
Ourselves almost. And more; it is to strive
To bring the mind up to one’s own esteem:
Who but the generous fail? It is to think,
While thought is standing thick upon the brain
As dew upon the brow—for thought is brain-sweat;
And gathering quick and dark, like storms in summer,
Until convulsed, condensed, in lightning sport,
It plays upon the heavens of the mind—
Opens the hemisphered abysses here,
And we become revealers to ourselves.

Student |

When night hath set her silver lamp on high,
Then is the time for study; when Heaven’s light
Pours itself on the page, like prophecy
On time, unglooming all its mighty meanings;
It is then we feel the sweet strength of the stars,
And magic of the moon.

Lucifer |

It’s a bad habit.

Student |

And wisdom dwells in secret and on high,
As do the stars. The sun’s diurnal glare
Is for the daily herd; but for the wise,
The cold pure radiance of the night-born light,
Wherewith is inspiration of the truth.
There was a time when I would never go
To rest before the sun rose; and for that,
Through a like length of time as that now gone,
The world shall speak of me six thousand years hence.

Lucifer |

How know you that the world wont end to-morrow?

Parson |

I now, an early riser, love to hail
The dreamy struggles of the stars with light,
And the recovering breath of earth, sleep-drowned,
Awakening to the wisdom of the sun,
And life of light within the tent of Heaven;—
To kiss the feet of Morning as she walks
In dewy light along the hills, while they,
All odorous as an angel’s fresh-culled crown,
Unveil to her their bounteous loveliness.

Student |

I am devote to study. Worthy books
Are not companions—they are solitudes:
We lose ourselves in them and all our cares.
The further back we search the human mind—
Mean in the mass, but in the instance great—
Which starting first with Deities and stars
And broods of beings earth-born, Heaven-begot,
And all the bright side of the broad world, now
Boats upon dreams and dim atomic truths,
Is all for comfort and no more for glory—
The nobler and more marvellous it shews.
Trifles like these make up the present time;
The Iliad and the Pyramids the past.

Festus |

The future will have glory not the less.
I can conceive a time when the world shall be
Much better visibly, and when, as far
As social life and its relations tend,
Men, morals, manners shall be lifted up
To a pure height we know not of nor dream;—
When all men’s rights and duties shall be clear,
And charitably exercised and borne;
When education, conscience, and good deeds
Shall have just equal sway, and civil claims;—
Great crimes shall be cast out, as were of old
Devils possessing madmen:—Truth shall reign,
Nature shall be rethroned, and man sublimed.

Student |

Oh! then may Heaven come down again to earth;
And dwell with her, as once, like to a friend.

Lucifer |

As like each other as a sword and scythe.
Oh! then shall lions mew and lambkins roar!

Festus |

And having studied—what next?

Student |

Much I long
To view the capital city of the world.
The mountains, the great cities, and the sea,
Are each an era in the life of youth.

Festus |

There to get worldly ways, and thoughts, and schemes;
To learn to detect, distrust, despise mankind—
To ken a false factitious glare amid much
That shines with seeming saintlike purity—
To gloss misdeeds—to trifle with great truths—
To pit the brain against the heart, and plead
Wit before wisdom—these are the world’s ways:
It learns us to lose that in crowds which we
Must after seek alone—our innocence;
And when the crowd is gone.

Student |

Not only that:
There all great things are round one. Interests.
Mighty and mountainous of estimate,
Are daily heaped or scattered ’neath the eye.
Great deeds, great thoughts, great schemes, and crimes, and all
Which is in purpose, or in practice, great
Of human nature—there are common things.
Men make themselves be deathless as in spite;
As if they waged some lineal feud with time;
As though their fathers were immortal, too,
And immortality an every-day
Accomplishment.

Festus |

Fie! fie! ’tis more for this:
Amid gayer people and more wanton ways,
To give a loose to all the lists of youth—
To tr your passion flowers high ahead,
And bind them on your brow as others do.
The mornlit revel and the shameless mate—
The tabled hues of darkness and of blood—
The published bosom and the crowning smile—
The cup excessive; and if aught there be
More vain than these or wanton—that to have—
Have all but always in intent, effect,
Or fact. Nay, nay, deny it not: I know.
Youth hath a strange and strong desire to try
All feelings on the heart: it is very wrong,
And dangerous, and deadly: strive against it!

Student |

It might be some old sage was warning us.

Festus |

Youth might be wise. We suffer less from pains
Than pleasures.

Student |

I should like to see the world,
And gain that knowledge which is—

Festus |

Barrener
Than ice; possessing and producing nought
But means and forms of death or vanity.
The world is just as hollow as an eggshell.
It is a surface not a solid, mind:
And all this boasted knowledge of the world
To me seems but to mean acquaintance with
Low things, or evil, or indifferent.

Farmer |

Much more is said of knowledge than it’s worth.
A man may gain all knowledge here, and yet
Be, after death, as much in the dark as I.

Lucifer |

What makes you know of living after death?

Farmer |

Why, nothing that I know; and there it is—
But something I am told has told me so.
No angel ever came to me to prove it;
And all my friends have died, and left no ghosts.

Festus |

All that is good a man may learn from himself;
And much, too, that is bad.

Parson |

Nay, let me speak!
Aught that is good the soul receives of God
When He hath made it His; and until then
Man cannot know, nor do, nor be, aught good.
Oh! there is nought on earth worth being known
But God and our own souls—the God we have
Within our hearts; for it is not the hope,
Nor faith, nap fear, nor notions others have
Of God can serve us, but the sense and soul
We have of Him within us; and, for men,
God loves us men each individually,
And deals with us in order, soul by soul.

Lucifer |

What are your politics?

Farmer |

I have none.

Lucifer |

Good.

Farmer |

I have my thoughts. I am no party man.
I care for measures more than men, but think
Some little may depend upon the men;
Something in fires depends upon the grate.

First Boy |

What are your colours?

Second Boy |

Blue as Heaven.

Third Boy |

And mine
Are yellow as the sun.

First Boy |

Mine, green as grass.

Second Boy |

Green’s forsaken, and yellow’s forsworn,
And blue’s the colour that shall be worn.

Student |

As to religion, politics, law, and war,
But little need be said. All are required,
And all are well enough. Of liberty,
And slavery, and tyranny we hear
Much; but the human mind affects extremes.
The heart is in the middle of the system;
And all affections gather round the truth,
The moderated joys and woes of life.
I love my God, my country, kind and kin,
Nor would I see a dog wronged of his bone.
My country! if a wretch should e’er arise,
Out of thy countless sons, who would curtail
Thy freedom, dim thy glory—while he lives
May an earth’s peoples curse him—for of all
Hast thou secured the blessing;—and if me
Exist who would not arm for liberty,
Be he too cursed living, and when dead,
Let him be buried downwards, with his face
Looking to Hell, and o’er his coward grave
The hare skulk in her form.

Lucifer |

Nay, gently, friend.
Curse nothing, not the Devil. He’s beside you—
For aught you know.

Student |

I neither know nor care.

They pass some card-players.
Festus |

Kings, queens, knaves, tens would trick the world away,
And it were not, now and then, for some brave ace.

Student |

You see yon wretched starved old man; his brow
Grooved out with wrinkles, like the brown dry sand
The tide of life is leaving?

Lucifer |

Yes, I see him.

Student |

Last week he thought he was about to die;
So he bade gold be strewn beneath his pillow,
Gold on a chest that he might lie and see,
And gold put in a basin on his bed,
That he might dabble with his fingers in.
He’s going now to grope for pence or pins.
He never gave a pin’s worth in his life.
What would you do to him?

Lucifer |

I would have him wrought
Into a living wire, which, beaten out,
Might make a golden network for the world;
Then melt him inch by inch and hell by hell,
Where is the law of wrath.

Student |

Oh, charity!
It is a thought the Devil might be proud of—
Once and away. Misers and spendthrifts may
Torment each other in the world to come.

Festus |

Men look on death as lightning, always far
Off, or in Heaven. They know not it is in
Themselves, a strong and inward tendency,
The soul of every atom, every hair:
That nature’s infinite electric life,
Escaping from each isolated frame,
Up out of earth, or down from Heaven, becomes
To each its proper death, and adds itself
Thus to the great reunion of the whole.
There is a man in mourning! What does he here?

Student |

He has just buried the only friend he had,
And now comes hither to enjoy himself.

Festus |

Why will we dedicate the dead to God,
And not ourselves, the living? Oft we speak,
With tears of joy and trust, of some dear friend
As surely up in Heaven; while that same soul,
For aught we know, may be shuddering even in Hell
To hear his name named; or there may be no
Soul in the case—and the fat icy worm,
Give him a tongue, can tell us all about him.

Student |

Here is music. Stay. That simple melody
Comes on the heart like infant innocence—
Fore feeling pure; while yet the new-bodied soul
Is swinging to the motion of the heavens,
And scarce hath caught, as yet, earth’s backening course.

Festus |

The heart is formed as earth was—its
Formless and void, and fit but for itself;
Then feelings half alive, just organized,
Come next—then creeping sports and purposes—
Then animal desires, delights, and loves—
For love is the first and granite-like effect
Of things—the longest and the highest: next
The wild and winged desires, youth’s saurian schemes,
Which creep and fly by turns; which kill, and eat,
And do disgorge each other: comes at length
The mould of perfect matchless manhood—then
Woman divides the heart, and multiplies it.
The insipidity of innocence
Palls: it is guilty, happy, and undone.
A death is laid upon it, and it goes—
Quits its green Eden for the sandy world,
Where it works out its nature, as it may,
In sweat, smiles, blood, tears, cursings, and what not.
And giant sins possess it; and it worships
Works of the hand, head, heart—its own or others—
A creature worship, which excludeth God’s:
The less thrusts out the greater. Warning comes,
But the heart fears not—feels not; till at last
Down comes the flood from Heaven; and that heart,
Broken inwards, earthlike, to its central hell;
Or like the bright and burning eye we see
Inly, when pressed hard backwards on the brain,
Ends and begins again—destroyed, is saved.
Every man is the first man to himself,
And Eves are just as plentiful as apples;
Nor do we fall, nor are we saved by proxy.
The Eden we live in is our own heart;
And the first thing we do, of our free choice,
Is sure and necessary to be sin.

Lucifer |

The only right me have is to be damned.
What is the good of music, or the beauty?
Music tells no truths.

Festus |

Oh! there is nought so sweet
As lying and listening music from the hands,
And singing from the lips, of one we love—
Lips that all others should be turned to. Then
The world would all be love and song; Heaven’s harps
And orbs join in: the whole be harmony—
Distinct, yet blended—blending all in one
Long and delicious tremble like a chord.
But to Thee, God! all being is a harp,
Whereon Thou makest mightiest melody.
Hast ever been in love?

Student |

I never was.

Festus |

’Tis love which mostly destinates our life.
What makes the world it after life I know not,
For our horizon alters as we age:
Power only can make up for the lack of love—
Power of some sort. The mind at one time grows
So fast, it fails; and then its stretch is more
Than its strength; but, as it opes, love fills it up,
Like to the stamen in the flower of life,
Till for the time we well-nigh grow all love;
And soon we feel the want of one kind heart
To love what’s well, and to forgive what’s ill,
In us—that heart we play for at all risks.

Student |

How can the heart which lies embodied deep,
In blood and bone, set like a ruby eye
Into the breast, be made a toy for beauty,
And, vane-like, blown about by every wanton sigh?
How can the soul, the rich star-travelled stranger,
Who here sojourneth only for a purchase,
Risk all the riches of his years of toil,
And his God-vouched inheritance of Heaven,
For one light momentary taste of love?

Festus |

It is so; and when once you know the sport—
The crowded pack of passions in full cry—
The sweet deceits, the tempting obstacles—
The smile, the sigh, the tear, and the embrace—
All the delights of love at last in one,
With kisses close as stars in the milky way,
In at the death you cry, though ’twere your own!

Student |

Upon my soul, most sound morality!
Nothing is thought of virtue, then, nor judgment?

Festus |

Oh! everything is thought of—but not then,
And—judgment—no! it is nowhere in the field.

Student |

Slow-paced and late arriving, still it comes.
I cannot understand this love; I hear
Of its idolatry, not its respect.

Festus |

Respect is what we owe; love what we give.
And men would mostly rather give than pay.
Morality’s the right rule for the world,
Nor could society cohere without
Virtue; and there are those whose spirits walk
Abreast of angels and the future, here.
Respect and love thou such.

Lucifer |

Of course you wish
Women to love you rather than love them.
It is better. Now, you say you are a student.
All things take study; what more than the face—
Whether year own, or hers you look and long at?
There are many ways to one end: here is one:—
You are good-looking; but that matters little:
It only pleases them. To please yourself
Your face may be as ugly as the—. Well, well;
But you must cultivate yourself: it will pay you.
Study a dimple; work hard at a smile:
The things most delicate require most pains.
Practice the upward—now the sidelong glance—
Now the long passionful unwinking gaze,
Which beats itself at last, and sees air only.
Be restless, and distress yourself for her.
Take up her hand—press it, and pore on it—
Let it drop—snatch it again as though you had
Let slip so much of honor or of Heaven.
Swear—vow by all means—never miss an oath:
If broken, why it only spoils itself;
It is a broken oath and not an whole one.
Frown—toss about—let her lips be for a time:
But steal a kiss at last like fire from Heaven.
Weep if you can, and call the tears heat-drops.
Droop your head—sigh deep—play the fool, in short,
One hour, and she will play the fool for ever.
Mind! it is folly to tell women truth;
They would rather live on lies so they be sweet.
Never be long in one mind to one love.
You change your practice with your subject. All
Differ. But yet, who knows one woman well
By heart, knows all. It is my experience;
And I advise on good authority.
So thank me for my lecture on delusion.

Festus |

Time laughs at love. It is a hateful sight,
That bald old grey-beard jeering the boy, Love.
But as to women: that game has two sides.
Passion is om affection; and there is nought
So maddening and so lowering as to have
The worse in passion. Think, when one by one,
Pride, love, and jealousy, and fifty more
Great feelings column up to force a heart.
And all are beaten back—all fail—all fail:
The tower intact: but risk it: we must learn.
To know the world, be wise and be a fool.
The heart will have its swing—the world its way:
Who seeks to stop them, only throws himself down.
We must take as we find: go as they go,
Or stand aside. Let the world have the wall.
How do you think, pray, to get through the world?

Student |

I mean not to get through the world at all,
But over it.

Festus |

Aspiring! You will find
The world is all up-hill when we would do;
All down-hill when we suffer. Nay, it will part
Like the Red Sea, so that the poor may pass.
We make our compliments to wretchedness,
And hope the poor want nothing, and are well.
But I mean, what profession will you choose?
Surely you will do something for a name.

Student |

Names are of much more consequence than things.

Festus |

Well; here’s our honest, all-exhorting friend
The parson—here the doctor. I am sure
The Devil might act as moderator there,
And do mankind some service.

Lucifer |

In his way.

Student |

But I care neither for men’s souls nor bodies.

Festus |

What say you to the law? are you ambitious?

Student |

Nor do I mind for other people’s business.
I have no heart for their predicaments:
I am for myself. I measure ever thing
By, what is it to me? from which I find
I have but little in common with the mass,
Except my meals and so forth; dress and sleep.
I have that within me I can live upon:
Spider-like, spin my place out anywhere.

Festus |

To none of all die arts and sciences—
Astronomy nor entomology,
Nor gunnery, for instance, then you feel
Attracted heartily and mentally?

Student |

Why no; there are so many rise and fall,
One knows not which to choose. As for the stars,
I never look on them without dismay.
Earth has outrun them in our modern mind,
By worlds of odds. Enough for us, it seems,
And our cold calculators to jot down
Their revolutions, distances, and squares;—
And the bright laws which stars and spirits rule,
Are all laid out and buried grave on grave.
The fourfold worlds and elemental spheres,
Which in concentric circles, like the ring
That the magician stands in, from on high
Give spiritual calling to our earth,
And lord it over her, yet in such wise,
That still by them we may conjoin our souls
Unto the starry spirits of all worlds;
Beyond the changed mansions of the moon,
Beyond the burning heart of heaven, where dwell
The governors of nature and the blest,
All knowing spirits and celestial,
And divine demons; are all gone—extinct.
There is no danger now of knowing aught
Which ought not to be known. No more of that!—
And you, ye planetary sons of light!
From him who hovereth, moth-like, round the sun
To six-mooned Uranus, Light’s loftiest round.
Tour aspects, dignities, ascendancies,
Tour partile quartiles, and your plastic trines,
And all your Heavenly houses and effects,
Shall meet no more devout expounders here.
You too, ye juried signs, earth’s sunny path
Upon her wheeling orbit, all farewell!
Your exaltations and triplicities,
Fiery, airy, and the rest; your falls,
And detriments, and governments, and gifts,
Are all abolished. Henceforth ye shall shine
In vain to man. Diurnal, cardinal,
Nocturnal, equinoctial, hot or dry,
Earthy, or moist, or feminine, or fixed,
Luxurious, violent, bicorporate,
Masculine, barren, and commanding, cold,
Fruitful or watery, or what not, now
It matters nothing. The joy of Jupiter,
The exaltation of the Dragon’s head,
The sun’s triplicity and glorious
Day house on high, the moon’s dim detriment,
And all the starry inclusions of all signs—
Shall rise, and rule, and pass, and no one know
That there are spirit-rulers of all worlds,
Which fraternise with earth, and, though unknown,
Hold in the shining voices of the stars
Communion on high, ever and everywhere.—
The mystic charm of numbers, and the sole
Oneness which is in all, of nature’s great
Triadic principle, in all things, seen;
In man thus, as composed of thrice three forms
Intrinsic; first, corporeally, blood,
Body, and bones; next, intellectively,
Imagination, judgment, memory;
And thirdly, spiritually, mind and soul,
And spirit, which unites with God the whole
Being, and comes from and returns to Him—
Allures no more man’s mind debased. Thus, too,
Of alchemy; the golden starry stone,
Invisible, the principle of life,
The quintessence of all the elements,
Is still unbought;—still flows the stream of pearl
Beneath the magic mountain; still the scent
As of a thousand amaranthine wreaths, which lures
All life unto its sweetness, floats around
Mistlike, the shining bath where Luna laves,
Or Sol, bright brother of that mooned maid,
Triumphs in light;—the spiritual sun,
The Heavenly Earth smaragdine, and the fire
Spirit of life, the live land still exist,
Immortally, internally unseen.—
Still breathes the Paradisal air around
The universal whole; the watery fire,
Destructive, yet impalpable to sense,
The initial and conclusion of the world,
Yea, the beginning and the end of Death,
The secret which is shared ’tween God and man,
And which is nature only, wholly, still
In Heavenly gloom incomprehensible
Wait the Deific will; yea, still the light
Whereto all elements contribute, burns
About us and within us, world and soul;—
The primal sperm and matter of the world,
Whose centre is the limit of all things—
The snowy gold, the star and spirit seed
Which is to render rich and deathless all—
The self-begot, self-wedded, and self-born,
Which the wind carries in its womb, all have,
And few receive; the spirit of the earth,
The water of immortal life still lives:—
The universal solvent of disease
Still bounds through nature’s veins; and still, in fine,
The secrets only to be told by fire
Starry or beamless, central and extreme,
Burn to be born. And other natures may
Use them, and do. In Demogorgon’s hall
Still sits the universal mystery
Throned in itself and ministered unto
By its own members:—Man, alas! alone,
The recreant spirit of the universe,
Contemns the operations of the light;
Loves surface-knowledge; calls the crimes of crowds
Virtue: adores the useful vices; licks
The gory dust from off the feet of war,
And swears it food for gods, though fit for fiends
Only:—reversing just the Devil’s state
When first he entered on this orb of man’s—
A fallen angel’s form, a reptile’s soul.

Lucifer |

Oh! this is libellous to man and fiend
And brute together.

Student |

All are art and part
Of the same mystic treason. But enough;—
The most material, immaterial
Departments of pure wisdom are despised.
For well we know that, properly prepared,
Souls self-adapted knowledge to receive
Are by the truth desired, illumined; man’s
Spirit, extolled, dilated, clarified,
By holy meditation and divine
Lore, fits him to convene with purer powers
Which do unseen surround us aye and gladden
In human good and exaltation; thus
The face of Heaven is not more clear to one,
Than to another outwardly; but one
By strong intention of his soul perceives,
Attracts, unites himself to essences
And elemental spirits of wider range
And more beneficent nature, by whose aid
Occasion, circumstance, futurity
Impress on him their image, and impart
Their secrets to his soul; thus chance and lot
Are sacred things; thus dreams are verities.
But oh! alas for all earth’s loftier lore,
And spiritual sympathy of worlds!—
There shall be no more magic nor cabala,
Nor Rosicrucian nor Alchymic lore,
Nor fairy fantasies; no more hobgoblins,
Nor ghosts, nor imps, nor demons. Conjurors.
Enchanters, witches, wizards, shall all die
Hopeless and heirless; their divining arts
Supernal or infernal—dead with them.
And so ’twill doubtless be with other things
In time; therefore I will commit my brain
To none of them.

Festus |

Perchance ’twere wiser not.
Man’s heart hath not half uttered itself yet,
And much remains to do as well as say.
The heart is some time ere it finds its focus.
And when it does, with the whole light of nature
Strained through it to a hair’s breadth, it but burns
The things beneath it, which it lights to death.
Well, farewell, Mr. Student. May you never
Regret those hours which make the mind, if they
Unmake the body; for the sooner we
Are fit to be all mind, the better. Blest
Is he whose heart is the home of the great dead,
And their great thoughts. Who can mistake great thoughts?
They seize upon the mind—arrest, and search,
And shake it—bow the tall soul as by wind—
Rush over it like rivers over reeds,
Which quaver in the current—turn us cold,
And pale, and voiceless; leaving in the brain
A rocking and a ringing—glorious,
But momentary, madness might it last,
And close the soul with Heaven as with a seal!
In lieu of all these things whose loss thou mournest,
If earnestly or not I know not, use
The great and good and true which ever live,
And are all common to pure eyes and true.
Upon the summit of each mountain-thought
Worship thou God; for Deity is seen
From every elevation of the soul.
Study the Light; attempt the high; seek out
The soul’s bright path; and since the soul is fire
Of heat intelligential, turn it aye
To the all-Fatherly source of light and life;
Piety purifies the soul to see
Perpetual apparitions of all grace
And power, which to the sight of those who dwell
In ignorant sin are never known. Obey
Thy genius, for a minister it is
Unto the throne of Fate. Draw to thy soul,
And centralise the rays which are around
Of the Divinity. Keep thy spirit pure
From worldly taint by the repellant strength
Of virtue. Think on noble thoughts and deeds,
Ever. Count o’er the rosary of truth;
And practice precepts which are proven wise.
It matters not then what thou fearest. Walk
Boldly and wisely in that light thou hast;—
There is a hand above will help thee on.
I am an omnist, and believe in all
Religions—fragments of one golden world
Yet to be relit in its place in Heaven—
For all are relatively true and false,
As evidence and earnest of the heart
To those who practice, or have faith in them.
The absolutely true religion is
In Heaven only, yea in Deity.
But foremost of all studies, let me not
Forget to bid thee learn Christ’s faith by heart.
Study its truths, and practice its behests:
They are the purest, sweetest, peacefullest,
Of all immortal reasons or records:
They will be with thee when all else have gone.
Mind, body, passion, all wear out—not faith,
Nor truth. Keep thy heart cool, or rule its heat
To fixed ends: waste it not upon itself.
Not all the agony of all the damned,
Fused in one pang, vies with that earthquake throb
Which wakens it from waste to let us see
The world rolled by for aye; and that we must
Wait an eternity for our next chance,
Whether it be in Heaven or elsewhere.

Student |

Sir,
I will remember this most grave advice,
And think of you with all respect.

Festus |

Well, mind!
The worst men often give the best advice.
Our deeds are sometimes better than our thoughts.
Commend me, friend, to every one you meet:
I am an universal favourite.
Old men admire me deeply for my beauty,
Young women for my genius and strict virtue,
And young men for my modesty and wisdom.
All turn to me, whenever I speak, full-faced,
As planets to the sun, or owls to a rushlight.
Farewell!

Student |

I hope to meet again.

Festus |

And I.—
Yonder’s a woman singing. Let us hear her.

Ballad-Singer |

In the gray church tower
Were the clear bells ringing
When a maiden sat in her lonely bower
Sadly and lowly singing,
And thus she sang, that maiden fair,
Of the soft blue eyes and the long light hair:

This hand hath oft been held by one
Who now is far away;
And here I sit and sigh alone
Through all the weary day.
Oh, when will he I love return!
Oh, when shall I forget to mourn!

Along the dark and dizzy path
Ambition madly runs,
’Tis there they say his course he hath,
And therefore love he shuns.
Oh, fame and honour bind his brow,
For so he would be with me now!

In the gray church tower
Were the dear bells ringing,
When a bounding step in that lonely bower
Broke on the maiden singing;
She turned, she saw; oh, happy fair!
For her love who loved her so well was there!

Lucifer |

And we might trust these youths and maidens fair,
The world was made for nothing bat love, love!
Now I think it was made but to be burned.

Festus |

And if I love not now, while woman is
All bosom to the young, when shall I love?
Who ever paused on passion’s fiery wheel?
Or trembling by the side of her he loved
Whose lightest touch brings all but madness, ever
Stopped coldly short to reckon up his pulse?
The car comes—and we lie—and let it come;
It crushes—kills—what then! It is joy to die.
Enough shall not fool me. I fling the foil
Away. Let me but look on aught which casts
The shadow of a pleasure, and here I bare
A breast which would embrace a bride of fire.
Pleasure—we part not! No! It were easier
To wring God’s lightnings from the grasp of God.
I must be mad; but so is all the world.
Folly. It matters not. What is the world
To me? Nought. I am all things to myself.
If my heart thundered, would the world rock? Well—
Then let the mad world fight its shadow down;
There soon will be nor sun, nor world, nor shadow.
And thou, my blood, my bright red running soul—
Rejoice thou, like a river in thy rapids!
Rejoice—thou wilt never pale with age, nor thin;
But in thy full dark beauty, vein by vein,
Fold by fold, serpent-like, encircling me
Like a stag, sunstruck, top thy bounds and die.
Throb, bubble, sparkle, laugh and leap along!
Make merry while the holidays shall last.
Heart! I could tear thee out, thou fool! thou fool!
And strip thee into shreds upon the wind:
What have I done that thou shouldst serve me thus?

Lucifer |

Let us away. We have had enough of this.

Festus |

The night is glooming on us. It is the hour
When lovers will speak lowly, for the sake
Of being nigh each other; and when love
Shoots up the eye like morning on the east,
Making amends for the long northern night
They passed ere either knew the other loved.
It is the hour of hearts, when all hearts feel
As they could love to mad death, finding aught
To give back fire; for love, like nature, is
War—sweet war! Arms! To arms! so they be
Woman! Old people may say what they please—
The heart of age is like an emptied wine-cup,
Its life lies in a heel-tap—how can they judge?
’Twere a waste of time to ask how they wasted theirs.
But while the blood is bright, breath sweet, skin smooth,
And limbs all made to minister delight—
Ere yet we have shed our locks like trees their leaves,
And we stand staring bare into the air—
He is a fool who is not for love and beauty.
I speak unto the young, for I am of them,
And alway shall be. What are years to me?
Traitors! that vice-like fang the hand ye lick:
Ye fall like small birds beaten by a storm
Against a dead wall, dead. I pity ye.
Oh! that such mean things should raise hope or fear;
Those Titans of the heart, that fight at Heaven
And sleep by fits on fire; whose slightest stir’s
An earthquake. I am bound and blest to youth!
Oh! give me to the young—the fair—the free—
The brave, who would breast a rushing burning world
Which came between them and their hearts’ delight.
None but the brave and beautiful can love.
Oh, for the young heart like a fountain playing!
Flinging its bright fresh feelings up to the skies
It loves and strives to reach—strives, loves in vain:
It is of earth, and never meant for Heaven.
Let us love both, and die. The sphinx-like heart,
Consistent in its inconsistency,
Loathes life the moment that life’s riddle is read:
The knot of our existence is untied,
And we lie loose and useless. Life is had;
And then we sigh, and say, can this be all?
It is not what we thought—it is very well—
But we want something more—there is but death.
And when we have said, and seen, and done, and had,
Enjoyed and suffered, all we have wished and feared—
From fame to ruin, and from love to loathing—
There can come but one more change—try it—death.
Oh! it is great to feel we care for nothing—
That hope, nor love, nor fear, nor aught of earth
Can check the royal lavishment of life;
But like a streamer strown upon the wind,
We fling our souls to fate and to the future.
And to die young is youth’s divinest gift—
To pass from one world fresh into another,
Ere change hath lost the charm of soft regret,
And feel the immortal impulse from within
Which makes the coming, life—cry, alway, on!
And follow it while strong—is Heaven’s last mercy.
There is a fire-fly in the southern clime
Which shineth only when upon the wing;
So is it with the mind: when once we rest,
We darken. On! said God unto the soul
As to the earth, for ever. On it goes,
A rejoicing native of the infinite—
As a bird of air—an orb of heaven.

X

Scene—The centre.

Festus and Lucifer.
Lucifer |

Behold us in the fire-crypts of the world!
Through seas and buried mountains tomblike tracts,
Fit to receive the skeleton of Death
When he is dead—through earthquakes, and the bones
Of earthquake-swallowed cities, have we wormed
Down to the ever burning forge of fire,
Whereon in awful and omnipotent ease
Nature, the delegate of God, brings forth
Her everlasting elements, and breathes
Around that fluent heat of life which clothes
Itself in lightnings, wandering through the air,
And pierces to the last and loftiest pore
Of Earth’s snow-mantled mountains. In these vaults
Are hid the archives of the universe;
And here, the ashes of all ages gone,
Each finally inurned. These pillars stand,
Earth’s testimony to eternity.

Festus |

All that is solid now was fluid once;
Water, or air, or fire, or some one
Permanent, permeating, element;
As in this focal, world-evolving fire
Like what I see around—the vacuous power
Whereon the world is based, e’en as wherein
It rolls, I must believe.

Lucifer |

The original
Of all things is one thing. Creation is
One whole. The differences a mortal sees
Are diverse only to the finite mind.

Festus |

This marble-walled immensity o’erroofed
With pendant mountains glittering, awes my soul.
God’s hand hath scooped the hollow of this world;
Yea, none but His could; and I stand in it,
Like a forgotten atom of the light,
Some star hath lost upon its lightning flight.

Lucifer |

Here mayst thou lay thy hand on nature’s heart,
And feel its thousand yeared throbbings cease.
High overhead, and deep beneath our feet,
The sea’s broad thunder booms, scarce heard; around,
The arches, like uplifted continents
Of starry matter, burning inwardly,
Stand; and, hard by, earth’s gleaming axle sleeps,
All moving, all unmoved.

Festus |

Age here on age
Lie heaped like withered leaves. And must it end?

Lucifer |

God worketh slowly: and a thousand years
He takes to lift His hand off. Layer on layer
He made earth, fashioned it and hardened it
Into the great, bright, useful thing it is;
Its seas, life-crowded, and soul-hallowed lands
He girded with the girdle of the sun,
That sets its bosom glowing like Love’s own
Breathless embrace, close-clinging as for life;—
Veined it with gold, and dusted it with gems,
Lined it with fire, and round its heart-fire bowed
Rock-ribs unbreakable: until at last
Earth took her shining station as a star,
In Heaven’s dark hall, high up the crowd of worlds.
All this and thus did God; and yet it ends.
The ball He rolled and rounded, melts away
E’en now to its constituent atomies.

Festus |

It is enough. Though here were posited
All secrets of existence, natural
Or supernatural, dwell not here would I,
Though ’twere to drain profoundest fountains. No!
I love it not, the science nor the scene.
I long to know again the fresh green earth,
The breathing breeze, the sea and sacred stars.
These recollections crowd upon my soul,
As constellations on the evening skies,
And will not be forgotten. Let us leave!

Lucifer |

Aught that reminds the exile of his home
Is surely pleasant. I, friend, am content.

Festus |

I cannot be content with less than Heaven.
O Heaven, I love thee ever! sole and whole,
Living and comprehensive of all life;
Thee, agy world, thee, universal Heaven,
And heavenly universe! thee, sacred seat
Of intellective Time, the throned stars
And old oracular night;—by night or day,
To me thou canst not but be beautiful,
Boundless, all-central, universal sphere!
Whether the sun all-light thee, or the moon,
Embayed in clouds, mid starry island round,
With mighty beauty inundate the air;—
Or when one star, like a great drop of light,
From her full flowing urn hangs tremulous—
Yea, like a tear from her the eye of night,
Let fall o’er nature’s volume as she reads:—
Or, when in radiant thousands, each star reigns
In imparticipable royalty,
Leaderless, uncontrasted with the light
Wherein their light is lost, the sons of fire,
Arch element of the Heavens;—when storm and cloud
Debar the mortal vision of the eye
From wandering o’er thy threshold—more and more
I love thee, thinking on the splendid calm
Which bounds the deadly fever of these days—
The higher, holier, spiritual Heaven.
And when this world, within whose heartstrings now
I feel myself encoiled, shall be resolved,
Thee I shall be permitted still perchance,
To love and live in endlessly.

Lucifer |

All here
Thou seet hath holden fellowship with gods;
With eldest Time and primal matter, space,
And stars, and air, and all-inherent fire,
The watery deep and chaos, night, the all,
And the interior immortality,
And first-begotten Love. These rocks retain
Their caverned footsteps printed in pure fire.
Those were the times, the ancient youth of earth,
The elemental years, when earth and Heaven
Made one in holy bridals—royal gods
Their bright immortal issue: when men’s minds
Were vast as continents, and not as now
Minute and indistinguishable plots,
With here and there acres of untilled brains; when lived
The great original, broad-eyed, sunken race,
Whose wisdom, like these sea-sustaining rocks,
Hath formed the base of the world’s fluctuous lore:—
When too, by mountainous travail, human might
Sought to possess the everlasting Heavens,
And incommunicable, by the right
Of self-acquirement and high kindred with
Celestial virtues;—when the mortal powers—
Forecounsel, wisdom, and experience,
Teachers of all arts, founders of all good,
With Godhood strove, and gloriously failed—
In failure half successful; as these scenes,
Fire-fountains, and volcano-utterances,
Earth-heavings, island vomitings, evince.

Festus |

The world hath made such comet-like advance
Lately on science, we may almost hope,
Before we die of sheer decay, to learn
Something about our infancy. But me
This troubles not. Were all earth’s mountain chains
To utter fire at once, what a grand show
Of pyrotechny for our neighbor moon!
Let us ascend; but not through the charred throat
Of an extinct volcano.

Lucifer |

This way—down.
So shalt thou thread the world at once.

Festus |

Haste, haste.

XI

Scene—A ruined temple.

Festus and Lucifer.
Festus |

Here will I worship solely.

Lucifer |

’Tis a fane
Once sacred to the Sun.

Festus |

It matters not
What false god here hath falsely been adored,
Or what life-hating rites these walls have viewed:
The truly holy soul, which hath received
The unattainable, can hallow hell.
Now to the only true and Triune God
These walls shall echo praise, if never yet.
Bring me a morsel of the fire without;
For I will make a sacred offering
To God, as though the High Priest of the world.
He lacks not consecration at best hands
Whom Thou hast hallowed, Lord, by choice; and these,
The elements I offer, Thou hast made
Holy, by making them.

Lucifer |

Lo! here is fire.
I will await thee in the air.

Festus |

Withdraw!
Thine, Lord! are all the elements and worlds;—
The sun is Thy bright servant, and the moon
Thy servant’s servant;—the round rushing earth,
The lifeful air, the thousand winged winds,
The Heaven-kinned fire, the continental clouds,
The sea broad breasted, and the tranced lake,
Th rich arterial rivers, and the hills
Which wave their woody tresses in the breeze,
In grateful undulation, all are Thine;—
Thine are the snow-robed mountains circling earth
As the white spirits God the Saviour’s throne;—
Thine the bright secrets, central in all orbs,
And rudimental mysteries of life.
The sun-starred night, the ever-maiden morn,
The all-prevailing day, consummate eve,
Confess them Thine through the perpetual world:—
All art hath wrought from earth, or science lured
From truth, like flame out of the fire cloud, are
Thine;—Thine the glory, all belongs to Thee,
Finite, indefinite and infinite,
As mountains to a world, as worlds to Heaven.
The high doomed city and the toilful town
And early hamlet—all that live or die,
That flourish or decay, that change, or stand
Before Thy face, unchanged, exist for Thee,
Or are not at Thy bidding; Thine, all souls;
Atom and world, the universe is Thine!—
Thou canst as easily turn Thy kindest eye
From comprehending the bright Infinite,
To this crushed temple, where the wild flower decks
Its earthquake-rifted walls, and the birds build
In corners of its columned capitals—
And to this crumbling heart I offer here,
As trust Thine own Eternity. Behold!
Accept, I pray Thee, Lord! this sacrifice;
These elemental offerings simple, pure,
Which in the name of man I make to Thee,
Formless, save prostrate soul and kneeling heart—
In token of Thy perfect monarchy
And all comprising mercy. These are they!
A flowery turf, a branch, a burning coal,
A cup of water and an empty bowl;
This air-filled bowl is typic of the world
Thou fillest with Thy spirit, and the soul,
Receptive of Thy life-conferring truth;—
This the symbolic element wherefrom
We are to be reborn, wherein made pure;
Those whom Thou choosest are to be redeemed
Out of the mighty multitudes of men;
Yet all as of one nature be redeemed.
This coal, torn flaming from the earth, proclaims
Thy sin-consuming mercy as of earth;
And may our souls ever aspire to Thee,
As these pale flames unto the stars; this turf
Is as the earthy nature and abode
We would subject to Thee; and lieth here,
The representative of every star
And world-extended matter! Lord! this branch,
Which waveth high o’er all, oh, let it sign
Thine own Eternal Son’s humanity,
Which was on earth, yet ever lives in Heaven,
Redemptive of all Being. Golden Branch!
Which, in the eld-time, seer’s and sybil’s words,
Full of dark central thought and mystic truth,
Foretold should overspread the spirit world,
And with its fruit heal every wound of Death—
Tree of eternal life, Thee all adore.
Accept this prayer, O Saviour! that if men
Can nothing do but sin, Thou mayst forgive
The creature crime, and bring back all to Thee.
Thou art the one who made the universe;
Yet didst Thou walk on earth; Thou brakest bread
And drankest wine with men, betokening so
Thine own complete, Divine Humanity.
May all obey Thy words and do Thy will!
We praise Thee God, our father; whoso would
Be saved, let him believe in Thee Triune.
Thou doest all things rightly; all are best,
Sorrow, or joy, or power, or suffering.
Providing, therefore, all things that must be
And ought to be, as Thou dost and hast done,
From the beginning even to the end,
This heart let cease from prayer, these lips from praise,
Save that which life shall offer pauselessly.
Now go I forth again, refreshed, consoled,
Upon my time-enduring pilgrimage.
Ho! Lucifer!

Lucifer |

I wait thee.

Festus |

Whither next?

Lucifer |

As thou wilt, apposite or opposite.
’Tis light translateth night; ’tis inspiration
Expounds experience; ’tis the west explains
The east: ’tis time unfolds Eternity.

XIV

Scene—Another and a better world.

Festus and Lucifer.
Festus |

What a sweet world! Which is this, Lucifer?

Lucifer |

This is the star of evening and of beauty.

Festus |

Otherwise Venus. I will stay here.

Lucifer |

Nay:
It is but a visit

Festus |

Let us look about us.
It is Heaven, it must be; aught so beautiful
Must, I am sure, have feeling. Cannot worlds live?
Least things have life. Why not the greatest, too?
An atom is a world, a world an atom
Seen relatively: Death an act of Life.

Lucifer |

This is a world where every loveliest thing
Lasts longest; where decay lifts never head
Above the grossest forms, and matter here
Is all transparent substance; the flower fades not,
The beautiful die never, here: Death lies
A dreaming—he has nought to do—the babe
Plays with his darts. Nought dies but what should die.
Here are no earthquakes, storms, nor plagues; no Hell
At heart; no floating flood on high. The soil
Is ever fresh and fragrant as a rose—
The skies, like one wide rainbow, stand on gold—
The clouds are light as rose leaves—and the dew,
’Tis of the tears which stars weep, sweet with joy—
The air is softer than a loved one’s sigh—
The ground is glowing with all priceless ore,
And glistening with gems like a bride’s bosom—
The trees have silver stems and emerald leaves—
The fountains bubble nectar—and the hills
Are half alive with light. Yet it is not Heaven.

Festus |

Oh, how this world should pity man’s! I love
To walk earth’s woods when the storm bends his bow,
And volleys all his arrows off at once;
And when the dead brown branch comes crashing close
To my feet, to tread it down, because I feel
Decay my foe: and not to triumph’s worse
Than not to win. It is wrong to think on earth;
But terror hath a beauty even as mildness;
And I have felt more pleasure far on earth;
When, like a lion or a day of battle,
The storm rose, roared, shook out his shaggy mane,
And leaped abroad on the world, and lay down red,
Licking himself to sleep as it got light;
And in the cataract-like tread of a crowd,
And its irresistable rush, flooding the green
As though it came to doom, than e’er I can
Feel in this faery orb of shade and shine.
I love earth!

Lucifer |

Thou art mad to dote on earth
When with this sphere of beauty.

Festus |

It is the blush
Of being; surely, too, a maiden world,
Unmarred by thee. Touch it not, Lucifer!

Lucifer |

It is too bright to tarnish.

Festus |

Didst thou fail?

Lucifer |

I cannot fail. With me success is nature.
I am the cause, means consequence of ill.
Thou canst not yet enjoy a sensuous world—
Refined though ne’er so little o’er thine own,
And yet wouldst enter Heaven. Valhalla’s halls,
And sculls o’erbrimmed with mead, Elysian plains—
Eden, where life was toilless, and gave man
All things to live with, nothing to live for;—
The Moslem’s bowers of love, and streams of wine,
And palaces of purest adamant,
Where dark-eyed houris, with their young white arms,
The ever virgin, woo and welcome ye,
The Chaldee’s orbs of gold, where dwells the primal Light,
Were all too pure to thee; yet shalt thou be
Surely in Heaven, ere Death unlock the heart.
I said that I would show thee marvels here;
For here dwell many angels—many souls
Who have run pure through earth, or been made pure
By their salvation since. It is a mart
Where all the holy spirits of the world
Perform sweet interchange, and purchase truth
With truth, and love with love. Hither came He,
The Son—the Savior of the universe;
Not in the stable-state He went to earth—
A servant unto slaves; but as a God,
Carrying His kingdom with Him, and His Heaven.

Festus |

Lo, here are spirits! and all seem to love
Each other.

Lucifer |

He hath only half a heart
Who loves not all.

Festus |

Speak for me to some angel.
See, here is one, a very soul of beauty:
It is the muse. I know her by the lyre
Hung on her arm, and eye like fount of fire.

Muse |

Mortal, approach! I am the holy Muse,
Whom all the great and bright of spirit choose—
’Tis I who breathe my soul into the lips
Of those great lights whom death nor time eclipse;
’Tis I who wing the loving heart with song,
And set its sighs to music on the tongue:
It is I who watch, and, with sweet dreams, reward
The starry slumbers of the youthful bard;
For I love every thing that is sweet and bright.
And but this morn, with the first wink of light
A sunbeam left the sun, and, as it sped,
I followed, watched, and listened what it said:
Wherefore, with all this brightness am I given
From sun to earth? Am I not fit for Heaven?
From God I came once; and, though worlds have passed,
Ages, and dooms, yet I am light to the last.
Whatever God hath once bent to His will
Is sacred; so the world’s to be loved still.
What of this swift, this bright, but downward being,
Too burning to be borne—too brief for seeing?
What is mine aim—mine end? I would not die
In dust, or water, or an idiots eye:
I would not cease in blood, nor end in fire,
Nor light the loveless to their low desire:
No; let me perish on the poet’s page,
Where he kisses from his beauty’s brow all age;
Spelling it fair for aye, and wrinkle scorning,
As when first that brow brake on him like a morning.
But yet I cannot quit this line I tread,
Though it lead and leave me to the eyeless dead:
It is mine errand: ’tis for this I come,
And live, and die, and go down to my doom.
This is my fate—right and bright to speed on.
God is His own God: fate and fall are one.
Straight from the sun I go, like life from God,
Which hits, now on a heaven, now on a clod.
But, spite of all, the world’s air warps our way,
And crops the roses off the cheek of day;
As some false friend, who holds our fall in trust,
Oils our decline, and hands us to the dust.
Where are the sunbeams gone of the young green earth?
Search dust and night: our death makes dear our birth—
It said—and saw earth; and one moment more
Fell bright beside a vine-shadowed cottage door:
In it came—glanced upon a glowing page,
Where, youth forestalling and foreshortening age—
Weak with the work of thought, a boyish bard,
Sate suing night and stars for his reward.
The sunbeam swerved and grew, a breathing, dim,
For the first time, as it lit and looked on him:
His forehead faded—pale his lip and dry—
Hollow his cheek—and fever fed his eye.
Clouds lay about his brain, as on a hill,
Quick with the thunder thought, and lightning will.
His clenched hand shook from its more than midnight clasp,
Till his pen fluttered like a winged asp,
Save that no deadly poison blacked its lips:
’Twas his to life-enlighten, not eclipse;
Nor would he shade one atom of another,
To have a sun his slave, a god his brother.
The young moon laid her down as one who dies,
Knowing that death can be no sacrifice,
For that the sun, her god, through nature’s night
Shall make her bosom to grow great with light.
Still he sate, though his lamp sunk; and he strained
His eyes to work the nightness which remained.
Vain pain! he could not make the light he wanted,
And soon thought’s wizard ring gets disenchanted.
When earth was dayed—was morrowed—the first ray
Perched on his pen, and diamonded its way;—
The sunray that I watched; which, proud to mark
The line it loved as deathless, there died dark—
Died in the only path it would have trod,
Were there as many ways as worlds to God—
There, in the eye of God again to burn,
Ab all man’s glory unto God’s must turn.
And so may sunbeams ever guide his pen,
And God his heart, who lights the morn of men;
For this life is but Being.s first faint ray;
And sun on sun, and heaven on heaven, make up God’s day.
And were there suns in day as stars in night,
They would shew but like one ray from out His full-sphered light;
As but one momentary gleam would fly;
Or, as years, the arrows of eternity.

Festus |

Poets are all who love—who feel great thruths—
And tell them; and the truth of truths is love.
There was a time—oh, I remember well!
When, like a sea-shell with its seaborn strain,
My soul aye rang with music of the lyre;
And my heart shed its lore as leaves their dew—
A honey dew, and throve on what it shed.
All things I loved; but song I loved in chief.
Imagination is the air of mind;
Judgment its earth, and memory its main;
Passion its fire. I was at home in Heaven;
Swiftlike I lived above: once touching earth,
The meanest thing might master me: long wings
But baffled. Still and still I harped on song.
Oh! to create within the mind is bliss;
And, shaping forth the lofty thought, or lovely,
We seek not, need not Heaven: and when the thought—
Cloudy and shapeless, first forms on the mind,
Slow darkening into, some gigantic make,
How the heart shakes with pride and fear, as heaven
Quakes under its own thunder: or as might,
Of old, the mortal mother of a god,
When first she saw him lessening up the skies.
And I began the toil divine of verse,
Which like a burning-bush, doth guest a god.
But this was only wing-flapping—not flight;
The pawing of the courser ere he win;
Till, by degrees, from wrestling with my soul,
I gathered strength to keep the fleet thoughts fast,
And made them bless me. Yes, there was a time
When tomes of ancient song held eye and heart—
Were the sole lore I recked of: the great bards
Of Greece, of Rome, and mine own master land,
And they who in the holy book are deathless—
Men who have vulgarized sublimity,
And bought up truth for the nations; parted it,
As soldiers lotted once the garb of God—
Men who have forged gods—uttered—made them pass:
In whose words, to be read with many a heaving
Of the heart, is a power, like wind in rain—
Sons of the sons of God, who, in olden days,
Did leave their passionless Heaven for earth and woman,
Brought an immortal to a mortal breast;
And, like a rainbow clasping the sweet earth,
And melting in the covenant of love,
Left here a bright precipitate of soul,
Which lives for ever through the lines of men,
Flashing, by fits, like fire from an enemy’s front—
Whose thoughts, like bars of sunshine in shut rooms,
Mid gloom, all glory, win the world to light—
Who make their very follies like their souls;
And, like the young moon with a ragged edge,
Still, in their imperfection, beautiful—
Whose weaknesses are lovely as their strengths.
Like the white nebulous matter between stars,
Which, if not lights at least is likest light—
Men whom we build our love round like an arch
Of triumph, as they pass us on their way
To glory and to immortality;
Men whose great thoughts possess us like a passion
Through every limb and the whole heart; whose words
Haunt us as eagles haunt the mountain air;
Thoughts which command all coming times and minds,
As from a tower a warden—fix themselves
Deep in the heart as meteor stones in earth,
Dropped from some higher sphere; the words of gods,
And fragments of the undeemed tongues of Heaven.
Men who walk up to fame as to a friend
Or their own house, which from the wrongful heir
They have wrested, from the world’s hard hand and gripe—
Men who, like Death, all bone, but all unarmed,
Have ta’en the giant world by the throat, and thrown him;
And made him swear to maintain their name and fame
At peril of his life—who shed great thoughts
As easily as an oak looseneth its golden leaves
In a kindly largess to the soil it grew on—
Whose rich dark ivy thoughts, sunned o’er with love,
Flourish around the deathless stems of their names—
Whose names are ever on the world’s broad tongue,
Like sound upon the falling of a force—
Whose words, if winged, are with angels’ wings—
Who play upon the heart as on a harp,
And make our eyes bright as we speak of them—
Whose hearts have a look southwards, and are open
To the whole noon of nature—these I have waked
And wept o’er, night by night; oft pondering thus:
Homer is gone; and where is Jove? and where
The rival cities seven? His song outlives
Time, tower, and god—all that then was save Heaven.

Muse |

Yea, but the poor perfections of thine earth
Shall be as little as nothing to thee here.

Festus |

God must be happy, who aye makes; and since
Mind’s first of things, who makes from mind is blest
O’er men. Thus saith the bard to his work:—I am
Thy god, and bid thee live as my God me:
I live or die with thee, soul of my soul!
Thou camest and went’st, sunlike, from morn to eve:
And smiledst fire upon my heaving heart,
Like the sun in the sea, tall it arose
And dashed about its house all might and mirth,
Like ocean’s tongue in Staffa’s stormy cave.
Thou art a weakly reed to lean upon;
But, like that reed the false one filched from Heaven,
Full of immortal fire—immortal as
The breath of God’s lips—every breath a soul.

Muse |

Mortal! the muse is with thee: leave her not.

Festus |

Once my ambition to another end
Stirred, stretched itself, but slept again. I rose
And dashed on earth the harp, mine other heart,
Which, ringing, brake; its discord ruinous
Harmony still; and coldly I rejoiced
No other joy I had, wormlike, to feed
Upon my ripe resolve. It might not be;
The more I strove against, the more I loved it.

Lucifer |

Come, let as walk along. So say farewell.

Festus |

I will not.

Muse |

No; my greeting is forever.

Lucifer |

Well, well, come on!

Festus |

Oh! shew me that sweet soul
Thou brought’st to me the first night that we met.
She must be here, where all are good and fair:
And thou didst promise me.

Lucifer |

Is that not she
Walking alone, up-looking to thine earth?
For, lo! it shineth through the mid-day air.

Festus |

It is! it is!

Lucifer |

Well, I will come again. Goes.

Festus |

Knowest thou me, mine own immortal love?
How shall I call thee? Say, what mayest thou be!

Angela |

I am a spirit, Festus; and I love
Thy spirit, and shall love, when once like mine,
More than we ever did or can even now.
Pure spirits are of Heaven all heavenly.
Yet marvel not to meet me in this guise,
All radiant like a diamond as it is.
We wander in what way we will through all
Or any of these worlds, and wheresoe’er
We are, there Heaven is, here, and there too, God.

Festus |

Thou dost remember me.

Angela |

Ay, every thought
And look of love which thou hast lent to me,
Comes daily through my memory as stars
Wear through the dark.

Festus |

And thou art happy, love?

Angela |

Yes: I am happy when I can do good.

Festus |

To be good is to do good. Who dwell here?
Are they all deathless—happy?

Angela |

All are not:
Some err, though rarely—slightly. Spirits sin
Only in thought; and they are of a race
Higher than thine—have fewer wants and less
Temptations—many more joys—greater powers.
They need no civil sway: each rules himself—
Obeys himself: all live, too, as they choose,
And they choose nought but good. They who have come
From earth, or other orb, use the same powers,
Passions, and purposes, they had e’er death;
Although enlarged and freed, to nobler ends,
With better means. Here the hard warrior whets
The sword of truth, and steels his soul against sin.
The fierce and lawless wills which trooped it over
His breast—the speared desires that overran
The fairest fields of virtue, sleep and lie
Like a slain host ’neath snow; he dyes his hands
Deep in the blood of evil passions. Mind!
There is no passion evil in itself;
In Heaven we shall enjoy all to right ends.
There sit the perfect women, perfect men;—
Minds which control themselves, hearts which indulge
Designs of wondrous goodness, but so far
Only, as soul extolled to bliss and power
Most high, sees fit for each, divinely. Here,
The statesman makes new laws for growing worlds,
Through their forefated ages. Here, the sage
Masters all mysteries, more and more, from day
To day, watching the thoughts of men and angels
Through moral microscopes; or hails afar,
By some vast intellectual instrument,
The mighty spirits, good or bad, which range
The space of mind; some spreading death and woe
On far off worlds—some great with good and life.
And here the poet, like that wall of fire
In ancient song, surrounds the universe;
Lighting himself, where’er he soars or dives,
With his own bright brain—this is the poet’s heaven.
Here he may realize each form or scene
He e’er on earth imagined; or bid dreams
Stand fast, and faery palaces appear.
Here he has Heaven to hear him; to the which
He sings, with manlike voice and song, the love
Which lent him his whole strength, as is the wont
Of all great spirits and good throughout the world.
Oh! happiest of the happy is the bard!
Here, too, some pluck the branch of peace wherewith
To greet a suffering saint, and shew his flood
Of woe hath sunken: this I love to do.
My love, we shall be happy here.

Festus |

Shall I
Ever come here?

Angela |

Thou mayest. I will pray for thee,
And watch thee.

Festus |

Thou wilt have, then, need to weep.
This heart must run its orbit. Pardon thou
Its many sad deflections. It will return
To thee and to the primal goal of Heaven.

Angela |

Practice thy spirit to great thoughts and things,
That thou mayst start, when here, from vantage ground,
We can foretell the future of ourselves,
And fateful only to himself is each.

Festus |

I do not fear to die; for, though I change
The mode of being, I shall ever be.
World after world will fall at my right hand;
The glorious future be the past despised:
All now that seemeth bright will soon seem dim,
And darker grow, like earth, as we approach it;
While I still stand upon yon heaven which now
Hangs over me. If aught can make me seek
Other to be than that lost soul I fear me,
It is, that thou lovest me. Heaven were not Heaven
Without thee.

Lucifer |

I am here now. Art thou ready?
Let us go.

Angela |

Well—farewell. It makes me grieve
To bid a loved one back to yon false world—
To give up even a mortal unto death.
Thou wilt forget me soon, or seek to do.

Festus |

When I forget that the stars shine in air—
When I forget that beauty is in stars—
When I forget that love with beauty is—
Will I forget thee: till then, all things else.
Thy love to me was perfect from the first,
Even as the rainbow in its native skies:
It did not grow: let meaner things mature.

Angela |

The rainbow dies in heaven, and not on earth;
But love can never die; from world to world,
Up the high wheel of heaven, it lives for aye.
Remember that I wait thee, hoping, here.
Life is the brief disunion of that nature
Which hath been one and same in Heaven ere now,
And shall be yet again, renewed by Death.
Come to me when thou diest!

Festus |

I will, I will.

Angela |

Then, in each other’s arms, we will waft through space,
Spirit in spirit, one! or we will dwell
Among these immortal groves; or watch new worlds,
As, like the great thoughts of a Maker-mind,
They are rounded out of chaos: and we will
Be oft on earth with those we love, and help them;
For God hath made it lawful for good souls
To make souls good; and saints to help the saintly.
That thou right soon mayst fold unto thy heart
The blissful consciousness of separate
Oneness with God, in Him in whom alone
The saved are deathless, shall become, for thee,
My earliest, earnest, and most constant prayer.
Oh! what is dear to creatures of the earth?
Life, love, fight, liberty! But dearer far
Than all—and oh! an universe more divine—
The gift, which God endows his chosen with,
Of His own uncreated glory—His
Before all worlds, all ages, and reserved
Till after all for those He loves and saves.
As when the eye first views some Andean chain
Of shadowy rolling mountains, based on air,
Height upon height, aspiring to the last,
Even to Heaven, in sunny snow sheen, up
Stretching the angel’s pinions, nor can tell
Which be the loftiest nor the loveliest;
As when an army, wakening with the sun,
Starts to its feet all hope, spear after spear
And line on line reundulating light,
While night’s dull watchfires reek themselves away,
So feels the spirit when it first receives
The bright and mountainous mysteries of God,
Containing Heaven, moving themselves towards us,
In their free greatness, as by ships at sea
Come icebergs, pure and pointed as a star
Afar off glittering, of invisible
Depth, and dissolving in the light above.

Festus |

My prayer shall be that thy prayer be fulfilled.
I must to earth again. Farewell, sweet soul!

Angela |

Farewell! I love thee, and will oft be with thee.

Lucifer |

I like earth more than this: I rather love
A splendid failing than a petty good;
Even as the thunderbolt, whose course is downwards,
Is nobler far than any fire which soars.

Festus |

I am determined to be good again—
Again? When was I otherwise than ill?
Does not sin pour from my soul like dew from earth,
And, vapouring up before the face of God,
Congregate there in clouds between Heaven and me?
What wonder that I lack delight of life?
For it is thus—when amid the world’s delights,
How warm so’er we feel a moment among them—
We find ourselves, when the hot blast hath blown,
Prostrate, and weak, and wretched, even as I am.
I wish that I could leap from off this star,
And dash my soul to atoms like a glass.

Lucifer |

I have done nothing for thee yet. Thou shalt
See Heaven, and Hell, and all the sights of space,
When’er thou choosest.

Festus |

Not then now.

Lucifer |

Up! rise!

Festus |

No; I’ll be good: and will see none of them.
Earth draws us like a loadstone. We are coming.

XVII

Scene—Space.

Festus and Lucifer.
Festus |

Listen! I hear the harmonies of Heaven,
From sphere to sphere and from the boundless round
Re-echoing bliss to those serenest heights
Where angels sit and strike their emulous harps,
Wreathed round with flowers and diamonded with dew;
Such dew as gemmed the everduring blooms
Of Eden winterless, or as all night
The tree of Life wept from its every leaf
Unwithering. And now methinks I hear
The music of the murmur of the stream
Which through the Bridal City of the Lord
Floweth all life for ever; and the breath
Through the star-shading branches of that Tree
Transplanted now to Heaven, but once on earth,
Whose fruit is for all Beings—breathed of God.
Oh! breathe on me, inspiring spirit-breath!
Oh! flow to me, ye heart-reviving waves;
Freshen the faded soul that droops and dies.

Lucifer |

The universe is but the gate of Heaven.
Lo! from this highest orb, the crown of space
And footstool unto Heaven, we can look up
And gain a glimpse of glory unconceived.

Festus |

See how yon angels stretch their shining arms,
Wave their star-haunting wings which gleam like glass,
And locks that look like Morning’s when she comes
Triumphant in the East. Is this their joy
O’er some world penitent?

Lucifer |

Lo! there it rides;
Blest to discharge on Heaven’s all peaceful shores
Its long accumulated load of life,
Its deathless freight—pilgrims of time and space.
Yon guilty orb of hesitating light
Slow looming, there, on its dark path, goes up
At the forewritten hour, as do all worlds
To God, to judgment; and the earthquake groans
Which rend its adamantine breast forebode
Its agonizing doom.

Festus |

And doth not Heaven
Grieve with the lost as gladden with the saved?

Lucifer |

How many immortals mourn at the decree
Of righteous wisdom, which alone to them
Is bliss sufficient, being infinite?

Festus |

If God hath made all He alone it is
Who hath to answer for all.

Lucifer |

He hath made.
To secondary natures it seems just
That justice should be realised, and there
Is one example extant in the skies.

Festus |

But wherefore did it not repent in Time?

Lucifer |

What unto us is Time, stands before God
Eternity. Repentance is the grief
For and effectual abstinence from sin,
Which secondary natures without God
Cannot, attain to.

Festus |

Cloudy and dear by turns
Thy words as Heaven. I know not what to think
Nor how to act.

Lucifer |

It is natural; and none
Can aim or hit but as appointed them.
There is but one great sinner, Human nature,
Predict of every world and predicate:
The wicked one, the Enemy of God,
To be destroyed in the eternal fire
Of His wrath, even thus in Deity—
In whom as they begin must all things end.
God loveth only His own spirit, so
All that is base shall perish. From the first
These things were fixed, and are and aye shall be
Consummating, and are revealed as writ
In words always fulfilled and burning truth
Under the buried basements of the skies,
Which after overthrown shall reäppear.
The unenlightened mind sees Deity
In all things, but the spiritual soul
All things in God. Now, ere we higher rise,
Look downwards from this coping of the world;
And know that down to the profoundest depth
Of utter space, where not an atom mars
The void invisible, it were easier far
To cast a line and calculate its rate,
Or pierce all space, nor cross the path of light,
Than fathom man’s dark heart or sound his soul.

XVIII

Scene—Heaven.

Lucifer and Festus, entering.
The Archangels |

Infinite God! Thy will is done:
The world’s last sand is all but run:
The night is feeding on the sun.

Lucifer |

All-being God! I come to Thee again,
Nor come alone. Mortality is here.
Thou bad’st me do my will, and I have dared
To do it. I have brought him up to Heaven;

God |

Thou canst not do what is not willed to be.
Suns are made up of atoms, Heaven of souls;
And souls and suns are but the atoms of
The body I, God, dwell in. What wilt thou
With him who is here with thee?

Lucifer |

Show him God.

God |

No being, upon part of whom the curse
Of death rests—were it only on his shadow,
Can look on God and live.

Lucifer |

Look, Festus, look!

Festus |

Eternal fountain of the Infinite,
On whose life-tide the stars seem strown like bubbles,
Forgive me that an atomie of being
Hath sought to see its Maker face to face.
I have seen all Thy works and wonders, passed
From star to star, from space to space, and feel
That to see all which can be seen is nothing,
And not to look on Thee the Invisible.
The spirits that I met all seemed to say,
As on they sped upon their starward course,
And slackened their lightning wings on moment o’er me,
I could not look on God whate’er I was.
And Thou didst give this spirit at my side
Power to make me more than them immortal.
So when we had winged through Thy wide world of things,
And seen stars made and saved, destroyed and judged,
I said—and trembled lest Thou shouldst not hear me,
And make Thyself right ready to forgive,
I will see God, before I die, in Heaven.
Forgive me, Lord!

God |

Rise, mortal! look on me.

Festus |

Oh! I see nothing but like dazzling darkness.

Lucifer |

I knew how it would be. I am away.

Festus |

I am Thy creature, God! oh, slay me not,
But let some angel take me, or I die.

Genius |

Come hither, Festus.

Who art thou?

Genius |

I am
One who hath aye been by thee from thy birth,
Thy guardian angel, thy good genius.

Festus |

I knew thee not till now.

Genius |

I am never seen
In the earth’s low thick light, but here in Heaven,
And in the air which God breathes, I am clear.
I tell to God each night thy thoughts and deeds;
And watching o’er thee both on earth and here,
Pray unto Him for thee and intercede.

Festus |

And this is Heaven. Lead on. Will God forgive
That I did long to see Him?

Genius |

It is the strain
Of all high spirits towards Him. Thou couldst not
Even if thou wouldst, behold God; masked in dust,
Thine eye did light on darkness; but when dead,
And the dust shaken off the shining essence,
God shall glow through thee as through living glass,
And every thought and atom of thy being
Shall guest His glory, be overbright with God.
Hadst thou not been by faith immortalized
For the instant, then thine eye had been thy death.
Come, I will show thee Heaven and all angels.
Lo! the recording angel.

Festus |

Him I see
High-seated, and the pen within his hand
Plumed like a storm-portending cloud which curves
Half over Heaven, and swift, in use divine,
As is a warrior’s spear!

Genius |

The book wherein
Are writ the records of the universe,
Lies like a world laid open at his feet.
And there, the Book of Life which holds the names,
Formed out in starry brilliants, of God’s sons—
The spirit-names which angels learn by heart,
Of worlds beforehand. Wilt thou see thine own?

Festus |

My name is written in the Book of Life.
It is enough. That constellated word
Is more to me and clearer than all stars,
Henceforward and for aye.

Genius |

Raise still thine eyes!
Thy gleaming throne! hewn from that mount of light
Which was before created light or night
Never created, Heaven’s eternal base,
Whereon God’s throne is ’stablished. Sit on it!

Festus |

Nay, I will forestall nothing more than sight.

Genius |

Turn then and view yon streams where spirits sport
Quaffing immortal life, preparing aye
For higher and intenser Being still.
These are the upper fountains of the Heavens,
The emanations of Eternity;
By washing them in which they purify
Their eyes to penetrate the essential light
In all things hidden, seen alone by eyes
Fire-spirited, etherially clear,
Which like the fabled stone, conceived of fire,
Son of the sun, transmutes all seen to soul.
And such the bliss and power reserved for man;
Yet but the surface-shadow canst thou see.
The substance is to be. Behold yon group
Of spirits blest! in their divinest eyes
The spirit speaks, and shows that in their own
All doubt and want hath ceased, as death hath ceased.
Hither they come, rejoicing, marvelling.

Festus |

How all with kindly wonder look on me!
Mayhap I tell of earth to their pure sense.
Some seem as if they knew me. I know none.
But how claim kinship with the glorified
Unless with them like-glorified! Yet, yes—
It is—it must be;—that angelic spirit!—
My heart outruns me—mother! see thy son.

Angel |

Child, how art thou here?

Festus |

God hath let me come.

Angel |

Hast thou not come unbidden and unprepared?

Festus |

Forgive me, if it be so. I am come.
And I have ever said there are two who will
Forgive me aught I do—my God and thou!

Angel |

I do! may He!

Festus |

Dear mother, thou art blessed;
And I am blessed, too, in knowing thee.

Angel |

Son of my hopes on earth and prayers In Heaven!
The love of God! oh, it is infinite
Even as our imperfection. Promise, child,
That thou wilt love Him more and more for this,
And for His boundless kindness thus towards me.
Now, my son, hear me! for the hours of Heaven
Are not as those of earth; and all is all
But lost that is not given unto God.
Oft have I seen with joy thy thoughts of Heaven,
And holy hopes, which track the soul with light,
Rise from dead doubts within thy troubled breast,
As souls of drowned bodies from the sea,
Upwards to God, and marked them so received,
That oh! my soul hath overflowed with rapture
As now thine eye with tears. But oh! my son
Beloved! fear thou ever for thy soul;
It yet hath to be saved. Nought perfect stands
But that which is in Heaven. God is all-kind;
And long time hath he made thee think of Him;
Think on Him yet in time. Ere I left earth,
With the last breath which air would spare for me,
With the last look which light would bless me with,
I prayed thou mightst be happy and be wise—
And half the prayer I brought myself to God—
And lo! thou art unhappy and unwise.

Festus |

Blessed one! I rejoice that thou art clear,
And all who have cared for me, of my misdeeds.
Thy spirit was on those who nurtured me.
All word and practice that could be of good,
Was given me; so that my sin is splendid.
Yes! if I have sinned, I have sinned sublimely;
And I am glad I suffer for my faults.
I would not if I might, be bad and happy.

Angel |

God laughs at ill by man made and allows it.
The vaunt of mountainious evil and the power
To challenge Heaven from molehill, child!

Festus |

God hath made but few better hearts than mine,
However much it fail in the wise ways
Of the world, as living in the dull dark streets
Of forms and follies wherein men build themselves.

Angel |

The goodness of the heart is shown in deeds
Of peacefulness and kindness. Hand and heart
Are one thing with the good as thou shouldst be.
The splendor of corruption hath no power
Nor vital essence; and content in sin
Shows apathy, not satisfied control.
Do my words trouble thee? Then treasure them.
Pain overgot gives peace as death does Heaven.
All things that speak of Heaven speak of peace.
Peace hath more might than war. High brows are calm.
Great thoughts are still as stars; and truths, like suns,
Stir not; though many systems tend round them.
Mind’s step is still as death’s; and all great things
Which cannot be controlled, whose end is good.
Behold yon throne! there, Love, Faith, Hope are one!
There, judgment, righteousness, and mercy make
One and the same thing. God’s salvation is
His vengeance, and his wrath glory, as on earth
Destruction restoration to the pure.
Humanity is perfected in Heaven.

Festus |

I did not make myself, nor plan my soul.
I am no angel nursed in the lap of light,
Nor fed on milk immortal of the stars,
Nor golden fruit grown in the summery suns.
How am I answerable for my heart?
It is my master, and is free with me,
As fixed with fate, even as a star which moves,
Yet moveth only on a certain course
In certain mode;—its liberties are laws,
Its laws tyrannic; I cannot hinder it,
It cannot hinder God. All that we do
Or bear is settled from eternity;
Whereof is no beginning, midst, nor end.
To act, is ours; quite sure, whate’er we do,
Whether it be for our own good or ill,
Or others’ ill or good, it is for God’s
Glory—the same and always: it is ordered.
The soul is but an organ, and it hath
No power of good and evil in itself,
More than the eye hath power of light or dark.
God fitted it for good; and evil is
Good, in another way we are not skilled in.
The good we do is of His own good will—
The ill, of His own letting. Doth not nature—
All light in life, shine, marsh-like, too, in death?
Yea, wandering fires wait even on rottenness
Like a stray gleam of thought in an idiot’s brain.
And thus I look on souls that seem decaying
In sin, and flying off by elements.
All may not live again; but all which do
Must change perpetually e’en in Heaven;
And not by death to death, but life to life.

Angel |

No! step by step, and throne by throne, we rise
Continually towards the infinite,
And ever nearer—never near—to God.

Festus |

Yet merit or demerit none I see
In nature, human or material,
In passions or affections good or bad.
We only know that God’s best purposes
Are oftenest brought about by dreadest sins.
Is thunder evil or is dew divine?
Does virtue lie in sunshine, sin in storm?
Is not each natural, each needful, best?
How know we what is evil from what good?
Wrath and revenge God claimeth as His own.
And yet men speculate on right and wrong
As upon day and night, forgetting both
Have but one cause, and that the same—God’s will,
Originally, ultimately Him.
All right is right divine. A worm hath rights
A king cannot despoil him of, nor sin;
Yet wrongs are things necessitate, like wants,
And oft are well permitted to best ends.
A double error sometimes sets us right.
In man there is no rule o£ right and wrong
Inherent as mere man. Why, conscience is
The basest thing of all. Its life is passed
In justifying and condemning sin;
Accomplice, traitor, judge and headsman, too,
But conscience knows its business and performs.
Nothing is lost in nature; and no soul,
Though buried in the centre of all sin,
Is lost to God; but there it works His will
And burns comformably. The weakest things
Are to be made the examples of His might;
The most defective, of His perfect grace,
Whene’er He thinketh well. Oh! everything
To me seems good and lovely and immortal;
The whole is beautiful; and I can see
Nought wrong in man nor nature, nought not meant;
As from His hands it comes who fashions all,
All holy as His word. The world is but
A revelation. He breathes Himself upon us
Before our birth, as o’er the formless void
He moveth at first, and we are all inspired
With His spirit. All things are God or of God.
For the whole world is in the mind of God
What a thought is in ours. Why boast we then
Of aught? All that is good belongs to God;
And good and God are all things, or shall be.

Angel |

There lacks in souls like thine unsaved, unraised,
The light within—the light of perfectness—
Such a there is in Heaven. The soul hath sunk
And perished like a light-house in the sea;
It is for God to raise it and rebuild.

Genius |

And his, thy son’s, He will raise. Since with me,
I have shown him infinite wonders: we have oped
And scanned the golden scroll of Fate, wherein
Are writ, in God’s own hand, all things which happen.
There we have seen the record of his being—
His long temptation, sin, and suffering.

Festus |

And hear it, oh beloved and blessed one!
Mine own salvation!

Angel |

God is great in love;
Infinite in His nature, power, and grace;
Creating, and redeeming, and destroying—
Infinite infinitely. But in love—
Oh! it is the truth transcendant over all—
When thus to one poor spirit He gives His hand,
He seems to impart His own unboundedness
Of bliss. We seem to be hardly worth destroying,
And much less saving; yet He loveth each
As though all were His equal.

Festus |

I know all
I have to go through henceforth—all the doubts,
Passions of life, and woes; but knowing them
Hinders them not; I bear obeyingly;
And pine no more, as once when I looked back
And saw how life had balked, and foiled, and fooled me.
Fresh as a spouting spring upon the hills
My heart leapt out to life; it little thought
Of all the vile cares that would rill into it,
And the low places it would have to go through—
The drains, the crossings, and the null-work after.
God hath endowed me with a soul that scorns life—
An element over and above the world’s:
But the price one pays for pride is mountain-high,
There is a curse beyond the rack of death—
A woe, wherein God hath put out His strength—
A pain past all the mad wretchedness we feel,
When the sacked secret hath flown out of us,
And the heart broken open by deep care—
The curse of a high spirit famishing,
Because all earth but sickens it.

Angel |

Go, child!
Fulfil thy fate! Be—do—bear—and thank God!
To me it seems as I had lived all ages
Since I left earth; and thou art yet scarce man.

Festus |

It was not, mother, that I knew thy face; strange
The luminous eclipse that is on it now,
Though it was fair on earth, would have made it
Even to one who knew as well as he loved thee;
And if these time-tired eyes ever imaged thine,
It was but for a moment, and the sight
Passed; and my life was broken like a line
At the first word—but my heart cried out in me.

Angel |

I knew thee well. And now to earth again!
Go, son! and say to all who once were mine—
I love them, and expect them.

Festus |

Blessed one!
I will.

Angel |

I charge thee, Genius, bear him safely.

Genius |

Through light, and night, and all the powers of air,
I have a passport.

Angel |

God be with thee, child!

Genius |

Come!

Festus |

I feel happier, better, nobler now.
See where she sits, and smiles, and points me out
To those who sit along with her. Who are
The two?

Genius |

One is the mother of mankind,
And one the mother of the Man who saved
Mankind; and she, thine own, the mother of
The last man of mankind—for thou art he.

Festus |

Am I? It is enough: I have seen God.

Genius |

God and His great idea, the universe,
Are over and above us. Be the one
Worshipped, the other reverently proved.
Wilt sojourn for a time among the worlds,
And test their natures?

Festus |

Gladly.

Genius |

Seek we, then,
All rareness and variety these worlds
Can offer, ere we reach thine orb. Descend!
Now is the age of worlds.

XIX

Scene—A visit.

Festus and Helen.
Helen |

Come to the light, love! Let me look on thee!
Let me make sure I have thee. Is it thou?
Is this thy hand? Are these thy velvet lips—
Thy lips so lovable? Nay, speak not yet!
For oft as I have dreamed of thee, it was
Thy speaking woke me. I will dream no more.
Am I alive? And do I really look
Upon these soft and sea-blue eyes of thine,
Wherein I half believe I can espy
The riches of the sea? These dark rolled looks!
Oh God! art Thou not glad, too, he is here!—
Where hast thou been so long? Never to hear,
Never to see, nor see one who had seen thee—
Come now, confess it was not kind to treat
Me in this manner.

Festus |

I confess, my love,
But I have been where neither tongue, nor pen,
Nor hand could give thee token where I was;
And seen, but ’tis enough! I see thee now.
I would rather look upon thy shadow there,
Than Heaven’s bright thrones for ever.

Helen |

Where hast been?

Festus |

Say, am I altered?

Helen |

Nowise.

Festus |

It is well.
Then in the resurrection we may know
Each other. I have been among the worlds,
Angels and spirits bodiless.

Helen |

Great God!
Can it be so?

Festus |

It is:—and that both here
And elsewhere. When the stars come, thou shalt see
The track I travelled through the light of night;
Where I have been, and whence my visitors.

Helen |

And thou hast been with angels all the while,
And still dost love me?

Festus |

Constantly as now.
But for the time I did devote my soul
To their divine society, I knew
Thou wouldst forgive, yet dared not trust myself
To see thee, or to pen one word, for fear
Thy love should overpower the plan conceived,
And acting, in my mind, of visiting
The spirits in their space-embosomed homes.

Helen |

Forgive thee! ’tis a deed which merits love.
And should I not be proud, too, who can say,
For me he left all angels?

Festus |

I forethought
So thou wouldst say; but with an offering
Came I provided, even with a trophy
Of love angelic, given me for thee;
For angel bosoms know no jealousy.

Helen |

Shew me.

Festus |

It is of jewels I received
From one who snatched them from the richest wreck
Of matter ever made, the holiest
And most resplendent.

Helen |

Why, what could it be?
Jewels are bawbles only; whether pearls
From the sea’s lightless depths, or diamonds
Culled from the mountain’s crown, or chrysolith,
Cat’s eye or moonstone, toys are they at best.
Jewels are not of all things in my sight
Most precious.

Festus |

Nor in mine. It is in the use
Of which they may be made their value lies;
In the pure thoughts of beauty they call up,
And qualities they emblem. So in that
Thou wearest there, thy cross;—to me it is
Suggestive of bright thoughts and hopes in Him
Whose one great sacrifice availeth all,
Living and dead, through all Eternity.
Not to the wanderer over southern seas
Rises the constellation of the Cross
More lovelily o’er sky and calm blue wave,
Than does to me that bright one on thy breast.
As diamonds are purest of all things,
And but embodied light which fire consumes
And renders back to air, that nought remains—
And as the cross is symbol of our creed,
So let that ornament signify to thee
The faith of Christ, all purity, all light,
Through fervency resolving into Heaven.
Each hath his cross, fair lady, on his heart.
Never may thine be heavier or darker
Than that now on thy breast, so light and bright,
Rising and falling with its bosom-swell.

Helen |

I thank thee for that wish, and for the love
Which prompts it—the immeasurable love
I know is mine, and I with none would share.
Forgive me; I have not yet felt my wings.
Now have I not been patient? Let me see
My promised present.

Festus |

Look, then—they are here;
Bracelets of chrysoprase.

Helen |

Most beautiful!

Festus |

Come, let me clasp them, dearest, on thine arms;
For these of those are worthy, and are named
In the foundation stones of the bright city,
Which is to be for the immortal saved,
Their last and blest abode; and such their hue,
The golden green of Paradisal plains
Which lie about it boundlessly, and more
Intensely tinted with the burning beauty
Of God’s eye, which alone doth light that land,
Than our earth’s cold grass garment with the sun;
Though even in the bright, hot, blue-skied East,
Where he doth live the life of light and Heaven;
Where, o’er the mountains, at midday is seen
The morning star, and the moon tans at night
The cheek of careless sleeper. Take them, love.
There are no nobler earthly ornaments
Than jewels of the city of the saved.

Helen |

But how are these of that bright city? I
Am eager for their history.

Festus |

They are
Thereof prophetically, and have been—
What I will shew thee presently, when I
Relate the story of the angel who
Gave them to me.

Helen |

Well; I will wait till then,
Or any time thou choosest: ’tis enough
That I believe thee always;—but would know,
If not in me too curious to ask,
How came about these miracles? Hast thou raised
The fiend of fiends, and made a compact dark,
Sealed with thy blood, symbolic of the soul,
Whereby all power is given thee for a time,
All means, all knowledge, to make more secure
Thy spirit’s dread perdition at the end?
I of such awful stories oft have heard,
And the unlawful lore which ruins souls.
Myself have charms, foresee events in dreams;
Can prophesy, prognosticate, know well
The secret ties between many magic herbs
And mortal feelings, nor condemn myself
For knowing what is innocent; but thou!
Thy helps are mightier far and more obscure.
Was it with wand and circle, book and scull,
With rites forbid and backward-jabbered prayers,
In cross-roads or in churchyard, at full moon,
And by instruction of the ghostly dead,
That thou hast wrought these wonders, and attained
Such high transcendent powers and secrets? Speak!
Or is man’ mastery over spirits not
Of such a vile and vulgar consequence?

Festus |

Were not my heart as guiltless of all mirth
As is the oracle of an extinct god
Of its priest-prompted answer, I might smile
To list such askings. Mind’s command o’er mind,
Spirit’s o’er spirit, is the dear effect
And natural action of an inward gift,
Given of God, whereby the incarnate soul
Hath power to pass free out of earth and death
To immortality and Heaven, and mate
With beings of a kind, condition, lot,
All diverse from his own. This mastery
Means but communion, the power to quit
Life’s little globule here, and coalesce
With the great mass about us. For the rest,
To raise the Devil were an infant’s task
To that of raising man. Why, every one
Conjures the Fiend from Hell into himself
When Passion chokes or blinds him. Sin is Hell.

Helen |

How dost thou bring a spirit to thee, Festus?

Festus |

It is my will which makes it visible.

Helen |

What are those like whom thou hast seen?

Festus |

They come,
The denizens of other worlds, arrayed
In diverse form and feature, mostly lovely;
In limb and wing ethereal finer far
Than an ephemeris’ pinion; others, armed
With gleaming plumes, that might o’ercome an air
Of adamantine denseness, pranked with fire.
All are of different offices and strengths,
Powers, orders, tendencies, in like degrees
As men, with even more variety;
Of different glories, duties, and delights.
Even as the light of meteor, satellite,
Planet and comet, sun, star, nebula,
Differ, and nature also, so do theirs.
With them is neither need, nor sex, nor age,
Nor generation growth, decay, nor death;
Or none whom I have known; there may be such.
Mature they are created and complete,
Or seem to be. Perfect from God they come.
Yet have they different degrees of beauty,
Even as strength and holy excellence.
Some seem of milder and more feminine
Nature than others, Beauty’s proper sex,
Shewn but by softer qualities of soul,
More lovable than awful, more devote
To deeds of individual piety,
And grace, than mighty missions fit to task
Sublimest spirits, or the toil intense
Of cultivating nations of their kind;
Or working out from the problem of the world
The great results of God—result, sum, cause.
These ofttimes charged with delegated powers,
Formative or destructive; those, in chief,
Ordained to better and to beautify
Existence as it is; with careful love
To tend upon particular worlds or souls;
Warning and training whom they love, to tread
The soft and blossom-bordered, silvery paths,
Which lead and lure the soul to Paradise,
Making the feet shine which do walk on them;
While each doth God’s great will alike, and both
With their whole nature’s fulness love His works.
To love them lifts the soul to Heaven.

Helen |

Let me, then!
Whence come they?

Festus |

Many of them come from orbs
Wherein the rudest matter is more worth
And fair than queenly gem; the dullest dust
Beneath their feet is rosy diamond:—
Others, direct from Heaven; but all in high
And serious love towards those to whom they come.
None but the blest are free to visit where
They choose. The lost are slaves for ever; here
Never but on their Master’s merciless
Business, nor elsewhere. Still sometimes with these
Dark spirits have I held communion,
And in their soul’s deep shadow, as within
A mountain cavern of the moon, conversed
With them, and wormed from them the gnawing truth
Of their extreme perdition; marking oft
Nature revealed by torture, as a leaf
Unfolds itself in fire and writhes the while,
Burning, jet unconsumed. Others there are
Come garlanded with flowers unwithering,
Or crowned with sunny jewels, clad in light,
And girded with the lightning, in their hands
Wands of pure rays or arrowy starbeams; some
Bright as the sun self-lit, in stature tall,
Strong, straight and splendid as the golden reed
Whereby the height, and length, and breadth, and depth,
Of the descendant city of the skies,
In which God sometime shall make glad with man,
Were measured by the angel; (the same reed
Wherewith our Lord was mocked that angel found
Close by the Cross and took; God made it gold,
And now it makes the sceptre of His Son
Over all worlds; the sole bright rule of Heaven,
The measure of immortal life, the scale
Of power, love, bliss, and glory infinite):—
Some gorgeous and gigantic, who with wings
Wide as the wings of armies in the field
Drawn out for death, sweep over Heaven, and eyes
Deep, dark as sea-worn caverns, with a torch
At the end, far back, glaring. Some with wings
Like an unfainting rainbow, studded round
With stones of every hue and excellence,
Writ o’er with mystic words which none may read,
But those to whom their spiritual state
Gives correlative meaning, fit thereto.
Some of these visit me in dreams; with some
Have I made one in visions, in their own
Abodes of brightness, blessedness, and power:
And know moreover I shall joy with them,
Ere long their sacred guest, through ages yet
To come, in worlds not now perhaps create,
As they have been mine here: and some of them
In unimaginable splendours I
Have walked with through their winged worlds of light,
Double and triple particoloured suns,
And systems circling each the other, clad
In tints of light and air, whereto this earth
Hath nothing like, and man no knowledge of:—
Orbs heaped with mountains, to the which ours are
Mere grave-mounds, and their skies flowered with stars,
Violet, rose or pearl-hued, or soft blue,
Golden or green, the light now blended, now
Alternate; many moons and planets, full,
Crescent, or gibbous-faced, illumining
In periodic and intricate beauty,
At once those strange and most felicitous skies.

Helen |

How I should love to visit other worlds,
Or see an angel!

Festus |

Wilt thou now?

Helen |

I dare not.
Not now at least. I am not in the mood.
Ere I behold a spirit I would pray.

Festus |

Light as a leaf thy step, or arrowy
Footing of breeze upon a waveless pool;
Sudden and soft, too, like a waft of light,
The beautiful immortals come to me;
Oh, ever lovely, ever welcome they!

Helen |

But why art thou, of all men, favoured thus?
To say there is a mystery in this
Or aught is only to confess God. Speak!

Festus |

It is God’s will that I possess this power,
Thus to attract great spirits to mine own,
As steel magnetically charged draws steel;
Himself the magnet of the universe,
Bound whom all spirits tremble, and towards whom
All tend.

Helen |

If as thou sayest, it is good:—
May it be an immortal good to thee.

Festus |

There is no keeping back the power we have.
He hath no power who hath not power to use.
Some of these bodies whom I speak of are
Pure spirits, others bodies soulical:
For spirit is to soul as wind to air.
They give me all I seek, and at a wish
Would furnish treasures, thrones, or palaces;
But all these things have I eschewed, and chosen
Command of mind alone, and of the world
Unbodied and all-lovely.

Helen |

Is not this
Pleasure too much for mortal to be good?

Festus |

All pleasure is with Thee, God! elsewhere, none.
Not silver-ceiled hall nor golden throne,
Set thick with priceless gems, as Heaven with stars,
Or the high heart of youth with its bright hopes;—
Nor marble gleaming like the white moonlight,
As ’twere an apparition of a palace
Inlaid with light as is a waterfall;—
Not rainbow-pinions coloured like yon cloud,
The sun’s broad banner o’er his western tent,
Can match the bright imaginings of a child
Upon the glories of his coming years;
How equal, then, the full-assured faith
Of him to whom the Saviour hath vouchsafed
The Heaven of His bosom? What can tempt
In its performance equal to that promise?
My soul stands fast to Heaven as doth a star;
And only God can move it who moves all.
There are who might have soared to what I spurned;
And like to heavenly orders human souls;
Some fitted most for contemplation, some
For action, these for thrones, and those for wheels.

Helen |

Tell me what they discourse upon, these angels?

Festus |

They speak of what is past or coming, less
Of present things or actions. Some say most
About the future, others of the gone,
The dim traditions of Eternity,
Or Time’s first golden moments. One there was—
From whose sweet lips elapsed as from a well,
Continuously, truths which made my soul
As they sank in it, fertile with rich thoughts—
Spake to me oft of Heaven, and our talk
Was of divine things always—angels, Heaven,
Salvation, immortality, and God;
The different states of spirits and the kinds
Of Being in all orbs, or physical,
Or intellectual. I never tired
Preferring questions, but at each response
My soul drew back, sealike, into its depths
To urge another charge on him. This spirit
Came to me daily for a long, long time,
Whene’er I prayed his presence. Many a world
He knew right well which man’s eye never yet
Hath marked, nor ever may mark while on earth;
Yet grew his knowledge every time he came.
His thoughts all great and solemn and serene,
Like the immensest features of an orb,
Whose eyes are blue seas, and whose clear broad brow,
Some cultured continent, came ever round
From truth to truth—day bringing as they came.
He was to me an all-explaining spirit,
Teaching divine things by analogy
With mortal and material. Thus of God,
He shewed, as the three primal rays make one
Sole beam of Light, so the three Persons make
One God; neither without the other is.
However bright or beautiful itself
The theme he touched, he made it more so by
His own light, like a fire-fly on a flower.
And one of all I knew the most of, yet
The least can say of him; for full oft
Our thoughts drown speech, like to a foaming force,
Which thunders down the echo it creates.
Yet must I somewhat tell of him. He was
The spirit evil of the universe,
Impersonate. Oh, strange and wild to know!
Perdition and destruction dwelt in him,
Like to a pair of eagles in one nest.
Hollow and wasteful as a whirlwind was
His soul; his heart as earthquake, and engulphed
World upon world. In him they disappeared
As might a morsel in a lion’s maw,
The world which met him rolled aside to let him
Pass on his piercing path. His eyeballs burned
Revolving lightnings like a world on fire;
Their very night was fatal as the shade
Of Death’s dark valley. And his space-spread wings—
Wide as the wings of Darkness when she rose
Scowling, and backing upwards, as the sun,
Giant of Light, first donned his burning crown,
Gladdening all Heaven with bis inaugural smile—
Were stained with the blood of many a starry world:
Yea, I have seen him seize upon an orb,
And cast it careless into worldless space,
As I might cast a pebble in the sea.
His might upon Ibis earth was wondrous most.
He stood a match for mountains. Ocean’s depths
He clove unto their rock-bed, as a sword,
Through blood and muscle to the central bone,
With one swoop of his arm. His brow was pale—
Pale as the life-blood of the undying worm
Which writhes around its frame of vital fire.
His voice blew like the desolating gust
Which strips the trees, and strews the earth with death.
His words were ever like a wheel of fire,
Rolling and burning this way now, now that:
Now whirling forth a blinding beam, now soft
And deep as Heaven’s own luminous blue—and now
Like to a oonqueror’s chariot wheel they came,
Sodden with blood and slow, revolving death:
And every tone fell on the ear and heart,
Heavy and harsh and startling, like the first
Handful of mould cast on the coffined dead,
As though he claimed them his.

Lucifer |

Entering.

Dost recognize
The portrait, lady?

Helen |

Festus! who is this?
What portrait?—

Festus |

Wherefore comest thou? Did I not
Claim privacy one evening?

Lucifer |

Why, indeed—
I simply called, as I was on my way
To Jupiter—and he’s a mouthful, mind;—
To keep the proverbs, too, in countenance.
Any commands for our planetary friends?
I go. Make my excuses! Goes.

Festus |

A mistake,
Dearest; but rectified. Apart. And he is gone!
Hell hath its own again. Some sorrow chills
Ever the spirit, like a cloudlet nursed
In the star-giant’s bosom.

Helen |

Tell me, love,
More of these angels!

Festus |

There was one I loved
Of those immortals, of a lofty air,
Dimly divine and sad, and side by side
Him whom I spake of first she oft would stand
With her fair form—shadow illuminate—
Like to the dark moon in the young one’s arms.
She never murmured at the doom which made
The sorrow that contained her, as the air
Infolds the orb whereon we dwell, but spake
Of God’s will alway as most good and wise.
She had but little pleasure; but her all,
Such as it was, was in devising plans
Of bliss to come, or in the tales of Time
And the sweet early earth. She was in truth,
Our earth’s own angel. Ofttimes would she dwell
With long and luminous sweetness on her theme,
Unwearying, unpausing, as a world.
The sun would rise and set; the soul-like moon,
In passive beauty and receptive light—
Absorbing inspiration from the sun,
As doth from God His prophet ceaselessly—
She too would rise and set; and the far stars,
The third estate of Light, complete the round
Of the divine day;—still our angel spake,
And still I listened to the eloquent tongue
Which e’en on earth retained the tone of Heaven.
The shadow of a cloud upon a lake,
O’er which the wind hath all day held his breath,
Is not more calm and fair than her dear face—
So sweetly sad and so consolingly,
When she spake even on the end of earth.
Save that her eye grew darker, and her brow
Brighter with thought, as with galactic light
Mid Heaven when clearest, at such times, not I
Had known that earth were dearer unto her
Than other of the visitants divine,
Which hallow oft mine hours;—save, too, that then,
As though to touch but on that topic had,
Torpedo-like, numbed thought, she would straight cease
All converse suddenly, and kneel and seem
Inwardly praying with much power—rise,
And vanish into Heaven. My mind is full
Of stories she hath told me of our world.
No word an angel utters lose I ever.
One I will tell thee now.

Helen |

Do! let me hear!
Thy talk is the sweet extract of all speech,
And holds mine ear in blissful slavery.

Festus |

’Twas on a lovely summer afternoon,
Close by the grassy marge of a deep tarn,
Nigh halfway up a mountain, that we stood,
I and the angel, when she told me this.
Above us rose the grey rocks, by our side
Forests of pines, and the bright breaking wavelets
Came crowding, dancing to the brink, like thoughts
Unto our lips. Before us shone the sun.
The angel waved her hand ere she began,
As bidding earth be still. The birds ceased singing
And the trees breathing, and the lake smoothed down
Each shining wrinkle and the wind drew off.
Time leant him o’er his scythe and, listening, wept.
The circling world reined in her lightning pace
A moment; Ocean hushed his snow-maned steeds,
And a cloud hid the sun, as does the face
A meditative hand: then spake she thus:—
Scarce had the sweet song of the morning stars,
Which rang through space at the first sign of life
Our earth gave, springing from the lap of God
On to her orbit, when from Heaven
Came down a white-winged host; and in the east,
Where Eden’s Pleasance was, first furled their wings,
Alighting like to snowflakes. There they built,
Out of the riches of the soil around,
A house to God. There were the ruby rocks,
And there, in blocks, the quarried diamonds lay;
Opal and emerald mountain, amethyst,
Sapphire and chrysoprase, and jacinth stood
With the still action of a star, all light,
Like sea-based icebergs, blinding. These, with tools
Tempered in Heaven, the band angelic wrought,
And raised, and fitted, having first laid down
The deep foundations of the holy dome
On bright and beaten gold; and all the while
A song of glory hovered round the work
Like rainbow round a fountain. Day and night
Went on the hallowed labor till ’twas done.
And yet but thrice the sun set, and but thrice
The moon arose; so quick is work divine.
Tower, and roof, and pinnacle, without,
Were solid diamond. Within, the dome
Was eyeblue sapphire, sown with gold-bright stars
And clustering constellations; the wide floor
All emerald, earthlike, veined with gold and silver,
Marble and mineral of every hue
And marvellous quality, the meanest thing,
Where all things were magnificent, was gold—
The plainest. The high altar there was shaped
Out of one ruby heartlike. Columned round
With alabaster pure was all. And now
So high and bright it shone in the midday light,
It could be seen from Heaven. Upon their thrones
The sun-eyed angels hailed it, and there rose
A hurricane of blissfulness in Heaven,
Which echoed for a thousand years. One dark,
One solitary and foreseeing thought,
Passed, like a planet’s transit o’er the sun,
Across the brow of God; but soon he smiled
Towards earth, and that smile did consecrate
The temple to Himself. And they who built
Bowed themselves down and worshipped in its walls.
High on the front were writ these words—to God!
The heavenly built this for the earthly ones,
That in his worship both might mix on earth,
As afterward they hoped to do in Heaven.
Had man stood good in £den this had been:
He fell and Eden vanished. The bright place
Reared by the angels of all precious things,
For the joint worship of the sons of earth
And Heaven, fell with him, on the very day
He should have met God and His angels there—
The very day he disobeyed and joined
The host of death blackbannered, Eden fell;
The groves and grounds, which God the Lord’s own feet
Had hallowed; the all-hued and odorous bowers
Where angels wandered, wishing them in Heaven;
The trees of life and knowledge—trees of death
And madness, as they proved to man—all fell;
And that bright fane fell first. No death-doomed eye
Gazed on its glory. Earthquakes gulped it down.
The Temple of the Angels, vast enough
To hold air nations worshipping at once,
Lay in its grave; the cherubs’ flaming swords
The sole sad torches of its funeral.
Till at the flood, when the world’s giant heart
Burst like a shell, it scattered east and west,
And far and wide, among less noble ruins,
The fragments of that angel-builded fane,
Which was in Eden, and of which all stones
That now are precious, were; and still shall be,
Gathered again unto a happier end,
In the pure City of the Son of God,
And temple yet to be rebuilt in Zion;
Which, though once overthrown, and once again
Torn down to its foundations, in the quick
Of earth, shall soul-like yet re-rise from ruin—
High, holy, happy, stainless as a star,
Imperishable as eternity.
—The angel ended; and the winds, waves, clouds,
The sun, the woods, and merry birds went on
As theretofore, in brightness, strength and music.
One scarce could think that earth at all had fallen,
To look upon her beauty. If the brand
Of sin were on her brow, it was surely hid
In natural art from every eye but God’s.
All things seemed innocence and happiness.
I was all thanks. And look! the angel said,
Take these, and give to one thou lovest best:
Mine own hands saved from them the shining ruin
Whereof I have late told thee; and she gave
What now are greenly glowing on thine arms.
Ere I could answer, she was up, star-high!
Winging her way through Heaven.

Helen |

How shall I thank thee
Enough, or that kind angel who hath made
The gift to me dear doubly? I shall be
Afraid almost to wear them, but would not
Part with them for the treasures of all worlds.
How shew my thanks?

Festus |

Love me as now, dear beauty!
Present or absent always, and ’twill be
More than enough of recompense for me.

Helen |

Hast met that angel late-while?

Festus |

I have not.
Yet oft methinks I see her, catch a glimpse
Of her sun-circling pinions or bright feet
Which fitter seem for rainbows than for earth,
Or Heaven’s triumphal arch, more firm and pure
Than the world’s whitest marble;—see her seated oft
On some high snowy cloud-cliff, harp in hand,
Singing the sun to sleep as down he lays
His head of glory on the rocking deep:
And so sing thou to me.

Helen |

There, rest thyself. Sings.

Oh! not the diamond starry bright
Can so delight my view,
As doth the moonstone’s changing light
And gleamy glowing hue;
Now blue as Heaven, and then anon
As golden as the sun,
It hath a charm in every change—
In brightening, darkening, one.

And so with beauty, so with love,
And everlasting mind;
It takes a tint from Heaven above,
And shines as it’s inclined;
Or from the sun, or towards the sun,
With blind or brilliant eye,
And only lights as it reflects
The life-light of the sky.
He sleeps! The fate of many a gracious moral
This, to be stranded on a drowsy ear.

XXI

Scene—Garden and bower by the sea.

Lucifer and Elissa.
Lucifer |

Night comes, world-jewelled, as my bride should be.
The stars rush forth in myriads as to wage
War with the lines of Darkness; and the moon,
Pale ghost of Night, comes haunting the cold earth
After the sun’s red sea-death—quietless.
Immortal Night! I love thee. Thou and I
Are of one seed—the eldest blood of God.
He makes; we mar together all things—all
But our own selves. Love makes thee cold and tremble,
And me all fire. Do off that starry robe;
Catch me up to thee. Let us love, and die,
And weld our souls together, Night! But here
Cometh mine earthly. My Elissa! welcome.

Elissa |

Is’t not a lovely, nay, a heavenly eve?

Lucifer |

Thy presence only makes it so to me.
The moments thou art with me are like stars
Peering through my dark life.

Elissa |

Nay, speak not so,
Or I shall weep, and thou wilt turn away
From woman’s tears: yet are they woman’s wealth.

Lucifer |

Then keep thy treasures, lady! I would not have
The world, if prized at one sad tear of thine.
One tear of beauty can outweigh a world
Even of sin and sorrow, heavy as this;
But beauty cannot sin and should not weep,
For she is mortal. Oh! let deathless things
Alone weep. Why should aught that dies be sad?

Elissa |

The noble mind is oft too generous,
And, by protecting, weakens lesser ones;
And tears must come of feeling though they quench
As oft the light which love lit in the eye.

Lucifer |

And thy love ever hangs about my heart
Like the pure pearl-wreath which enrings thy brow.
I meant not to be mournful. Tel me, now,
How thou hast passed the hours since last we met?

Elissa |

I have, stayed the livelong day within this bower;
It was here that thou did promise me to come—
Watching from wanton morn to repentant eve,
The self-same roses ope and close; untired,
Listening the same hirds’ first and latest songs—
And still thou camest not. To the mind which waits
Upon one hour the others are but slaves.
The week hath but one day—the day one hour—
That hour of the heart—that lord of time.

Lucifer |

Sweet one! I raced with light and passed the laggard
To meet thee—or, I mean I could have done—
Yea, have outsped the very dart of Death—
Se much I sought; and were I living light
From God, with leave to range the world, and choose
Another brow than His whereon to beam—
To mark what even an angel could but covet—
A something lovelier than Heaven’s loveliness—
To thee I straight would dart unheeding all
The lives of other worlds, even those who name
Themselves thy kind; for oft my mind o’ersoars
The stars; and pondering upon what may be
Of their chief lording natures, man’s seems worst—
The darkest, meanest, which, through all these worlds,
Drags what is deathless, may be, down to dust.

Elissa |

Speak not so bitterly of human kind;
I know that thou dost love it. Hast not heard
Of those great spirits, who, the greater grow,
The better we are able them to prize?
Great minds can never cease; yet have they not
A separate estate of deathlessness:
The future is a remnant of their life:
Our time is part of theirs, not theirs of ours:
They know the thoughts of ages long before.
It is not the weak mind feels the great mind’s might;
None but the great can test it. Does the oak
Or reed feel the strong storm most? Oh! unsay
What thou hast said of man; nor deem me wrong.
Mind cannot mind despise—it is itself.
Mind must love mind: the great and good are friends;
And he is but half great who is not good.
And, oh! humanity is the fairest flower
Blooming in earthly breasts; so sweet and pure,
That it might freshen even the fadeless wreaths
Twined round the golden harps of those in Heaven.

Lucifer |

For thy sake I will love even man, or aught.
Spirit were I, and a mere mortal thou,
For thy sake I would even seek to die;
That, dead, or living, I might still be with thee.
But no! I’ll deem thee deathless—mind and make,
And worthier of some spirit’s love than mine;
Yea, of the first-born of God’s sons, could he
In that sweet shade thy beauty casts o’er all,
One moment lay and cool his burning soul;
Or might the ark of his wide flood-like woe
But rest upon that mount of peace and bliss—
Thy heart inbosomed in all beauteousness.
Nay, lady! shrink not. Thinkest thou I am he?

Elissa |

Thou art too noble, far. I oft have wished,
Ere I knew thee, I had some spirit’s love;
But thou art more like what I sought than man,
And a forbidden quest, it seems; for thou
Hast more of awe than love about thee, like
The mystery of dreams which we can feel,
But cannot touch.

Lucifer |

Nay, think not so! It is wrong.
Come, let us sit in this thy favourite bower,
And I win hear thee sing. I love that voice,
Dipping more softly on the subject ear
Than that calm kiss the willow gives the wave—
A soft rich tone, a rainbow of sweet sounds,
Just spanning the soothed sense. Come, nay me not.

Elissa |

Do thou lead out some lay; I’ll follow thine.

Lucifer |

Well, I agree. It will spare me much of shame
In coming after thee. My song is said
Of Lucifer the star. See there he shines! Sings.

I am Lucifer, the star:
Oh! think on me,
As I lighten from afar
The Heavens and thee!
In town, or tower,
Or this fair bower,
Oh! think on me;
Though a wandering star,
As the loveliest are,
I love but thee.

Lady! When I brightest beam,
Love! look on me!
I am not what I may seem
To the world or thee;
But fain would love
With thee above,
Where thou wilt be.
But if love be a dream,
As the world doth deem,
What is’t to me?

Elissa |

Could we but deem the stars had hearts, and loved,
They would seem happier, holier, even than now;
And ah! why not? they are so beautiful;
And love is part and union in itself
Of all that is in nature brilliant, pure—
Of all in feeling sacred and sublime.
Surely the stars are images of love:
The sunbeam and the starbeam doth bring love.
The sky, the sea, the rainbow, and the stream
And dark blue hill, where all the loveliness
Of earth and Heaven, in sweet extatic strife,
Seem mingling hues which might immortal be,
If length of life by height of beauty went:
All seem but made for love—love made for all:
We do become all heart with those we love:
It is nature’s self—it is everywhere—it is here.

Lucifer |

To me there is but one place in the world,
And that where thou art; for where’er I be,
Thy love doth seek its way into my heart,
As will a bird into her secret nest:
Then sit and sing; sweet wing of beauty, sing.

Elissa |

Bright one! who dwellest in the happy skies,
Rejoicing in thy light as does the brave,
In his keen flashing sword, and his strong arm’s
Swift swoop, canst thou, from among the sons of men,
Single out those who love thee as do I
Thee from thy fellow glories? If so, star,
Turn hither thy bright front; I love thee, friend.
Thou hast no deeds of darkness. All thou dost
Is to us light and beauty: yea, thou art
A globe all glory; thou who at the first
Didst answer to the angels which in Heaven
Sang the bright birth of earth, and even now,
As star by tar is born, dost sing the same
With countless hosts in infinite delight,
Be unto me a moment! Write thy bright
Light on my heart before the sun shall rise
And vanquish sight. Thou art the prophecy
Of light which He fulfils. Speak, shining star,
Drop from thy golden lips the truths of Heaven;
First of all stars and favourite of the skies,
Apostle of the sun—thou upon whom
His mantle resteth—speak, prophetic beauty!
Speak, shining star out of the heights of Heaven,
Beautiful being, speak to God for man!
Is it because of beauty thou wast chosen
To be the sign of sin? For surely sin
Must be surpassing lovely when for her
Men forfeit God’s reward of deathless bliss
And life divine; or, is it that such beauty,
Sometimes, before the truth, and sometimes after,
As is a moral or a prophecy,
Is ever warning? Why wast thou accorded
To the great Evil? Is it because thou art
Of all the sun’s bright servants nearest earth?
And shall we then forget that Christ hath said
He is thyself, the light-bringer of Heaven?
Star of the morning! unto us thou art
The presage of a day of power. Like thee
Let us rejoice in life, then, and proclaim
A glory coming greater than our own.
All ages are but stars to that which comes,
Sunlike. Oh! speak, star! Lift thou up thy voice
Out of yon radiant ranks, and I on earth,
As thou in Heaven, will bless the Lord God ever.
Hear, Lucifer, thou star! I answer thee. Sings.

Oh! ask me not to look and love,
But bid me worship thee;
For thou art earthly things above,
As far as angels be:
Then whether in the eve or morn
Thou dost the maiden skies adorn,
Oh! let me worship thee!

I am but as this drop of dew;
Oh! let me worship thee!
Thy light, thy strength, is ever new,
Even as the angels’ be:
And as this dew-drop, till it dies,
Bosoms the golden stars and skies,
Oh! let me worship thee!

But, dearest, why that dark look?

Lucifer |

Let it not
Cloud thine even with its shadow: but the ground
Of all great thoughts is sadness; and I mused
Upon past happiness. Well—be it past!
Did Lucifer, as I do, gaze on thee,
The flame of woe would flicker in his breast,
And straight die out—the brightness of thy beauty
Quenching it as the sun doth earthly fire.

Elissa |

Nay, look not on me so intensely sad.

Lucifer |

Forgive me: it was an agony of bliss.
I love thee, and am full of happiness.
My bosom bounds beneath thy smile as doth
The sea’s unto the moon, his mighty mistress;
Lying and looking up to her, and saying—
Lovely! lovely! lovely! lady of the Heavens!
Oh! when the thoughts of other joyous days—
Perchance, if such may be, of happier times—
Are falling gently on the memory
Like autumn leaves distained with dusky gold,
Yet softly as a snowflake; and the smile
Of kindliness, like thine, is beaming on me—
Oh! pardon, if I lose myself, nor know
Whether I be with Heaven or thee.

Elissa |

Use not
Such ardent phrase, nor mix the claim of aught
On earth with thoughts more than with hopes of Heaven.

Lucifer |

Hopes, lady! I have none.

Elissa |

Thou must have. All
Have hopes, however wretched they may be,
Or blest. It is hope which lifts the lark so high—
Hope of a lighter air and bluer sky:
And the poor hack which drops down on the flints—
Upon whose eye the dust is settling—
He hopes to die. No being is which hath
Not love and hope.

Lucifer |

Yes—one! The ancient Ill,
Dwelling and damned through all which is; that spirit
Whose heart is hate—who is the foe of God—
The foe of all.

Elissa |

How knowest thou such doth live?
Love is the happy privilege of mind—
Love is the reason of all living things.
A Trinity there seems of principles,
Which represent and rule created life—
The love of self, our fellows, and our God.
In all throughout one common feeling reigns:
Each doth maintain and is maintained by the other;
All are compatible—all needful; one
To life—to virtue one—and one to bliss;
Which thus together make the power, the end,
And the perfection of created Being.
From these three principles doth every deed,
Desire, and will, and reasoning, good or bad, come;
To these they all determine—sum and scheme:
The three are one in centre and in round;
Wrapping the world of life as do the skies
Our world. Hail! air of love by which we live!
How sweet, how fragrant! Spirit, though unseen—
Void of gross sign—is scarce a simple essence,
Immortal, immaterial, though it be.
One only simple essence liveth—God—
Creator, uncreate. The brutes beneath,
The angels high above us, with ourselves,
Are but compounded things of mind and form.
In all things animate is therefore cored
An elemental sameness of existence;
For God, being Love, in love created all,
As He contains the whole, and penetrates.
Seraphs love God, and angels love the good:
We love each other; and these lower lives,
Which walk the earth in thousand diverse shapes,
According to their reason, love us too:
The most intelligent affect us most.
Nay, man’s chief wisdom’s love—the love of God.
The new religion—final perfect, pure—
Was that of Christ and love. His great command—
His all-sufficing precept—was’t not love?
Truly to love ourselves we must love God—
To love God we must all His creatures love—
To love His creatures, both ourselves and Him.
Thus love is all that’s wise, fair, good, and happy.

Lucifer |

How knowest thou God doth live? Why did He not,
With that creating hand which sprinkled stars
On space’s bosom, bidding her breathe and wake
From the long death-like trance in which she lay—
With that same hand which scattered o’er the sky,
As this small dust I strew upon the wind,
Yon countless orbs, aye fixing each on Him
Its flaming eye, which winks and blenches oft
Beneath His glance—with the finger of that hand
Which spangled o’er infinity with suns,
And wrapped it round about Him as a robe—
Why did He not write out his own great name
In spheres of fire, that Heaven might alway tell
To every creature, God? If not, then why
Should I believe when I behold around me
Nought scarce, save ill and woe?

Elissa |

God surely lives!
Without God all things are in tunnel darkness.
Let there be God, and all are sun—all God.
And to the just soul, in a future state,
Defect’s dark mist, thick-spreading o’er this vale,
Shall dim the eye no more, nor bound survey;
And evil, now which boweth being down
As dew the grass, shall only fit all life
For fresher growth and for intenser day,
Where God shall dry all tears as the sun dew.

Lucifer |

Oh! lady, I am wretched.

Elissa |

Say not so.
With thee I could not deem myself unhappy.
Hark to the sea! It sounds like the near hum
Of a great city.

Lucifer |

Say, the city earth;
For such these orbs are in the realms of space.

Elissa |

I dreamed once that the night came down to me;
In figure, oh! too like thine own for truth,
And looked into me with his thousand eyes,
And that made me unhappy; but it passed,
And I half wished it back. Mind hath its earth
And Heaven. The many petty common thoughts
On which we daily tread, as it were, make one,
And above which few look; the other is
That high and welkin-like infinity—
The brighter, upper half of the mind’s world,
Thick with great sun-like and constellate thoughts;
And in the night of mind, which is our sleep,
These thoughts shine out in dreams. Dreams double life;
They are the heart’s bright shadow on life’s flood;
And even the step from death to deathlessness—
From this earth’s gross existence unto Heaven—
Can scarce be more than from the harsh hot day
To sleep’s soft scenes, the moonlight of the mind.
The wave is never weary of the wind,
But in mountainous playfulness leaps to it
Always; but mind gets weary of the world,
And glooms itself in sleep, like a sweet smile,
Line by line, settling into proper sadness;
For sleep seems part of our immortality:
And why should any thing that dies be sad?
Last night I dreamed I walked within a hall—
The inside of the world. Long shroud-like lights
Lit up its lift-like dome and pale wide walls,
Horizon-like; and every one was there:
It was the house of Death, and Death was there.
We could not see him, but he was a feeling:
We knew he was around us—heard us—eyed us;
But where wast thou? I never met thee once.
And all was still as nothing; or as God,
Deep judging, when the thought of making first
Quickened and stirred within Him; and He made
All Heaven at one thought as at a glance.
Noise was there none; and yet there was a sound
Which seemed to be half like silence, half like sound.
All crept about still as the cold wet worms,
Which slid among our feet, we could not scape from.
Bound me were ruined fragments of dead gods—
Those shadows of the mystery of One—
And the red worms, too, flourished over these,
For marble is a shadow weighed with mind;
Each being, as men of old believed, distinct
In form, and place, and power. But Oh! not all
The gathered gods of Eld could shine like ours,
No more than all yon stars could make a sun.
But truly then men lived in moral night,
’Neath a dim starlight of religious truth.
I felt my spirit’s spring gush out more clear,
Gazing on these: they beautified my mind
As rocks and flowers reflected do a well.
Mind makes itself like that it lives amidst,
And on; and thus, among dreams, imaginings,
And scenes of awe, and purity, and power,
Grows sternly sweet and calm—all beautiful
With god-like coldness and unconsciousness
Of mortal passion, mental toil; until,
Like to the marble model of a god,
It doth assume a firm and dazzling form,
Scarcely less incorruptible than that
It emblems: and so grew, methought, my mind.
Matter hath many qualities; mind, one:
It is irresistible: pure power—pure god.
While wandering on I met what seemed myself:
Was it not strange that we should meet, and there?
But all is strange in dreaming, as in death,
And waking, as in life: nought is not strange.
Methought that I was happy, because dead.
All hurried to and fro; and many cried
To each other—Can I do thee any good?
But no one heeded: nothing could avail:
The world was one great grave. I looked, and saw
Time on his two great wings—one, night—one, day—
Fly, moth-like, right into the flickering sun;
So that the sun went out, and they both perished.
And one gat up and spake—a holy man—
Exhorting them; but each and all cried out—
Go to!—it helps not—means not: we are dead.
Death spake no word methought, but me he made
Speak for him; and I dreamed that I was Death;
Then, that Death only lived: all things were mixed;
Up and down shooting, like the brain’s fierce dance
In a delirium, when we are apt to die.
Hell is my heir; what kin to me is Heaven?
Bring out your hearts before me. Give your limbs
To whom ye list or love. My son, Decay,
Will take them: give them him. I want your hearts,
That I may take them up to God. There came
These words among us, but we knew not whence;
It was as if the air spake. And there rose
Out of the earth a giant thing, all earth;
His eye was earthy, and his arm was earthy:
He had no heart. He but said, I am Decay;
And, as he spake, he crumbled into earth,
And the was nothing of him. But we all
Lifted our faces up at the word, God,
And spied a dark star high above in the midst
Of others, numberless as are the dead.
And all plucked out their hearts, and held them in
Their right hands. Many tried to pick out specks
And stains, but could not: each gave up his heart.
And something—all things—nothing—it was Death,
Said, as before, from air—Let us to God!
And straight we rose, leaving behind the raw
Worms and dead gods, all of us—soared and soared
Right upwards, till the star I told thee of
Looked like a moon—the moon became a sun:
The sun—there came a hand between the sun and us,
And its five fingers made five nights in air.
God tore the glory from the sun’s broad brow,
And flung the flaming scalp off flat to Hell.
I saw Him do it; and it passed close by us.
And then I heard a long, cold, skeleton scream,
Like a trumpet whining through a catacomb,
Which made the sides of that great grave shake in.
I saw the world and vision of the dead
Dim itself off—and all was life! I woke,
And felt the high sun blazoning on my brow
His own almighty mockery of woe,
And fierce and infinite laugh at things which cease.
Hell hath its light—and Heaven; he burns with both.
And my dream broke, like life from the last limb—
Quivering; so loth I felt to let it go,
Just as I thought I had caught sight of Heaven.
It came to nought, as dreams of Heaven on earth
Do always.

Lucifer |

It is time we part again.

Elissa |

Farewell, then, gentle stars! To-night, farewell!
For we all part at once. It is thus the bright
Visions and joys of youth break up—but they
For ever. When ye shine again I will
Be with ye; for I love ye next to him.
To all, adieu! When shall I see thee next?

Lucifer |

Lady, I know not.

Elissa |

Say!

Lucifer |

Never! perchance.

Elissa |

There is but one immortal in the world
Who need say—never!

Lucifer |

What if I were he?

Elissa |

But thou art not he; and thou shalt not say it.
Stars vise and set—rise, set, and rise again
In their sublime-like beauty through all time.
Why should not we, too, ever meet, like them?

Lucifer |

I see no beauty—feel no love—all things
Are unlovely.

Elissa |

O earth! be deaf; and Heaven!
Shut thy blue eye. He doth blaspheme the world.
Dost not love me?

Lucifer |

Love thee? Ay! Earth and Heaven
Together could not make a love like mine.

Elissa |

When wilt thou come again? To-morrow?

Lucifer |

Well.
And then I cross yon sea ere I return;
For I have matters in another land.
Fear not.

Elissa |

When will our parting days be over?

Lucifer |

Oh! soon—soon! Think of me love, on the waters!
Be happy! and, for me, I love few things more
Than at night to ride upon the broad-backed billow,
Seaing along and plunging on his precipitous path;
While the red moon is westering low away,
And the mad waves are fighting for the stars,
Like men for—what they know not.

Elissa |

Scorner!

Lucifer |

Saint!

Elissa |

The world hath much that’s great; and but one sea,
Which is her spirit; and to her it stands
As the mad monarch passion to the heart—
Fathomless, overwhelming, which receives
The rivers of all feeling; in whose depths
Lie wrecked the riches of all nature. God,
When He did make thee, moved upon thee then,
And left His impress there, the same even now
As when thy last wave leapt from Chaos.—Hark!
Nay, there is some one coming.

Festus |

Entering.

It is I.
I said we should be sure to meet thee here:
For I have brought one who would speak with thee.

Lucifer |

Thanks! and where is he?

Festus |

Yonder. He would not
Come up so far as this.

Lucifer |

Who is it?

Festus |

I know not
Who he may be, or what; but I can guess.

Lucifer |

Remain a moment, love, till I return.

Elissa |

Nay—let me leave!

Lucifer |

Not yet: do not dislike him.
He is a friend, and—more another time.

Festus |

I am sorry, lady, to have caused this parting.
I fear I am unwelcome.

Elissa |

We were parting.

Festus |

Then am I doubly sorry; for I know
It is the saddest and the sacredest
Moment of all with those who love.

Elissa |

He is coming!
So I forgive thee.

Lucifer |

I must leave thee, love:
I know not for how long; it rests with thee
If it seem long at all. Eternity
Might pass, and I not know it in thy love.

Elissa |

If to believe that I do love thee always
May make time fly the fleeter—

Lucifer |

I’ll believe it—
Trust me. I leave this lady in thy charge.

Festus |

Be kind—wait on her—may he, love?

Elissa |

Thou knowest. I receive him as thy friend
Whenever he come.

Festus |

I ask no higher title
Than friend of the lovely and the generous.

Elissa |

Farewell!

Festus |

Lady! I will not forget my trust.
Apart. The breeze which curls the lake’s bright lip but lifts
A purer, deeper, water to the light;
The ruffling of the wild bird’s wing but wakes
A warmer beauty and a downier depth.
That startled shrink, that faintest blossom-blush
Of constancy alarmed!—Love! if thou hast
One weapon in that shining armoury,
The quiver on thy shoulder, where thou keep’st
Each arrowy eye-beam feathered with a sigh;—
If from that bow, shaped so like Beauty’s lip
Strung with a string of pearls, thou wilt twang forth
Bat one dart, fair into the mark I mean—
Do it, and I will worship thee for ever:
Yea, I will give thee glory and a name
Known, sunlike, in all nations. Heart, be still!

Lucifer |

This parting over—

Elissa |

Yes, this one—and then?

Lucifer |

Why, then another, may be.

Elissa |

No—no more.
I’ll be unhappy if thou tell’st me so.

Lucifer |

Well, then—no more.

Elissa |

But when wilt thou come back?

Lucifer |

Almost before thou wishest. He will know.

Elissa |

I shall be always asking him. Farewell! Goes.

Lucifer |

Shine on, ye stars! and light her to her rest;
Scarce are ye worthy for her handmaidens.
Why, Hell would laugh to learn I had been in love.
I have affairs in Hell. Wilt go with me?

Festus |

Yes, in a month or two:—not just this minute.

Lucifer |

I shall be there and back again ere then.

Festus |

Meanwhile I can amuse myself: so, go!
But sometime I would fain behold thy home,
And pass the gates of fire.

Lucifer |

And so thou shalt.
My home is everywhere where spirit is.
All things are as I meant them. Fare thee well. Goes.

Festus |

The strongest passion which I have is honour:
I would I had none: it is in my way.

XXII

Scene—Everywhere.

Lucifer and Festus.
Festus |

Why, earth is in the very midst of Heaven!
And space, though void of things, feels full of God.
Hath space no limit?

Lucifer |

None to thee. Yet, if
Infinite, it would equal God; and that
To think of is most vain.

Festus |

And yet if not
Infinite how can God exist therein?

Lucifer |

I say not.

Festus |

No. So soon when placed beside
The infinite the poor immortal fails.

Lucifer |

Space is God’s space: Eternity is His
Eternity; His, Heaven. He only holds
Perfections which are but the impossible
To other beings.

Festus |

We are things of time.

Lucifer |

With God time is not. Unto Him all is
Present Eternity. Worlds, beings, years,
With all their natures, powers, and events,
The range whereof when making He ordains,
Unfold themselves like flowers. He foresees
Not, but sees all at once. Time must not be
Contrasted with Eternity: ’tis not
A second of the everlasting year.
Perfections although infinite with God,
Are all identical; as much of Him—
And holy is His mercy, merciful
His wisdom, wise His love, and kind his wrath—
As form, extension, parts, are requisites
Of matter. Spirit hath no parts. It is
One substance, whole and indivisible,
Whatever else. Souls see each other clear
At one glance, as two drops of rain in air
Might look into each other, had they life.
Death does away disguise. Even here I feel
Among these mighty things, that, as I am,
I am akin to God;—that I am part
Of the use universal, and can grasp
Some portion of that reason in the which
The whole is ruled and founded;—that I have
A spirit nobler in its cause and end,
Lovelier in order, greater in its powers,
Than all these bright immensities—how swift!
And doth creation’s tide for ever flow,
Nor ebb with like destruction? World on world,
Are they for ever heaping up, and still
The mighty measure never full?

Lucifer |

To act
Is powers habit; alway to create,
God’s; which, thus ever causing worlds, to Him
Nought cumbrous more than new down to a wing,
Aye multiplies at once my power and pain.
I have seen many frames of being pass.
This generation of the universe
Will soon be gathered to its grave. These worlds,
Which bear its sky-pall, soon will follow thine.
I, both. All things must die.

Festus |

What are ye orbs?
The words of God—the Scriptures of the skies?
For words with Him cannot be passing, nor
Less real, vast, or glorious than yourselves.
The world is a great poem, and the worlds
The words it is writ in, and we souls the thoughts.
Ye cannot die.

Lucifer |

Think not on death. Here all
Is life, light, beauty. Harp not so on death.

Festus |

I cannot help me, spirit! Chide no more.
As who dare gaze the sun, doth after see
Betwixt him and else a dark sun in his eye;
So I, once having braved my burning doom,
See nought beside—or that in everything.
Hark, what is that I hear?

Lucifer |

An angel weeping—
Earth’s guardian angel. She is ever weeping.

Festus |

See where she flies, spirit-torn, round the heavens,
Like a fore-feel of madness about the brain.

Angel of Earth |

Star, stars!
Stop your bright cars!
Stint your breath—
Repent ere worse—
Think of the death
Of the universe.
Fear doom, and fear,
The fate of your kin-sphere.
As a corse in the tomb,
Earth! thou art laid in doom:
The worm is at thy heart.
I see all things part:—
The bright air thicken,
Thunder-stricken:
Birds from the sky
Shower like leaves:
Streamlets stop
Like ice on leaves:
The sun go blind:
Swoon the wind
On the high hill top—
Swoon and die:
Earth rear off her cities
As a horse his rider;
And still, with each death-strain,
Her heart-wound tear wider:
The lion roar and die
With his eye-balls on the sky:
The eagle scream
And drop like a beam:
Men crowd and cry,
Out on this deathful dream!
A low dull sound—
’Tis the march of many bones
Under ground;
Up! and they fling,
Like a fly’s wing,
Off them the grey grave-stones;
They sit in their biers—
Father and mother,
Man and wife,
Sister and brother,
As in life;
Lady and lover—
Love all over.
Their flesh re-appears—
Their hearts beat—
Their eyes have tears:
Woe! woe!
Do they speak?
Stir? No!
Tongues were too weak,
Save to repeat
Woe!
But they smile
In a while;
For to wipe from His word
The dust of years,
He comes! he comes! the Lord,
Man-God, re-appears;
To bless, and to save
From death and the grave—
To redeem and deliver
For ever and ever!
The dead rise—
Death dies.
Go, Time, and sink
Thy great thoughts in the sea!
And quench thy red link!
Let him flutter to rest
On thy God-nursing breast,
Eternity!
Mother Eternity!
What is for me?

Festus |

Poor angel! Ah! it is the good who suffer.
Look! like a cloud, she has wept herself away.
What of this world we view and all yon worlds?
If God made not all things from nothing, how
Is He creator? Something must exist
If otherwise, eternal with Himself;
And all things had not origin in Him.

Lucifer |

He made all things of Him. The visible world
Is as the Christ of nature; God the maker
In matter made self manifest through time.
All things are formed of all things—all of God.
The world is made of wonders. Every day
Is born a new creation. Every orb
Hath its revealed word; and every race
Of Being hath its judgment, or shall have.

Festus |

Are all these worlds, then, stocked with souls like man’s—
Free, fallible, and sinful?

Lucifer |

Ay, they are.
All creature-minds, like man’s, are fallible.
The seraph who in Heaven highest stands
May fall to ruin deepest. God is mind—
Pure, perfect, sinless. Man imperfect is—
Momently sinning. Evil then results
From imperfection. The idea of good
Is owned in imperfection’s lowest form.
God would not, could not, make aught wholly ill,
Nor aught not like to err. Man never was
Perfect nor pure, or he would be so now.
Thy nature hath some excellencies—these
Oft thwarted by low lusts and wicked wills.
What then? They are necessitate in kind,
As change in nature, or as shade to light.
No darkness hath the sun—no weakness God:
These only be the faulty qualities
Of secondary natures—planets, men.
God hath no attributes unless To Be
Be one: ’twould mix Him with the things He hath made.
God is all God, as life is that which lives.
I am a mighty spirit, and yet I
Am but to God what lightning is to light:
Lightning slays one thing—light makes all things live.
Bear, then, thy necessary ills with grace;
No positive estate or principle
Is Evil—debtor wholly for its form
And measure to defect—defect to good.
Good’s the sole positive principle in the world;
It is only thus, that what God makes, He loves—
And must: the others are but off-shoots. Ill
Is limited. One cannot form a scheme
For universal evil; not even I.

Festus |

Can imperfection from perfection come?
Can God make aught defective?

Lucifer |

How aught else?
There are but three proportions in all things—
The greater—equal—less. God could not make
A God above Himself, nor equal with—
By nature and necessity the Highest;
So, if He make, it must be lesser minds
Little and less from angels down to men,
Whose natures are imperfect, as His own
Must be all-perfect. These two states are not,
Except as whole unto its parts, opposed;
And evil is itself no ill unless
Creation be.

Festus |

Is God the cause of evil?

Lucifer |

So far as evil comes from imperfection,
And imperfection from the things He hath made,
And what He hath made from His will to make.

Festus |

Oh! let me rest, be it but a moment’s pause!
This endless light-like journey wearies me.
Remember still my spirit toils in dust—
A dark close cloud.

Lucifer |

Alight, then, on this orb.
I am not wearied: I will watch by thee.
He sleeps—he dreams. How far men see in dreams!
In dreams they can accomplish worlds of things:
The heart then suffers a fusion of all feeling
Back to its youthful hours of innocence,
And nakedness, and paradise; ere yet
The world had wound a perishing garb around it;
While yet its God came down and spake to it.
Such and so great are dreams. My might, my being
To him is but a dream’s. And could a state
To come fill up their dream-stretched minds, they might
Be gods. And may it not be so? Then man
Is worth my ruining. What does he dream?
With all the sway his spirit now exerts
O’er time, space, thought it is but a shadowy sway,
Light as a mountain shadow on a lake.
Mine is the mountain’s self. A touch would shake
To nought whatever his soul now feels or acts;
But not a world-quake could touch aught of mine:
Thus much we differ. I will not envy man.
Power alone makes being bearable.
And yet this dream-power is mind-power—real:
All things are real: fiction cannot be.
A thought is real as the world—a dream
True as all God doth know—with whom all is true.
The deep dense sleep of half-dead exhaustedness!
Would I could feel it. Ah! he wakes at last.

Festus |

Oh! I have dreamed a dream so beautiful!
Methought I lay as it were here; and, lo!
A spirit came and gave me wings of light,
Which thrice I waved delighted. Up we flew
Sheer through the shining air, far past the sun’s
Broad blazing disk—past where the great great snake
Binds in his bright coil half the host of Heaven—
Past thee, Orion! who, with arm uplift,
Threatening the throne of God, dost ever stand
Sublimely impious; and thy mighty mace
Whirling on high, down from its glorious seat
Drops, crushed and shattered, many a shining world.
And so the brave and beautiful of old
Believed thou wast a giant made of worlds:
And they were rights if thus they bodied out
The immortal mind; for it hath starlike beauty,
And worldlike might; and is as high above
The things it scorns, and will make war with God,
Though He gave it earth and Heaven, and arms to win
Them both; and, spite of lust and pride, to earn them.
And now thy soul informs yon hundred stars,
As mine my limbs—well, ’tis a noble end.
What now to thee be mortal maid or goddess?
Look! she who fled thee once, now loves and longs
To clasp thee to her cold and beamy breast.
Pine moon! thou art as far below him now,
As once she was above thee, thou of the world-belt!
And she who had thee, and who knew thee god,
Died of her boast, and lies in her own dust.
And she who loved thee, the young blushy Morning,
Who caught thee in her arms, and bore thee off
Far o’er the lashing seas to a lonely isle,
Where she might pleasure longer and in secret—
That love undid thee; and it is so now:
Whether the beauty seek, or flee, or have,
’Tis a like ill—this beauty doubly mortal.
What though the moon with madness slew thee there,
Let me believe it was within the arms
That loved thee even in the stroke of death,
And that there snapped the lightning link of life.
Kill, but not conquer, man nor mind may gods.
Thou image of the Almighty error, man!
Banished and banned to Heaven, by a weak world,
Which makes the minds it cannot master gods
And thou, the first and greatest of half-gods,
Which they in olden time did star together
To an idolatrous immortality;
Who nationalized the Heavens, and gave all stars
Unto the spirits of the good and brave,
Forestalling God by ages—wondrous men!
And if—beguiled by wine, and the low wiles
Thou wouldst not creep to meet, and a drunken sleep,
Like to high noon in the midst of all his might,
Close by the brink of immortality—
The deep dominions of thy sea-sire, thou
Didst lose thy light by kings who hate the great,
Thou only hadst to stand up to the sun,
And gain again thine eyes. So the great king,
The world, the tyrant we elect, in vain
Puts out the eyes of mind: it looks to God,
And reaps its light again. Wherefore, revenge!
Out with the sword! the world will run before thee,
Orion! belted giant of the skies!
Thou with the treble strain of godhood in thee!
March! there is nought to hinder thee in Heaven:—
Past that great sickle saved for one day’s work,
When He who sowed shall reap Creation’s field;—
Past those high diademed orbs which show to man
His crown to come;—up through the starry strings
Of that high harp close by the feet of God,
Which He, methought, took up and struck, till Heaven,
In love’s immortal madness, rang and reeled;
The stars fell on their faces; and, far off,
The wild world halted—shook his burning man—
Then, like a fresh-blown trumpet blast, went on,
Or like a god gone mad. On, on we flew,
I and the spirit, far beyond all things
Of measure, motion, time and aught create;
Where the stars stood on the edge of the first nothing,
And looked each other in the face and fled—
Past even the last long starless void, to God;
Whom straight I heard, methought, commanding thus:
Immortal! I am God. Hie back to earth,
And say to all, that God doth say—Love God!

Lucifer |

God visits men adreaming: I, awake.

Festus |

And my dream changed to one of general doom.
Wilt hear it?

Lucifer |

Ay, say on! It is but a dream.

Festus |

God made all mind and motion cease; and, lo!
The whole was death and peace. An endless time
Obtained, in which the power of all made failed.
God bade the worlds to judgment, and they came—
Pale, trembling, corpse-like. To the souls therein
Then spake the Maker: Deathless spirits, rise!
And straight they thronged around the throne. His arm
The Almighty then uplift, and smote the worlds
Once, and they fell in fragments like to spray,
And vanished in their native void. He shook
The stars from Heaven like rain-drops from a bough;
Like tears they poured adown creation’s face.
Spirit and space were all things. Matter, death,
And time, left even not a wake to tell
Where once their track o’er being. God’s own light
Undarkened and unhindered by a sun,
Glowed forth alone in glory. And through all
A dear and tremulous sense of God prevailed,
Like to the blush of love upon the cheek,
Or the full feeling lightening through the eye,
Or the quick music in the chords of harps.
God judged all creatures unto bliss or woe,
According to their deeds, and faith, and His
Own will: and straight the saved upraised a voice
Which seemed to emulate eternity
In its triumphant overblossedness.
The lost leapt up and cursed God to His face—
A curse might make the sun turn cold to hear;
And thee, in all thy burning glory, tremble,
In front of all thine angels, like a chord.
Rage writhed each brow into a changeless scowl.
Madly they mocked at God, and dared His eye,
Safe in their curse of deathlessness. To Hell
They hied like storms; and, cursing all things, each
Soul wrapped him in his shroud of fire for aye,
With one long loud howl which seemed to deafen Heaven—
And then I woke.

Lucifer |

A wild fantastic dream!
A mere mirage of mind! Come, let us leave:
We have seen enough of this world.

Festus |

Lift me up then!
World upon world how they come rolling on!
But none that I see are so fair as earth:
There is so much to love that is purely earth.
Now I could wander all day in the wood,
Where nature, like a sibyl, writes the fate
Of all that live on her red forest leaves:
And have no other aim than wandering
Within that wood, and wind my arms around
Its grey gaunt trunks, and think and feel to them;
While the wind, sinking moans over the earth
Like a giant over some dead captive dame,
Whom death had saved from madness and his love;—
Could tramp across the brown and springy moor,
And over the purple ling, and never tire;—
Could look upon the ripple of a river,
Or on a tree’s long shadow down a hill,
For a whole summer’s day, wishing the sun
Would drink my soul up to him as he draws
Dew from the earth. These things are in my mind,
And suns and systems cannot drive them out.
Dost ravage a these worlds?

Lucifer |

Ay, all mine own.
Where spirit is, there evil; and the world
Is full of me as ocean is of brine.

Festus |

God is all perfect; man imperfect. Thou?

Lucifer |

I am the imperfection of the whole—
The pitch profoundest of the fallible.
Myself the all of evil which exists—
The ocean heaped into a single surge.

Festus |

O God! why wouldst Thou make the universe?

Lucifer |

Child! quench yon suns; strip death of its decay;
Men of their follies—Hell of all its woe!
These, if thou didst, thou couldst not banish me.
I am the shadow which Creation casts
From God’s own light.—But here we are, at Hell.
Hark to the thunderous roaring of its fires!
Yet ere we further pass—stop! dost thou shrink?

Festus |

At nought—not I! Come on, fiend! follow me!

XXIV

Scene—Colonnade and lawn.

Festus and Clara.
Clara |

What is it thou wilt tell me?

Festus |

I have seen
What ne’er again may be, nor e’er till now hath been.

Clara |

Where didst thou see—and what?

Festus |

In space. He took me there,
Of whom I oft have told thee. Midst in air
Was God. I’ll tell thee that he told the spheres;
For the great family of the universe
Bound Him were gathered as a fire: but we
Held back; and, saving God, none did us see.
Though round his throne in sunny halo rolls
A ceaseless, countless throng of sainted souls.

Clara |

Say on, love! Let me hear.

Festus |

A sound, then, first
I heard as of a pent-up flood just burst:
It was the rush of God’s world-winnowing wing;
Which bowed the orbs as flowers are bowed by breath of spring.
And then a voice I heard, a voice sublime—
To which the hoarded thunders of all time
Pealing earth’s death-knell shall a whisper be—
Saying these words—Where will ye worship me?
Ay, where shall be your Maker’s holy place?
The Heaven of Heavens is poor before His face.
How shall ye mete my temple, ye who die?
Look! can ye span your God’s infinity?
Hear, mighty universe, thy Maker’s voice!
Let all thy myriad, myriad worlds rejoice!
Lo! I, your Maker, do amid ye come,
To choose my worship and to name my home.
This heard each sphere; and all throughout the sky
Came crowding round. Our earth was rolling by,
When God said to it—Rest! and fast it stood.
With voice like winds through some wide olden wood,
Thus spake the One again: Behold, O Earth!
Thy parent, God! it is I who gave thee birth.
With all my love I did thee once endow;
With all my mercy—and thou hast them now.
But hear my words! thou never lovedst me well,
Nor fearedst my wrath: dreadst thou no longer Hell?
Dream’st thou that guilt shall always mock those fires?
That deathless death which Hell for aye expires?
Should all creation its rebellion raise,
I speak, and this broad universe doth blaze—
Pass like a dew-drop ’neath mine angry rays—
Blaze like the fat in sacrificial flame:
And that burned offering, when I come to claim,
Its scorching, quenchless mass, all, I will pour
Upon thy naked soul:—canst thou endure?
He spake; and, as the fear-fraught words flew past,
Earth fluttered like a dead leaf in their blast.
Am not I God? Answer me! Hope not thou,
Impenitent, to ward my righteous blow.
Yet, come again! my proffered mercy hear!
Rejoice and sing! sweet music in thine ear
And peace I speak: seek but to be forgiven:
Repent! and thou shalt meet thy God in Heaven.
Go! cleanse thy brow from blood, thy heart from crime,
And on thy Saviour call while yet is time!
Now to this universe of pride and sin
I speak, ere yet I call mine angels in.
Draw nigh, ye worlds!—and, lo! their light did seem
Before His eye paled to a pearl’s dull beam.
Attend! said God—o’er all He lift his hand.—
Where will ye set my tent? where shall my temple stand?
And all were dumb. Distracting silence spread
Throughout that host as each were stricken dead.
I made ye. I endowed ye. Ye are mine.
Then trembled out each orb: Thine, God! for ever Thine!
All that ye have, within myself have I;
God, am complete; full inexhaustibly.
I dwell within myself, and ye in me,
Not in yourselves; I have infinity.
The everything in all things is my throne;
Your might is my might, and your wealth mine own:
’Tis by my power and sufferance that ye shine:
I live in light and all your light is mine.
Be dark! said God. Night was. Each glowing sphere
Dulled, Night seemed everything and everywhere,
Save that in utter space a feeble flare
Told that the pits of hell were sunken there.
Shuddered in fear the universe the while,
Till God again embraced it with a smile.
And all things made were glad. Come now and hear,
Ye worlds! said God, the truth I thus make clear:
My words are mercy, wherefore should ye fear?
And straight, obedient to his sacred will,
One great concentrate globe they crowd to fill;
Systems and suns pour forth their glowing urns;
Full in the face of God the glory burns.
Hearken, thou host! thy trembling hope to raise,
I to all Being thus make plain my ways;—
God, the creator, bade creation rise,
And matter came in void like clouds in skies;
Lifeless and cold it spread throughout all space,
And darkness dwelt and frowned upon its face:
Chaos I bade depart this work of mine,
And straight the mighty elements disjoin.
Then light I lit; then order I ordained,
And put the dance of atoms to an end.
Matter I brake, and scattered into globes,
And clad ye each in green and growing robes:
Your sizes, places, forms, I fixed with laws,
And wrought the link between effect and cause.
Then formed I lives for each, which might inherit
Will, reason, form, and power—not deathless spirit.
Then I made spirits, things of Heavenly worth,
Deathless, Divine. Round these, from every earth,
I gathered forms and features fit for love,
Trust, pleasure, power, and all I could approve.
To every spirit I disclosed my name,
My love, my might, and whence all Being came:
To deathless souls I righteously decreed
Accountability for thought, word, deed.
Then every orb complete, along the sky,
In glory, beauty, order, harmony,
I launched. Souls, worlds did every thing possess
Which could a mortal and immortal bless.
To all the hope of happier state was given—
For all I keep one common boundless Heaven.
Ye all have freedom, and ye all do sin,
For ye are creatures: but ye all may win
Life everlasting—everlasting joy,
If ye do but the love of sin destroy:
This only is offence; for sin ye must
Not by my will; but weakness dwells with dust,
Unless ye have sinned ye cannot enter Heaven.
How shall a sinless creature be forgiven?
And by forgiveness only can ye claim
Hope in my mercy, trust upon my name.
I knew that ye would all to sin be given;
But I, even God, have paid your price to Heaven:
And if ye will not journey on that way—
The truth—the life—what do ye merit? say!
Death is the gate of life, and sin, of bliss:
Mark the dread truth! but mourn your deeds amiss.
Cast off your guilt! abandon folly’s path!
Turn to the Lord your God ere hell His wrath!
Turn from your madness, wicked ones, and live!
Take, take the bliss which God alone can give.
God, the Creator, me all beings own—
God, the Redeemer, I will still be known—
God, too, the Judge—the each—the three—the one.
Again the Everlasting cried—Repent!
To bless or curse I am Omnipotent.
And what art thou, created Being? Round
That world of worlds His arm the Almighty wound;
The bright immensity He raised, and pressed,
All trembling, like a babe, unto His breast.
There, in the Father’s bosom rose again,
Of filial love, the universal strain;
Strong and exultant—blissful, pure, sublime,
It rolled, and thrilled, and swelled in notes unknown to time.
Think ye that I, who thus do ye maintain;
Thus always cherish ye, or all were vain—
Ye all would drop into your native void,
If by my hand ye were not held and buoyed:
Think ye that I cannot uphold in Heaven,
In righteous state, the souls I have forgiven?
Is this a weightier task? with God, ’tis one
To guide a sunbeam or create a sun—
To rule ten thousand thousand worlds or none.
Go, worlds! said God, but learn, ere ye depart,
My favoured temple is an humble heart;
Therein to dwell I leave my loftiest skies—
There shall my holy of all holies rise!
He spake; and swiftly, reverent to His will,
Sprang each bright orb on high its sphere to fill.
Glory to God! they chanted as they soared—
Father Almighty! be Thou all-adored.
Thou art the glory—we, Thine universe,
Serve but abroad Thy lustre to disperse.
Unsearchable, and yet to all made known!
The world at once Thy kingdom and Thy throne—
Pity us, God! nor chase us quite away
Before Thy wrath, as night before the day.
In Thee, our God, we live; from Thee we came—
The feeble sparks of Thine eternal flame.
Thy breath from nothing filled us all at first,
And could again as soon the bubble burst.
In Thee, like motes in the sunbeam, we move;
Glow in Thy light, and gladden in Thy love.
And midst this praise, earth was the only one
Sullen remained in that grand union
Of joy and harmony. Word spake she none.

Clara |

Earth only had been chidden.

Festus |

Not alone.
High o’er all height, God gat upon His throne.
Downwards He bent; and, as a grain of sand,
He lifted up our globe. Then from His hand,
As ’twere in pity, bowled the ingrate sphere,
Which rushed like ruin down its dark career.
And high the air’s blue billows rolled and swelled
On many an island world mine eye beheld.

Clara |

And where and what is he, this mighty friend,
Who to thee, human, thus his might doth lend?
Who bore thee harmless, as thou sayst, through space,
And brought thee front before thy Maker’s face?

Festus |

I know not where he is. It is but at times
That he is with me; but he aye sublimes
His visits thus, by lending me his might
O’er things more bright than day, more deep than night.
And he obeys me—whether good or ill
His or my object, he obeys me still.

Clara |

O Festus! I conjure thee to beware
Lest thus the Evil one thy soul ensnare.

Festus |

What! may not a free spirit have preferred
A mortal to his heart—as thou thy bird
Lovest, because it singeth of the sky,
Although it is as far below thy soul
As I ’neath an archangel’s majesty?
God will protect the atom as the whole.

Clara |

Him, then, I pray: the spirit full must share
The truths it feels with God Himself in prayer.
So guide us, God! in all our works and ways,
That heart may feel, hand act, mouth show Thy praise;
Thai when they meet, who love, and when they part,
Each may be high in hope, and pure in heart:
That they who have seen, and they who have but heard
Of Thy great deeds, may both obey Thy word!

Festus |

Unto the wise belongs the sphere of light,
And to the spirit world-compelling might.
Yon sun, now setting in the golden main,
Shall count me his ere next he rise again.
Would that the earth had nothing fair to lure,
Nor being more to answer or endure!
But I foresee, fore-suffer. Bound to earth,
Wrecked in the deeps of Heaven, in Death’s expiring birth!

XXV

Scene—The Sun.

Festus |

Soul of the world, divine Necessity,
Servant of God, and master of all things!
Here, in the Heaven of light’s eternal noon,
First see I all things clear: from end to end
The divine cycle of the soul of man;
How spirit, soul, mind, life, flesh, feeling, mix,
And how, withal they each reciprocate,
As ocean, earth, air, fire and wind; how flow
The streams of feeling, and the cataracts
Of passion; mine and mountain, this of pride,
And that of covetousness. Man I know;
The human universe and the divine
And central fate; know all must be fufilled
Of nature that there is; of sin and strife,
Peace, righteousness, change, self-delusion, self—
Destruction, ere the earth can take new life,
Or man become the minister of God.
The world and man are just reciprocal,
Yet contrary. Spirit invadeth sense
And carries captive Nature. Be this true,
All good is Heaven, and all ill is Hell.
All things are means for greater good. Thou, Sun,
Art just a giant-slave, a god in bonds.
The summit-flower of all created life
Is its unition with Divinity,
In essence, yet existence separate.
High o’er my own existence, here then I
Look down upon the nature and the earth,
Yet mine, whose separate and combined ends
Have still to be evolved. How wide men miss,
While in the lower world of soul and sense,
In aiming even at life-ruling Truth—
Formless as air, simple and one as Death.
If Heaven and all its stars depend on earth,
Then may eternity on time;—not else.
But since now earth is as a crumb of Heaven,
And time an atom of eternity,
Neither depends upon the other, both
One essence being emanant from God,
Whose flowings forth are aye and infinite,
And radiant as the rivers of the skies.
One only truth hath consequence, God’s truth
Inspirited in man. Mere human truth
Or falsehood matters not. The world may act,
Believe, or bless, or curse, as best it lists.
Yet men expend life, solemnizing points
Uncertain as the site of Paradise
And area of Hades. Not the less,
There is no disappointment we endure
One half so great as that we are to ourselves.
We make our hearts the centres of all hopes,
All powers, all rewards, remembering not
That centres are imaginary points.
Imaginary circles only too
Are perfect; therefore, draw life as we may,
Bound as a world, or as an atom round,
And pure as virgin visionary’s dream,
Or perfect faith’s regenerative wave—
It fails to match the true invisible
Whereof we labor. It is come to this.
One state of life with me hath passed away.
Aught henceforth that may matter be of doubt
To me is matter of indifference. I
Love only that is certain. Me no more
The spirits of the bright invisible
Shall throng round as the winds some mountain-top;
Nor watery lightfulness of ghostly eyes,
Belonging heavenly forms informed with light,
Impose their spell of record under pain.
The inspiration quits me—it is gone—
Like a retreating army from the land
Which it hath wasted—the long gleaming mass,
Snakelike, at last hath wound itself away,
And left me weak and wretched. None again
Of all the starry tribes of shining mien—
Swifter than undulations of the light,
A million in a moment, multiform
As atomies of air, shall visit me;
Their word of leave is taken back—henceforth,
Restricted to perfection, earth they quit.
True, albeit, I loved them more than life;
I felt myself made sacred by their touch:—
But they are gone, and there is nought on earth
Left acceptable. Fiery shadows, hence!
I have outbraved ye once. It matters not.
I have left all for one; Truth’s countless rays
For Truth itself; the mean for the supreme,
The dubitable for the throned power.
Yet thus I cannot rest. The mightiest sphere
Is not for man. The elements of mind
And matter are proportioned in all worlds;
The father they and mother of all things.
And earth hath favour over crowds of stars.
I must reseek earth. Still what boots it now,
To plunge in pleasure or to passion bow,
The very lion-honey of the heart
Which dwelleth in corruption? Yet, perchance,
’Twere wisdom to extract it while we may.
The oak, as lily, feels the lightest breeze.
The ineradicable seed is sown
Of love in life, and tide-like ’twill have way
O’er the impalaced prisoner of the breast.
The thirst for power and knowledge still exist,
And meet with dizzy mixture in the brain.
If suffering could expiate offence,
They who have most enjoyed have most atoned,
It may be, humanly;—but it cannot.
Earth-like, the heart must undergo all change
Ere the superior life be formed therein,
The chastity of heart which loves but God.
Life’s sensuous warmth, the spirit’s holy chill,
Time’s week-day work, have yet to be gone through.
The hortus siccus of a Paradise
Is all earth now can boast. To God belongs
The autumn of all nature. But, alas!
Not yet can we o’ercome our nature here,
Would we. If therefore passion strike the heart,
Let it have length of line and plenteous play.
The safety of superior principles
Lies in exhaustion of the lower ones,
However vast or violent. Men and angels
Obey the order of existence. Fate!
Who seeks thee everywhere, will find thee there.

XXVII

Scene—Garden and bower by the sea.

Elissa |

Alone.

Come, Festus, let me think on thee, my love!
And fold the thought of thee unto my soul,
Until it fills it, and is one with it.
Ah! these poor arms are far from where they should be;
And this heart farther still. Mine only love!
Why art thou thus so long away from me?
I have whispered it unto the southern wind
And charged it with my love: why should it not
Carry that love to thee as air bears light?
And thou hast said I was all light to thee.
The stars grow bright together, and for aye,
Lover-like, watch each other; and though apart,
Like us, they fill each other’s eyes with love
And beauty: and mine only fill with tears.
Oh! life is less than nothing without love!
And what is love without the embrace of love?
I would give worlds for one more ere I die.
Festus! come to me. I do think I am dying.
Let me bequeath my life to thee, that so,
In doubling thine, I may live alway with thee.
I know that I am dying. It is my heart
Which makes me live that kills me. But I want
To see him ere I do die. Oh! he will come!
He must know how I love him. It is long—
Long since I saw him: I am ill with waiting.
And I will fancy him coming to me now—
Now he is thinking of me, loving me—
He sees me—flies to me, half out of breath—
His hand is on my arm—he looks on me—
And puts my long locks backwards—God! Thy ban
Lies upon waking dreams. To weep and sleep—
Dream—wake, and find one’s only one hope false—
Is what we can bear, for we do endure it,
And bear with Heaven still. Just one year ago,
I watched that large bright star where it is now:—
Time hath not touched its everlasting lightning,
Nor dimmed the glorious glances of its eye—
Nor passion clouded it—nor any star
Eclipsed—it is the leader still of Heaven.
And I who loved it then can love it now;
But am not what I was, in one degree.
Calm star! who was it named thee Lucifer,
From him who drew the third of Heaven down with him?
Oh! it was but the tradition of thy beauty!
For if the sun hath one part, and the moon one,
Thou hast the third part of the host of Heaven—
Which is its power—which power is its beauty!

Lucifer |

It was no tradition, lady, but of truth!

Elissa |

I thought we parted last to meet no more.

Lucifer |

It was so lady; but it is not so.

Elissa |

Am I to leave, or thou, then?

Lucifer |

Neither, yet.
I mean that thou shouldst fear me and obey.

Elissa |

And who art thou that I should fear and serve?

Lucifer |

I am the morning and the evening star,
The star thou lovest and thy lover too;
I am that star! as once before I told thee,
Though thou wouldst not believe me, but I am
A spirit, and a star—a power—an ill
Which doth outbalance being. Look at me!
Am I not more than mortal in my form?
Millions of years have circled round my brow
Like worlds upon their centres;—still I live;
And age but presses with a halo’s weight.
This single arm hath dashed the light of Heaven;
This one hand dragged the angels from their thrones:—
Am I not worthy to have loved thee, lady?
Thou mortal model of all Heavenliness!
And yet I have abandoned all these spoils,
Cowered my powers, and becalmed my course,
And stooped from the high destruction of the skies
For thee, and for the youth who loveth thee—
And is lost with ye: ye are both, both—lost!
Thou hast but served the purpose of the Fiend.
And thou art but the vessel of the sin
Whose poison hath made drunk a soul to death;
And he hath drunk; and thou art useless now.
And it is for this I come; to bid thee die!

Elissa |

I said that I was dying. God is good.
The Heavens grow darker as they grow the purer:
And both, as we do near them; so, near death,
The soul grows darker and diviner, hourly.
Could I love less I should be happier!
But it is always to that mad extreme,
That death alone appears the fitting finish
To bliss like that my spirit presses for.

Lucifer |

Thy death hall be as gentle as thy life.
I will not hurt thee, for I loved thee once.
And thy sweet love, upon my burning breast,
Fell like a snowflake on a fevered lip.
Thy soul shall pass out of thee like a dream.
One moment more, and thou shalt wake in Heaven!

Elissa |

I ever thought thee to be more than mortal.
And if thou art thus mighty, grant me this!—
Since now we love no more—as friend to friend—
Bring him I love, one moment, ere I die.

Lucifer |

Thou judgest well; I am all but almighty.
And I have stretched my strength unto its limits
To satisfy the heart of him who loves thee:
In proof whereof, did I not give up thee,
Because he loved thee? I have given him all things
Body or spirit could desire or have.
And even at this moment, now he reigns
King of the sun, and monarch of the seven
Orbs that surround him—leaving earth alone—
The earth is in good keeping as it is.
I know that he is hasting hither now;
But may not see thee living.

Elissa |

It is not thou
Who takest life: it is God, whose I shall be!—
And his, with God, whom here my heart deifies.
I glory in his power as in his love.
But I will, will see him while I am alive.
I hear him—he is come—it is he! it is he!

Lucifer |

Die! thou shalt never look on him again.

Elissa |

My love! haste, Festus! I am dying—

Lucifer |

Dead!
A word could kill her. She hath gone to Heaven.

Festus |

Fiend! what is this? Elissa—she is not dead.

Lucifer |

She is. I bade her die, as I had reason.

Festus |

Now do I hate thee and renounce for ever!—
Abhor thee—go!

Lucifer |

Who seeks the other first?
I am gone.

Festus |

Away, Fiend! Leave me! My Elissa!

XXVIII

Scene—A library and balcony—A summer night.

Festus |

Alone.

The last high upward slant of sun on the trees,
Like a dead soldier’s sword upon his pall,
Seems to console earth for the glory gone.
Oh! I could weep to see the day die thus;
The death-bed of a day, how beautiful!
Linger, ye clouds, one moment longer there;
Fan it to slumber with your golden wings!
Like pious prayers ye seem to soothe its end.
It will wake no more till the all-revealing day;
When, like a drop of water, greatened bright
Into a shadow, it shall show itself
With all its little tyrannous things and deeds,
Unhomed and clear. The day hath gone to God—
Straight, like an infant’s spirit, or a mocked
And mourning messenger of grace to man.
Would it had taken me too on its wing!
My end is nigh. Would I might die outright!
And slip the coil without waiting its unwind.
Who that hath lain lonely on a high hill,
In the imperious silence of full noon,
With nothing but the clear dark sky about him,
Like God’s hand laid upon the head of earth—
But hath expected that some natural spirit
Should start out of the universal air—
And gathering his cloudy robe around him,
As one in act to teach mysterious things,
Explain that he must die?—that having got
As high as earth can lift him up—as far
Above that thing, the world, as flesh can mount—
Over the tyrant wind, and the clouded lightning,
And the round rainbow—and that having gained
A loftier and a more mysterious beauty
Of feeling—something like a starry darkness
Seizing the soul—say he must die—and vanish?
Who hath not, at such moments, felt as now
I feel, that to be happy we must die?
And here I rest—above the world and its ways;
The wind, opinion—and the rainbow, beauty—
And the thunder, superstition—I am free
Of all:—save death, what want I to be happy?
And shall I leave no trace, then, of my life?
The soul begetteth shadows of itself
Which do outlive their author: and are more
Substantial than all nature, and the red
Realities of flesh and blood, as echo
Is longer, louder, further than the voice
Of man can thunder, or his ear report.
And oft the world hath Deified its echoes.
A year!—and who shall find them? Can it be
The mind’s works have been deathless—not the mind?
Or will the world’s immortals die with me?—
The sages, and the heroes, and the bards—
Whose verse set to the thunder of the seas,
Seems as immortal as their ceaseless music!
O God! I fain would deem Thou livest not:
And that this world hath sprung up from chance seed,
Unknown to thee; and is not reckoned on.
Hell solves all doubts.—Come to me, Lucifer!

Lucifer |

Lo! I am here: and ever prompt when called for.
How speed thy general pleasures?

Festus |

Bravely! joys
Are bubble-like—what makes them, bursts them, too.
And, like the milky way, there! dim with stars,
The soul that numbers most will shine the less.

Lucifer |

No matter—mind it not!

Festus |

Yet, joys of earth!
That ye should ruin spirits is too hard.
Who can avoid ye? who can say ye nay?
Or take his eyes from off ye? who so chaste?

Lucifer |

They have well-nigh unimmortalized myself.

Festus |

Yet have they nought to sate the pining spirit
Which doth enamour immortality.
No! they are all base, impure, ruinous—
The harlots of the heart. Forgive me, God!
I am getting too forlorn to live—too waste.
Aught that I can or do love, shoots by me,
Like a train upon an iron road. And yet
I need not now reproach mine arm or aim;
For I have winged each pleasure as it flew,
How swift or high soever in its flight.
We cannot live alone. The heart must have
A prop without, or it will fall and break.
But nature’s common joys are common cheats.
As he who sails southwards, beholds, each night,
New constellations rise, all dear, and fair;
So, o’er the waters of the world, as we
Reach the mid zone of life, or go beyond,
Beauty and bounty still beset our course;
New beauties wait upon as every where;
New lights enlighten and new worlds attract.
Bat I have seen and I have done with all.
Friendship hath passed me like a ship at sea;
And I have seen no more of it. I had
A friend with whom, in boyhood, I was wont
To learn, think, laugh, weep, strive, and love, together;
For we were alway rivals in all things—
Together up high springy hills, to trace
A runnel to its birthplace—to pursue
A river—to search, haunt old ruined towers,
And muse in them—to scale the cloud-clad hills
While thunders murmured in our very ear;
To leap the lair of the live cataract,
And pray its foaming pardon for the insult;
To dare the broken tree-bridge across the stream;
To crouch behind the broad white waterfall,
Tongue of the glen, like to a hidden thought—
Dazzled, and deafened, yet the more delighted;
To reach the rock which makes the fall and pool;
There to fee safe, or not to care if not;
To fling the free loot over my native hills,
Which seemed to breathe the bracing breeze we loved
The more it lifted up our loosened locks,
That nought might be between us and the skies;
Or, hand in hand, leap, laughing, with closed eyes,
In Trent’s death-loving deeps; yet was she kind
Ever to us; and bare us buoyant up,
And followed our young strokes, and cheered us on—
Even as an elder sister bending above
A child, to teach it how to order its feet—
As quick we dashed, in reckless rivalry,
To reach, perchance, some long green floating flag—
Just when the sun’s hot lip first touched the stream,
Reddening to be so kissed; and we rejoiced,
As breasting it on we went over depth and death,
Strong in the naked strife of elements,
Toying with danger in as little fear
As with a maiden’s ringlets. And oft, at night,
Bewildered and bewitched by favorite stars,
We would breathe ourselves amid unfooted snows,
For there is poetry where aught is pure;
Or over the still dark heath, leap along, like harts,
Through the broad moonlight; for we felt where’er
We leapt the golden gorse, or lowly ling,
We could not be from home.—That friend is gone.
There’s the whole universe before our souls.
Where shall we meet next? Shall we meet again?
Oh! might it be in some far happy world,
That I might light upon his lonely soul,
Hard by some broad blue stream, where high the hills,
Wood-bearded, sweep to its brink—musing, as wont,
With love-like sadness, upon sacred things;
For much in youth we loved and mused on them.
To say what ought to be to human wills,
And measure mortals sternly; to explore
The bearings of men’s duties and desires;
To note the nature and the laws of mind;
To balance good with evil; and compare
The nature and necessity of each;
To long to see the ends and end of things;
Or, if no end there be, the endless, then,
As suns look into space; these were our joys—
Our hopes—our meditations—our attempts.
And, if I have enjoyed more love than others,
It is but superior suffering, and is more
Than balanced by the loss of one we love.
And love, itself, hath passed. One fond fair girl
Remains; one only, and she loves me still.
But it is not love I feel: it is pore kindness.
How shall I find another like my last?
The golden and the gorgeous loveliness—
A sunset beauty! Ah! I saw it set.
My heart, alas! set with it. I have drained
Life of all love, as doth an iron rod
The Heaven’s of lightning; I have done with it,
And all its waking woes, and dreamed-of joys.
No more shall beauty star the air I live in;
And no more will I wake at dead of night,
And hearken to the roaring of the wind,
As though it came to carry one away—
Claiming for sin. Ah! I am lost forever.
To earn the world’s delights by equal sins.
Seems the great aim of life—the aim succeeds.
Here it is madness, and perdition there.
And, but for thee, I had renounced these joys—
These cursed joys my soul now writhes among,
Like to a half-crushed reptile on a rose:—
Ay, but for thee, I might have now been happy!

Lucifer |

Why charge, why wrong me thus? When first I knew thee,
I deemed it thine ambition to be damned.
Thine every thought, almost, had gone from good,
As far as finite is from infinite;
And then thou wast as near to me as now.
Thou hadst declined in worship, and in wish
To please thy God; nor wouldst thou e’er repent.
What more need I to justify attempt?
Have I shrunk back from granting aught I promised?
Thy love of knowledge—is that satisfied?

Festus |

It is. Yet knowledge is a doubtful boon—
Root of all good and fruit of all that’s bad.
I have caused face to face with elements,
Yea, learned the luminous language of the skies,
And the angelic kindred of high Heaven;
The bright articulations of all spheres—
Impetuous hearted orbs, and mountain-maned,
Aye circling onwards breathless through the air—
And wisest stars which speak themselves in signs
Too sacred to be explicable here;
And now what better am I?—nearer God?
When the void finds a voice mine answer know.

Lucifer |

What better or what worse thou canst not tell.
For, good and evil! Wherein differ they?
Do they not both accrue from the same cause—
As ripeness and decay? Light, light alone
Of hues, how contrary soever, is
The common cause.

Festus |

Distracter of God’s truth!
Shall not His word suffice the living world?

Lucifer |

Thou canst not have lacked joys?

Festus |

We seek them oft
Among our own delusions, pains and follies.

Lucifer |

Hath not care perished from thy heart, as did
The viper flung from the apostle’s hand?

Festus |

Ay; and, like that, all care will cease in fire.
Dark wretched thoughts like ice-isles in a stream,
Choke up my mind and clash;—and to no end.
In spite of all we suffer and enjoy,
There comes this question, over and over again,
Driven into the brain as a pile is driven—
What shall become of us hereafter? what
Is it we shall do? how feel, how be?
And there are times when burning memory flows
In on the mind, that saving it would slay,
As did the lava-floods which choked of yore
The Cyclopean cities—brimming up
Brasslike their mighty moulds. And shall the past
Thus ruinously perfect aye remain;
Or present, past, and coming, all be one,
In natural mystery? Like snow, which lies
Down-wreathed round the lips of some black pit,
Thoughts which obscure the truth accumulate,
And those which solve it in it lose themselves;
And there is no true knowledge till descent,
Nor then till after. What shall make the truth
Visible? Through the smoky glass of sense
The blessed sun would never know himself.
All truth is one. All error is alike.
The shadow of a mountain hath no more
Substance than hath a dead and moss-mailed pine’s;
But only more gigantic impotence.

Lucifer |

Hast thou not had thine every quest?

Festus |

Save one.

Lucifer |

I proffer now the power which thou dost long for.
Say but the word, and thou shalt press a throne
But less than mine—the scarcely less than God’s;—
A throne, at which earth’s puny potentates
May sue for slavedoms—and be satisfied.

Festus |

I have had enough of the infinities:
I am moderate now. I will have the throne of earth.

Lucifer |

Thou shalt. Yet, mind!—with that, the world must end.

Festus |

I can survive.

Lucifer |

Nay, die with it must thou.

Festus |

Why should I die? I am egg-full of life:
And life’s as serious a thing as death.
The world is in its first young quarter yet;
I dare not, cannot credit it shall die.
I will not have it, then.

Lucifer |

It matters not;
I know thou wilt never have ease at heart
Until thou hast thy soul’s whole, fall desire;
Whenever that may happen, all is done.

Festus |

Well, then—be it now! I live but for myself—
The whole world but for me. Friends, loves, and all
I sought, abandon me. It is time to die.
I am yet young; yet have I been deserted,
And wronged, by those whom most I have loved and served.
Sun, moon, and stars! may they all fall on me,
When next I trust another—man or woman.
Earth rivals Hell too often, at the best.
All hearts are stronger for the being hollow.
And that was why mine was no match for theirs.
The pith is out of it now.—Lord of the world!
It will not directly perish?

Lucifer |

Not, perhaps.—
Thou wilt have all fame, while thou livest, now.

Festus |

I care not: fame is folly: for, it is, sure,
Far more to be well known of God than man.
With all my sins I feel that I am God’s.

Lucifer |

Farewell, then, for a time!

Festus |

I am alone.—
Alone? He clings around me like the clouds
Upon a hill. When will the clouds roll off?
When will sun visit me? O! Thou great God!
In whose right hand the elements are atoms—
In whose eye, light and darkness but a wink—
Who, in Thine anger, like a blast of cold,
Dost make the mountains shake like chattering teeth—
Have mercy! Pity me! For it is Thou
Who hast fixed me to this test. Wilt Thou not save?
Forgive me, Father! but I long to die:—
I long to live to Thee, a pure, free mind.
Take again, God! and thou, fair Earth, the form
And spirit which, at first, ye lent me.
Such as they were, I have used them. Let them part.
I weary of this world; and, like the dove,
Urged o’er life’s barren flood, sweep, tired, back
To thee who sent’st me forth. Bear with me, God!
I am not worthy of thy wrath, nor love!—
Oh! that the things which have been were not now
In memory’s resurrection! But the past
Bears in her arms the present and the future;
And what can perish while perdition is?
From the hot, angry, crowding courts of doubt
Within the breast, it is sweet to escape, and soothe
The soul in looking upon natural beauty.
Oh! earth, like man her son, is half divine.
There is not a leaf within this quiet spot,
But which I seem to know; should miss, if gone.
I could run over its features, hour by hour.
The quaintly figured beds—the various flowers—
The mazy paths all cunningly converged—
The black yew hedge, like a beleaguering host,
Round some fair garden province—here and there,
The cloud-like laurel clumps sleep, soft and fast,
Pillowed by their own shadows—and beyond,
The ripe and ruddy fruitage—the sharp firs’
Fringe, like an eyelash, on the faint-blue west—
The white owl, wheeling from the grey old church—
Its age-peeled pinnacles; and tufted top—
The oaks, which spread their broad arms in the blast,
And bid storms come, and welcome; there they stand,
To whom a summer passes like a smile:—
And the proud peacock towers himself there and screams,
Ruffling the imperial purples of his neck.
O’er all, the giant poplars, which maintain
Equality with clouds half way up Heaven;
Which whisper with the winds none else can see,
And how to angels as they wing by them;—
The lonely, bowery, woodland view before—
And, making all more beautiful, thou, sweet moon,
Leading slow pomp, as triumphing o’er Heaven!
High riding in thy loveless, deathless brightness,
And in thy cold, unconquerable beauty,
As though there were nothing worthy in the world
Even to lie below thee, face to God.
And Night, in her own name, and God’s again,
Hath dipped the earth in dew;—and there she lies,
Even like a heart all trembling with delight,
Till passion murder power to speak—so mute.
Young maiden moon! just looming into light—
I would that aspect never might be changed;
Nor that fine form, so spirit-like, be spoiled
With fuller light. Oh! keep that brilliant shape;
Keep the delicious honor of thy youth,
Sweet sister of the sun, more beauteous thou
Than he sublime. Shine on, nor dread decay.
It may take meaner things; but thy bright look,
Smiling away an immortality,
Assures it us—nay, it seems, half, to give.
Earth may decease. God will not part with thee,
Fair ark of light, and every blessedness!
Yes, earth, this earth, may foul the face of life,
Like some swart mole on beauty’s breast—or dead,
Stiff, mangled reptile, some clear well—while thou
Shalt shine, aye brilliant, on creation’s corse,
Like to a diamond on a dead man’s hand;
Whence God shall pluck thee to His breast, or bid
Beam ’mid His lightning locks. What are earth’s joys
To watching thee, tending thy bright flock over
The fields of Heaven? Thy light misleadeth not,
Though eyes which image Heaven oft lure to Hell;—
Thy smile betrayeth not—though sweet as that
Which wins and damns. Mother, and maid of light!
That, like a God, redeems the world to Heaven—
Making us one with thee, and with the sun,
And with the stars in glory—lovely moon!
I am immortal as thyself; and we
Shall look upon each other yet, in Heaven,
Often—but never, never more on earth.
Am I to die so soon? This death—the thought
Comes oh my heart as through a burning glass.
I cannot bend mine eyes to earth, but thence
It riseth, spectre-like, to mock—nor towards
The west, where sunset is, whose long bright pomp
Makes men in love with change—but there it lowers
Eve’s last, still lingering, darkening, cloud; and on
The escutcheon of the morn, it is there—it is there!
But fears will come upon the bravest mind,
Like the white moon upon the crimson west.
I have attractions for all miseries:
And every course of thought, within my heart,
Leaves a new layer of woe. But it must end.
It will all be one, hereafter. Let it be!
My bosom, like the grave, holds all quenched passions.
It is not that I have not found what I sought—
But, that the world—tush! I shall see it die.
I hate, and shall outlive the hypocrite.
Stealthily, slowly, like the polar sun,
Who peeps by fits above the air-walled world—
The heavenly fief, he knows and feels his own,
My heart o’erlooks the Paradise of life
Which it hath lost, in cold, reluctant joy.
I live and see all beauteous things about me,
But feel no nature prompting from within
To meet and profit by them. I am like
That fabled forest of the Apennine,
Which leafless lives; whereto the spring’s bright showers,
Summer’s heat breathless, autumn’s fruitful juice,
Nothing avail;—nor winter’s killing cold.
Yet have I done, said, thought, in time now past,
What, rather than remember, I would die,
Or do again. It is the thinking on’t,
And the repentance, maddens. I have thought
Upon such things so long and grievously,
My lip have grown like to a cliff-chafed sea,
Pale with a tidal passion; and my soul,
Once high and bright and self-sustained as Heaven,
Unsettled now for life or death, feels like
The grey gull balanced on her bowlike wings,
Between two black waves seeking where to dive.
Long we live, thinking nothing of our fate,
For in the morn of life we mark it not—
It falls behind; but as our day goes down
We catch it lengthening with a giant’s stride,
And ushering us unto the feet of night.
Dark thoughts, like spots upon the sun, revolve
In troops fox days together round my soul,
Disfiguring and dimming. Death! oh death!
The past, the present, and the future, like
The dog three-headed, by the gates of woe
Sitting, seem ready to devour me each.
I dare not look on them. I dare not think.
The very best deeds I have ever done
Seem worthy reprobation, have to be
Repented of. But have I done aught good?
Oh that my soul were calmer! Grant me, God!
Thy peace; that added, I can smile and die.
Thy Spirit only is reality:
All things beside are folly, falsehood, shame.

XXIX

Scene—Elsewhere.

Festus |

Alone.

I feel as if I could devour the days
Till the time came when I shall gain mine end;
God shall have made me ruler, and all worlds
Signed the sublime recognizance. Till then—
Even as a boat lies rocking on the beach,
Waiting the one white wave to float it free,
Wait I the great event;—too great it seems.
Yet, Lord, thou knowest that the power I seek
Is but for others’ good and Thine own glory,
And the desire for it inspired by Thee.
So use me as I use it. Thou hast passed
Thy word that such I shall enjoy, and then
My mission is accomplished in this world.
I go unto another, where all souls
Begin again, or take, up life from where
Death broke it at. I cannot think there will be
Like disproportion there between our powers
And will, as here; if not, I shall be happy.
I feel no bounds. I cannot think but thought
On thought springs up, illimitably, round,
As a great forest sows itself; but here
There is nor ground nor light enough to live.
Could I, I would be every where at once,
Like the sea, for I feel as if I could
Spread out my spirit o’er the endless world,
And act at all points:—I am bound to one.
I must be here, and there, and everywhere,
Or I am nowhere. Sense, flesh, fueling, fail
Before the feet of the imperious mind,
To which they are but as the dust she treads—
Windlike treads o’er, uplifts and leaves behind.
How mind will act with body glorified
And spiritualized, and senses fined,
And pointed brilliantwise, we know not. Here
Even, it may be wrong in us to deem
The senses degradations, otherwise
Than as fine steps, whereby the Queenly soul
Comes down from her bright throne to view the mass
She hath dominion over, and the things
Of her inheritance; and reascends,
With an indignant fiery purity,
Not to be touched, her seat. The visible world,
Whereby God maketh Nature known to us,
Is not derogatory to Himself
As the pure Spirit Infinite. A world
Is but, perhaps, a sense of God’s, by which
He may explain His nature, and receive
Fit pleasure. But the hour is hard at hand,
When Time’s grey wing shall winnow all away,
The atoms of the earth, the stars of Heaven;
When the created and Creator mind
Shall know each other, worlds and bodies both
Put off for aye; man and his Maker meet
Where all, who through the universe do well,
Embrace their heart’s desire; what things they will,
And whom remember; live, too, where they list;
And with the beings they love best, and God,
Inherit and inhabit boundless bliss.
Hear me, all-favouring God! my latest prayer;
Thou unto whom all nations of the world
Lift up their hearts, like grass-blades to the sun;
Thou who hast all things and hast need of nought;
Thou who hast given me Earth and all it holds,
Give me, from out Thy garner stored with good,
Some sign, Lord! while I live, in proof to earth
My prayers are with Thee; that they rend the clouds,
And, rising through the sightless dark of space,
Reach to Thy central throne. Oh! let me feel,
What was my constant dream in my young years,
And is in all my better moments now—
My hope, my faith, my nature’s sum and end,
Oneness with Thee and Heaven. Lord! make me sure
My soul already is in unison
With the triumphant. Ah! I surely hear
The voices of the spirits of the saints,
And witnesses to the Redeeming Truth;
Not, as of old, in scanty scattered strains,
Breathed from the caves of earth and cells of cities—
Nor as the voice of martyr choked with fire—
But in one solemn Heaven-pervading hymn
Of happiness impregnable, as when
From the bright walls of the Son’s city they
Looked on the war of Hell, host upon host,
Foiled by God’s single sword before their gates
Of perfect pearl;—nearer and nearer now!
This is the sign, O God! which Thou hast given,
And I will praise Thee through Eternity.

The Saints |

From Heaven.

Call all who love Thee, Lord, to Thee!
Thou knowest how they long
To leve these broken lays, and aid
In Heaven’s unceasing song;
How they long, Lord, to go to Thee,
And hail Thee with their eyes—
Thee in Thy blessedness, and all
The nations of the skies;

All who have loved Thee and done well,
Of every age, creed, clime,
The boat of saved ones from the ends
And all the worlds of time:
The wise in matter and in mind,
The soldier, sage, and priest,
King, prophet, hero, saint, and bard,
The greatest soul and least;

The old and young and very babe,
The maiden and the youth,
All re-born angels of one age—
The age of Heaven and truth;
The rich, the poor, the good, the bad,
Redeemed, alike, from sin;
Lord! close the book of time, and let
Eternity begin.

Festus |

Will ye away, ye blessed ones? To God
I then commend ye, and my soul with yours.
And midst the light in which ye live, oh! mind
Of all the sunless days and starless nights
Which myriads pass on earth, and pray for them!
Oh! pray for those who in the world’s dark womb
Are bound, Who know not yet their Father, God!—
Lord of all earth, all worlds, all Heaven! lift up
My spirit to Thy glory! Let me share
The comfort of Thy love, and while ordained
To the great task I have to go through, let
No more misgivings, fears, nor mortal doubts,
With the cold dew of darkness chill the soul
Which Thou hast hallowed with Thy love, and which,
Like molten gold within its mould, hath made
The thing that holds it precious;—or if, Lord!
For Thine own purpose, Thou wilt suffer such,
May they pass quick and perish tracelessly;
So, too, all thoughts of earth and pangs of death
May I o’ercome at last, and with Thy chosen,
Seraphs and saints, and all-possessing souls,
Which minister unto the universe,
Enthroned in spirit and intensest bliss,
Succeed to Heaven for ever.

Guardian Angel |

Mortal, hear!
The soul once saved shall never cease from bliss,
Nor God lose that He buyeth with His blood.
She doth not sin. The deeds which look like sin,
The flesh and the false world, are all to her
Hallowed and glorified. The world is changed.
She hath a resurrection unto God
While in the flesh, before the final one,
And is with God. Her state shall never fail.
Even the molten granite which hath split
Mountains, and lieth now like curdled blood
In marble veins, shall flow again when comes
The heat which is to end all; when the air
Is as a ravening fire, and what at first
Produced, at last consumeth; but the soul
Redeemed is dear to God as His own throne,
And shall no sooner perish. Hearken, man!
Wilt thou distrust God? Doubt on doubt no more.
Prepare thee for the power and lot sublime
Whereto the Lord hath called thee. He hath heard
The prayers with which thou hast entreated Him,
And bids me tell thee, shrink not, doubt not. He
Will comfort and uphold thee at the end;
For after God the Chooser, God the Slain,
Cometh the God of Comfort to the heart,
Whose action and effect is ministrant
For ever after—consummating all.

Festus |

I fear, I fear this miracle of Death
Is something terrible. But go to God,
Thou angel, and declare that I repent
Of all misdeeds; that but for His own grace
I should repent of my whole life; that on
That grace, which now hath sanctified the whole,
I trust for all the rest of it, and then
For ever; that I am prepared to act
And suffer as He bids, and in all things
To do His will rejoicing.

Angel |

It is done.

Festus |

Oh! I repent me of a thousand sins,
In number as the breaths which I have breathed.
Am I forgiven?

Angel |

Child of God, thou art.
It is God prompts, inspires, and answers prayer;
Not sin, nor yet repentance, which avails:
And none can truly worship but who have
The earnest of their glory from on high—
God’s nature in them. The world cannot worship.
And whether the lip speak, or in inspired
Silence we clasp our hearts as a shut book
Of song unsung, the silence and the speech
Is each His; and as coming from and going
To Him, is worthy of Him and His Love.
Prayer is the spirit speaking truth to Truth;
The expiration of the thing inspired.
I go. Thy God is with thee. We shall meet
Again in Heaven, no more to part

Festus |

Thou art gone!
’Tis sweet to feel we are encircled here
By breath of angels as the stars by Heaven;
And the soul’s own relations, all divine,
As kind as even those of blood;—and thus
While friends and kin, like Saturn’s double rings,
Cheer us along our orbit, we may feel
We are not lone in life, but that earth’s part
Of Heaven and all things. Praise we, therefore God!
O all ye angels, pray and praise with us!—

XXX

Scene—A gathering of kings and peoples.

Festus |

Throned.

Princes and Peoples! Powers once, of earth!
It suits not that I point to ye the path
By which I reached this sole supreme domain—
This mountain of all mortal might. Enough
That I am monarch of the world—the world.
Let all acknowledge loyally my laws,
And love me as I them love! It will be best.
No rise against me can stand. I rule of God;
And am God’s sceptre here. Think not the world
Is greater than my might—less than my love—
Or that it stretcheth further than mine arm!
Kings! ye are Kings no longer. Cast your crowns
Here—for my footstool. Every power is mine.
Nobles! be first in honour. Ye, too, lose
Your place, in place: retrieve yourselves, in good.
Peoples! be mighty in obedience.
Let each one labour for the common weal.
Be every man a people in his mind.
Kings—nobles—nations! love me and obey.
I need no aid—no arms. Burn books—break swords!
The world shall rest, and moss itself with peace.
Stand forth, and speak, sole servant of my throne!
If aught thou hast to settle and explain—
Or send away these nations to their homes.

Lucifer |

Ye mighty once—ye many weak, give ear!
I and my god—for god he sure must be,
In human form, who sitteth there enthroned—
For readier rule, and for the good of all,
Have cast again the dynasties of earth
According to the courses of the air:—
Therefore, from east, and west, and north, and south,
Four element-like ministers shall bend
Before his feet. Hearken, thou unkinged crowd!
Ye have not sought the good of those ye governed.
The people only for the people care.
Ye seem to have thought earth but a ball for kings
To play with: rolling the royal bauble, empire,
Now east—now west. Your hour and power is past.
Ye are the very vainest of mankind,
As loftiest things weigh lightest. Ye are gone!
Nations, away with them! Nor do ye boast!
Ye find that power means not good, not bliss.
But ye would wed delusion:—now, ye know her.
And she is yours for life—and death—and judgment.
There is no power, nor majesty, save his:
His is the kingdom of the world and glory.
His throne is founded centre-deep by Heaven;
And the whole earth doth bless him. Unto all
He hath laid out one perfect level law—
His will. For as the people cannot rule
Themselves, so neither may a crowd of kings:
And hence hath been the evil of the earth—
Now ceased for ever. War will be no more.
His is the sway of social sovereign peace:
His tyranny is love and good to all:—
His is the vice-royed, vouched-safe sway of God:—
And he will turn the world, at will; as light
Turneth the world round. Greet your Lord, and go!
Depart, ye nations!

Festus |

Hark! thou fiend! dost hear?

Lucifer |

Ay! it is the death groan of the sons of men—
Thy subjects—King!

Festus |

Why hadst thou this so soon?

Lucifer |

It is God who brings it all about—not I.

Festus |

I am not ready—and—it shall not be!

Lucifer |

I cannot help it, monarch! and—it is!
Hast not had time for good!

Festus |

One day—perchance.

Lucifer |

Then hold that day as an eternity.

Festus |

All around me die. The earth is one great death-bed.

Clara |

Oh! save me, Festus! I have fled to thee,
Through all the countless nations of yon dead—
For well I knew it was thou who sattest there,
To die with thee, if that thou art not Death:
And, if thou wert, I would not shrink from thee.
I am thine own, own Clara!

Festus |

Thou art safe!
Here in the holy chancel of my hearts—
The heavenly end of this our fleshly fane,
I hold thee to communion. Rest thee safe!

Clara |

Men thought I was an angel, as I passed;
And caught up at my feet—but I ’scaped all.
I knew—I was sure, that I should die by thee.
The heart is a true oracle—I knew it!

Festus |

Then there is faith among these mortals yet.
Thy beauty cometh first, and goeth last—
Willow-like. Welcome!

Clara |

Oh! I am so happy!

Festus |

I speak of thee as of the dead; the dead
Are alway faithful.

Clara |

I will stay with thee—
Though angels beckon—may I? Let me, love!
I dare not—cannot, take mine eyes from thee,
For fear of looking on the dead. Dear Festus!

Festus |

Thou art the only one hast answered me,
Love to love—life to life.

Clara |

Oh! I am dying!
Give me one kiss—the kiss of life and death—
The only taste of earth I will take to Heaven.
Here! let me die, die in it. Dies.

Festus |

Last and best!
Now am I one, again. Oh! memory runs
To madness, like a river to the sea.
Happy as Heaven have I been with thee, love!
Thine innocent heart hath passed through a pure life,
Like a white dove, wing-sunned through the blue sky.
A better heart God never saved in Heaven.
She died as all the good die—blessing—hoping.
There are some hearts, aloe-like, flower once, and die:
And hers was of them. Ah! all life hath ceased.
And silence reads the dead world’s burial tale.
And Death sits quivering, there, and watering,
His great gaunt jaw at me. When must I die?

Lucifer |

Say! dost thou feel to be mortal, or immortal?

Festus |

Away!—and let me die alone.

Lucifer |

I go:
And I will come again: but spare thee, now,
One hour to think—Goes.

Festus |

On all things. God, my God!
One hour to sum a life’s iniquities!
One hour to fit me for eternity—
To make me up for judgment and for God!
Only one hour to curse thee! Nay, for that,
There may be endless hours. God! I despair—
And I am dying. Let me hold my breath!
I know not if I ever may draw another.
I feel Death blowing hard at the lamp of life.
My heart feels filling like a sinking boat;
It will soon be down—down. What will come of me?
It is as I always wished it;—I shall die
In darkness, and in silence, and alone.
Even my last wish is petted. God! I thank Thee;
It is the earnest of Thy coming—what?
Forgiveness? Let it be so: for I know not
What I have done to merit endless pain.
Is pleasure crime? Forbid it, God of bliss!
Who spurn at this world’s pleasures, lie to God;
And show they are not worthy of the next.
What are Thy joys we know not—nor can we
Come near Thee, in Thy power, nor truth, nor justice;
Ute nearest point wherein we come towards Thee,
Is loving—making love—and being happy.
Thou wilt not chronicle our sandlike sins;
For sin is small, and mean, and barren. Good,
Only, is great, and generous, and fruitful.
Number the mountains, not the sands, O God!
God will not look as we do on our deeds;
Nor yet as others. If He more condemn,
Shall He not more approve? A few fair deeds
Bedeck my life, like gilded cherubs on
A tomb, beneath which lie dust, decay, and darkness.
But each is better than the other thinks.
Thank God! man is not to be judged by man:—
Or, man by man, the world would damn itself.
What do I see? It is the dead. They rise
In clouds! and clouds come sweeping from all sides.
Upwards to God: and now they are all gone—
Gone, in a moment, to eternity.
But there is something near me.

Spirit |

It is I.

Festus |

Go on! I follow, when it is my time.
There is no shadow on the face of life:
It is the noon of fate. Why may not I die?
Methinks I shall have yet to slay myself.
I am calm now. Can this be the same heart
Which, when it did sleep, slept from dizziness,
And pure rapidity of passion, like
The centre circlet of the whirlpool’s wheel?
The earth is breaking up; all things are thawing.
River and mountain melt into their atoms;
A little time, and atoms will be all.
The sea boils; and the mountains rise and sink
Like marble bubbles, bursting into death.
O thou hereafter! on whose shore I stand—
Waiting each toppling moment to engulf me—
What am I? Say, thou Present!—say, thou Past!
Ye three wise children of Eternity!
A life?—a death?—and an immortal?—all?
Is this the threefold mystery of man?
The lower, darker Trinity of earth?
It is vain to ask. Nought answers me—not God.
The air grows thick and dark. The sky comes down.
The sun draws round him streaky clouds, like God
Gleaning up wrath. Hope hath leapt off my heart,
And overturned it. I am bound to die.
God, why wilt Thou not save? The great round world
Hath wasted to a column beneath my feet.
I will hurl me off it, then; and search the depth
Of space, in this one infinite plunge!—Farewell,
To earth, and Heaven, and God! Doom! spread thy lap!
I come—I come!

God |

Forbear!

Festus |

I am God’s!

God |

Man, die!

XXXII

Scene—The Millennial Earth.

Saints and Angels conversing; Festus.
Angel |

The Earth is all one Eden. Pity, sure,
That it should ever end.

Saint |

I say not so;
Although I have a thousand plans in hand,
Some interwoven with the farthest stars—
Each one of which might ask a year of years
To perfect.

Angel |

True; our Maker knoweth best
What thought or deed may best belong to time
Or to eternity.

Saint |

All prophecy
Hath said the earth shall cease, and that right soon.

Festus |

’Tis like enough. Beauty’s akin to Death.

Angel |

Behold, our sister Graces of the skies,
Faith, Hope, and Love, descend! Methinks of late
Ye chiefly dwell on earth.

Love |

Where lives and reigns
The Son of God, there are we ever seen,
Successive, as the seasons to the sun.

Saints |

Well are ye known and welcome in all worlds.
Wherever lofty thought or godly deed
Is lodged or compassed, there your blessings rest.

Hope |

How sweet, how sacred now, this earth of man’s!
The prelude of a yet sublimer bliss!—
I marked it from the first, while yet it lay
Lightless and stirless; ere the forming fire
Was kindled in its bosom, or the land
Lift its Volcanic breastwork up from sea.
The deluge and idolatries of men
I viewed, though shuddering, and with faltering eye,
E’en to the incarnation of Heaven’s Lord,
And dawning of His faith; that faith which was
An infant and anon a giant; was
A star, and grew a Heaven-fulfilling sun;
Which was an outcast, and became, ere long,
A dweller in all palaces; which hid
Its head in dens of deserts, and sat throned,
After, in richest temples high as hills;
Which was poured out in mortal blood, and rose
Li an immortal spirit; as a slave
Was sold for gold and prostrated to power;—
And now that lowly bondmaid is a Queen;
And lo! she is beloved in earth and Heaven;
And lieth in the bosom of her Lord,
The Bride of the all-worshipped, one with God.

Love |

We even of divinest origin
In infinite progression view all worlds;
And we are happy.

Faith |

The dead sleep as yet;
But their time cometh, and the bonds of death
Already slacken round the living soul;
The mortal sleep of ages, which began
When Time sank down into his slumberous west,
Thins even now o’er the reviving eyes
Gathering their Heaven-lent light, no more to wane
In woe or age; never be quenched in tears
Like a star in the sea. ’Tis as I ever knew;
My life is to receive and to believe
The Word and words of God.

Love |

I, who am Love
And Grace and Charity, rejoice with you;
Whither ye wend I with ye; whether here,
Or on the utmost rim of Light’s broad reign—
The least and last of stars which even seems
To tremble at its insignificance
In presence of Infinity; where yet
No angel’s wing hath waved, nor foot of fiend
Left its hot imprint;—still, in all do we
Find fit delight and honour, as now here.
Now earth and Heaven hold commune, day and night;
There’s not a wind but bears upon its wing
The messages of God; and not a star
But knows the bliss of earth.

Festus |

The earth hath God
Remade, and all its elements refined,
Fit for sublimer Being. Flesh hath passed
Its fiery baptism, and come forth clear
As crystal gold: all that of vile or mean
Pertained to it hath perished atomless.
Earth, like a diamond, basks in her own free light;
Unfed, unaided, unrequiring aught.
All now is purity and power and peace.
The first-born of creation, they who hail
Archangels as their brethren, mountainlike
Reign o’er the plains of men, converting all;
Reaping the fields of immortality,
Each one his sheaf, for Him the Harvest-Lord,
To whom belongs earth’s whole estate and life
And every world’s.

Angel |

And He shall gamer all.
The awful tribes which have in Hades dwelt,
Past count of time, await their rising. God’s
Great day, the sabbath of the world’s long week,
Is at high noon; and Christ hath yet to come
To judge and save the living and the dead.

Saint |

The shadows of Eternity o’ercast
Already Time’s bright towers. The Heavens shall come
Down like a cloud upon a hill, and sweep
Their spirit over earth, and the whole face
And form of things shall be dissolved and change.
Nothing shall be but essence, perfect, pure,
And void of every attribute but God’s.
This even is too gross for that which is
To come. The holy have both earth and Heaven.

Festus |

Nor pain, nor toil of mind or frame, nor doubt,
Nor discontent, nor enmity to God,
Disturb the steady joy the spirit feels;
Nor element can torture, nor time tire;
Nor sea nor mountain make or bar or fear;
Sickness and woe and death are things gone by;
Destroyed with the destruction of the world:—
Shadows of things which have been, never more
To waste the world’s bright hours, nor grate the heart
Of mighty man; now fit for thrones and wings;
Ruler of worlds, main minister of Heaven,
Inheritor of all the prophecies
Of God fore-uttered through the tongues of Time,
Ages of ages. Evil is no more.

Archangel |

And does earth satisfy thee now?

Festus |

As earth.
There is a brighter, loftier life for man
Even yet, the very union with God.

Archangel |

God works by means. Between the two extremes
Of earth and Heaven there lies a mediate state—
A pause between the lightning lapse of life
And following thunders of eternity;—
Between eternity and time a lapse,
To soul unconscious, though agelasting, where
Spirit is tempered to its final fate;
When every interfulgeht conscious state
Within or between worlds, repose or bliss,
Divested, man shall, mix with Deity,
And the Eternal and Immortal make
One Being. As in earth’s first paradise
God’s Spirit walked with man, and commune made
With him, so in the second, after death,
Man’s spirit walks with God in an elect
Existence, and a vigil of the great,
The holy day which is to break in Heaven.
Thither the Lord of Life went, in the hour
That Hell by Earth revenged itself on Heaven,
With one soul penitent accompanied;—
Nor long remained He there, yet long enough
To cheer earth’s faithful, who received Him then
Tn silent unknown blessedness of soul,
With time-outwearing hope that yet in Him
They should partake the Godhood of His love.
And with Him rose then, in prophetic proof
Of His Divinity, many a deathless ghost,
Triumphant o’er that blind revenge which wrought,
Hell! thy destruction—thy salvation, Earth!

Festus |

That such will be, the just well know; and all
Earth’s great events and changes tend thereto;
Its fiery dissolution in the past,
And supernatural recommencement now
Under the universal creed of Christ.
The chosen and the world-redeemed partake
His personal and spiritual reign.

Archangel |

And this shall last, till, like the setting sun
Deserting earth, He shall retire to Heaven,
With all His captive victors in His train,
Triumphant, and translated evermore
Into the hierarchal skies. Wilt see,
While yet time is, earth’s shadowy world within—
The inward living death she bears about
Her heart, hath ever borne—and, augur-like,
Explore the ominous bowels of the earth?
To me are given the secrets of the centre,
The keys of earth, to lock and to unlock,
Coffer-like. I, it was who seized and bound,
At His behest who wills and it is done—
Even on their thrones, the mighty thou wilt see.

Festus |

Angel of Heaven! I would view these things.

Archangel |

Nor these alone, but other wonders yet.
The valley where Death’s dark wings brooded o’er,
A God-offending night, unvisited
By sun or star, where but the fatuous fire
Of man’s weak judgment wandered, till God’s Son
Laid o’er the black abyss a bridge of light,
And married earth to the mainland of Heaven:—
This shalt thou see, Death’s grave; and over him,
And over it, that monument of light,
Enlightening earth. The gods and fiends of old,
And all the fictions of the heart of man,
Imagined of the future past for aye,
Thou shalt inspect. Behold this mountain! We
Must pass through it; for under lie the gates
Of the invisible regions whereunto
We tend, for a brief season.

Festus |

On then!

Archangel |

Bare
Thy marble breast, O mountain, to its depths!
An angel and a man divine demand
A way through these foundations.

Festus |

And the rocks
Open like mists before thee.

Archangel |

Follow me!

XXXIII

Scene—Hades.

Archangel, Festus, Death, Lucifer.
Festus |

Almighty God! sustain me. This is Death;—
And this—I knew not, angel! he was here—
Is Lucifer—the fallen, like a bolt
Of thunder forged in intramundane air,
Self-buried in the centre. Lucifer!
Wake from thy sealike sleep; in peace or wrath,
Rouse from thine age-long trance; arise and see;
The representatives of earth and Heaven
Stand by thee. As for me, I blame no more
The part thou tookest in my mortal life;
’Tis gone—nor spurn thee for delusions dead.
The blood that hath been spilled is sunk in earth,
And run into the rivers, and dried up
Into the air;—and there’s an end of it.
What good hath come of it alone I bear
At heart. And we have both offended God.
Let me, though not in nature to forget,
Forgive, what every one hath sometime felt—
The Devil’s burning gripe upon his heart.
I see thee with compassion, half with hope.

Lucifer |

Mortal! I bow to thee, arid would do to
The least and lowest spirit God hath made:
But still the curse that I am cursed with
Outlasts the elements—outlives all time.

Festus |

All curses cease with time; all ill, all woe.
Blessings star forth for ever; but a curse
Is like a cloud—it passes.

Lucifer |

’Twas by him—
Yon angel, only not almighty, there!
As with a chain of mountains I was bound
And hurled into this unformed nebulous life;
Stripped of all might when mightiest, struck down
While triumphing the loftiest—enslaved
When most a monarch o’er both earth and hell,
And made a shadow among shadows here.
It recks not. Let the impenetrable soul
Be ground as through a mill, I only know
In action or inaction equal woe—
Suffering, doing, being, one extreme.
Pass on! we meet again!

Festus |

And when we do,
May God forgive, as I!—

Archangel |

Behold there, Death!
Throned on his tomb—entombed in his throne;
Just as he ceased he rests for aye—his scythe,
Still wet out of its bloody swathe, one hand
Tottering sustains; the other strikes the cold
Drops from his bony brow: his mouldy breath
Tainteth all air.

Festus |

I dread him now no more,
Not hate. He is a vanquished enemy.

Archangel |

Listen! he speaks.

Death |

To you, ye sons of God,
My latest words I utter. Unto him
Who ever lives, and hath for aye destroyed
Me and my reign, give ye this crown usurped,
And lay it at His feet; and this dulled dart
Which was my sceptre. To the conqueror
Belong these trophies. All the progeny
Of time will soon cease. Lo! the end’s at hand.

Archangel |

Thus shall it be, O Death! and thus it is.

Festus |

And who are these gigantic awful shades
Which fill the midst—the present of the place?

Archangel |

These are the mighty nothings man of old
Made; the dread unrealities by whom
He swore, to whom he prayed, and at whose shrines
He sacrificed a thousand times a day:—
His brother falsehoods these, men like himself,
Which mere imagination changed to gods,
Some for their good deeds, others for their bad:
Bel, Odin, Bramh and Zeus, the Lords of death
And fire, and judgment, waiting here their death
And fiery judgment—Time and Titan—war—
Beauty, and strength, and Light, and the long roll
Of creatural powers and passions Deified;—
Who gave their names to stars which still roam round
The skies, all worshipless, even from climes
Where their own altars once topped every hill.

Jove |

Before the Christian cross and Muslim mosque
My marble fanes have fallen, and my shrines
Shrunk like a withered hand ages ago.
But now all signs and sacred domes for gods
To dwell in are extinct. The world is all
One Temple of the Truth.

Bramh |

The ages feigned
That made Time groan to think how old he was,
And Deities in millions are no more.
Ageless eternity and God the sole,
The royalty of Heaven, is at hand.

Boodh |

All things that are shall nothing be at last,
Save what’s resolvable in Deity.

Festus |

And all these lesser shades, which move like moons,
Half-darkened by the greater—half-illumed—
Are priests and prophets of the mightier ones?

Archangel |

They are;—and further round thine eye can mark,
The myriads of adorers of each god,
Confused and prostrate, as their souls awake
To the demoniac madness of their creeds.
Behold! they kneel to those they hailed on earth
As makers—as omnipotent—eterne—
And cry for help, for comfort; none have they
To give to others or themselves. The false,
The base, the brutish Deities give way,
And all their sacred follies in their train,
Before the earthquake truth, engulphing all.
Woe to the false gods, woe! to prophet, priest,
And worshipper, all woe!

Festus |

Hark! round the earth
Each soul hath found a tongue and uttereth woe.
Lo! from their thrones the man-made gods descend,
And rend their robes and trample on their crowns,
And hurl away their sceptres. Woe to all
The gods and idols of the heart of man!
Their sun is set for ever in the night
Which was ere Light was. Surely it is more
To be true man or woman than false god
And falser prophet. God alone the true,
The God of Heaven, shall be witnessed to
And worshipped.

Archangel |

Witnessed, worshipped, too,
By all: the faithful and the faithless—saint
And sinner.

Festus |

Lo! the nations of the dead,
Which do outnumber all earth races, rise,
And high in sumless myriads over head
Sweep past us in a cloud, as ’twere the skirts
Of the Eternal passing.

A Voice |

Souls, arise
To deathless life!

Archangel |

’Tis God speaks. Let us hence.
The general judgment is in hand—God’s hand.
The souls of those whom God loves circle us.
For thee, thy lot thou knowest. As a seed
Buried in earth doth multiply itself
Full fifty fold, so will thy nature when
Changed, it lifts head in the air divine of Heaven.

Festus |

Out of the depths of earth and the world’s womb
Thine unborn angels seek thee, God, all Love!
Now is Thine hour for which all hours were made,
All life created, all things else ordained;
Be it the hour of mercy, Lord! to all,
For Thy Son’s sake, who, for the sake of man,
Came down from Heaven into the pit of earth,
And lived as one of us and died;—He died
The death of all at once of every age;
The world’s accumulated weight of woe,
From its first life unto its last, which none
But the Omnipotent could bear—He bore;
And all for us. God became man that man
Might become God. Oh, favour infinite!
Now reap the righteous, righteous but in Him
Any, their guerdon. Evil to repay
With good was Christs command, and earth with Heaven
Is thus the great example of His word.
Enough for sinners this, for all which live.
Do Thou, Lord! be with us. In Thee we live;
Our treasure, trust and triumph is in Thee.
Behold the day of our salvation come
Unto the countless all Thou hast redeemed!
The ages sweep around me with their wings
Like angered eagles cheated of their prey,
The ages of all time: the glowing Heavens
Are rushing to receive us. Oh, rejoice
All ye that are immortal—and whate’er
Hath been predestined to eternal end,
The day determined ere all time was dawns!

XXXIV

Scene—Earth.

Angels and Saints—An Angel descending; Festus.
Saint |

Whence art thou?

Angel |

I? from Heaven, and thither tend;—
One moment here to bid ye to prepare.
Our Lord the Eternal Son comes hither, girt
With His victorious hosts, to judge the world.

Saint |

What victory hath our Almighty gained?

Angel |

One final, over Death and Hell. Shout, earth!
Thy freedom is accomplished, and thy foes
Brought down to endless ruin.

Saint |

Angel, speak!
We burn to learn the tidings of this war,
Whereof thou tell’st, and doubtless wast a part.

Angel |

Hot from the fight I come. This lightning blade
Hath holpen well to thin the infernal rout,
Which back hath fled to hell, howling like winds.
But let me, at your will, ye peaceful saints,
Relate what happed to us from first to last.
The time was come in Heaven when God the Son,
Bowing his head before the Omnipotent,
Who doubled every blessing infinite
Wherewith he had enriched His Only One
From first, rose from his glorious throne, and stepped
Into His sun-bright car, calling aloud
His angels to attend Him while He went
To judge the earth, as fore-ordained of old:
That Heaven and earth might view the majesty
And mercy of the God of all. We came,
Selectest spirits, countless—crowded bright
As the great stream of stars which flows through Heaven
Fast by the foot of God, each wave a world—
Eager to the eye this act of glory long
Talked of in Heaven, and now to be achieved.
Forth from the starry towers, and world-wide walls,
Of Heaven, we set in high and silent joy,
And journeyed half our way through Heaven, when lo!
A sight which checked the foremost flaming ranks,
That halted frontwise, working doubt at first,
But triumph after. Shielded and drawn up close,
Behind a broken and decaying world,
From which the light had vanished like the light
Out of a death-shrunk eye, sat Lucifer—
Midst in the powers of darkness, and the hosts
Of hell, enthroned sublime; and all were still
As ambushed silence round the Foe of God.
But oh! how changed from him we knew in Heaven,
Whose brightness nothing made might match nor mar;
Who rose, and it was morn;—who stretched his wing,
And stepped from star to star;—so changed he showed
Most like a shadowy meteor, thorough which
The stars dim glint—woe-wasted, pined with pain.
And by his side there sat or shrank a shape
We angels knew not, but the Son of God
Knew him, and called him Death; whom, when he saw,
Arousing, after, out of sleep intense,
That unrealmed tyrant drew his mortal dart,
And drave it through himself—a shade, shade-quelled.
Then to that chief of mischief and his fiends,
Who, thick as burning stones that from the throat
Of some volcano foul the benighted sky,
Shot up triumphant into air as they
Beheld our ranks move on, thus spake our Lord—
Not wrathfully, but sternly pitying:
Hell’s wretched remnant! wherefore crouch ye here?
Is it to sue destruction, or to bar
My passage? If it be, in both ye err.
And will ye trust yourselves again to war
With me Almighty? Have I not overcome
Ye separately, both? Speak, brutal Death!
Fit follower and fellow to all woes—
Wherefore this instantaneous haste from hell,
And both from Hadeän bondage, thus again
So soon to compass mightiest wickedness,
And tempt extremest wrath? Speak, head of hell!
To Him thus Lucifer: Almighty Son!
Thy power I defy not; but in peace
I war with fate. My life is to destroy.
Evil hath more activity, if good
More strength: and one must wear the other out.
The more august the sin, so much the more
Is my necessity. Yon earth hath been
The battle-plain of Heaven and hell. From Thee,
Who knowest all things, it were vain to hide
My purpose, which for a thousand years, the years
Of bondage, hath grown in me and lived on,
Toad-like within a rock—vital where all
Beside was death—to seize the nascent souls
Of men a they rerose from death to life,
And sweep them off in midst of all these hosts,
Assembled for that cause here as Thou seest,
To hell;—the universal race of man.
But if ordained that not on them, but Thee
And Thine, old hate shall satisfy itself,
Approach no nearer; for we live by death;—
Or turn the tide of fate, Thou sole who canst!
Ceasing thereat, his host upraised a shout
Which shook the stars, and made them ring again.
Our Lord to him then spake thus, mild as Spring,
Addressing earth when smiling she lets fall
All flowerets from her lips—’Tis well there is a God!
Lo! to what base extremes infernal pride
Can push a princely spirit once in Heaven.
Thee we will not destroy now, for thine hour
Hath yet to come—when least thou thinkest it.
God’s wrath thou hast endured in punishment.
Not yet His power. Away! I warn ye hence
Ere wrath ride forth again. To Him the Fiend
Answered: God rules not us the unordered damned,
Nor recks of hell. For ages past belief,
Unless by those who like ourselves denied
Thine own eternity—by creature mind,
However lofty, hardly compassed—we
Have borne our pain without remorse, or sign
Of pity from our Maker. Shall we now
Believe, while thus confronting Him again,
He means us better? Never worse than now.
Therefore I say to ye, on! mightiest fiends,
On! Let us reap companions for our woes,
Or earn annihilation! At the word,
His fiery phalanx rushed to bar the way
Of Him whose ways are over all His works.
A million spears blazed forth their answer bright,
As of as many tongues. Serene our ranks
Stood as the stars o’er thunder. God the Son
Sat in His orbèd car, and breathed on them;
And they were rolled up like the desert sands
Before the burning wind—throne wrecked on throne,
All ruined and fordone. Pursue! He cried,
Nor let them near the earth I go to judge.
And we pursued, as many as He chose,
And chased from sphere to sphere that wretched wreck
Of falsest fiends:—and I, it seems, am first
Of all my victor brethren to declare
The triumph past and coming, and to cheer
Tour hearts with tidings of our Lord, to whom
Be glory for His universal deeds,
And to him, only God!

Saint |

Behold where comes
Another warrior-angel from on high;
Like angels, always singly or in hosts.

Angel |

It is the most dread Azrael, unto whom
The sword of Death is given as a boon.

Saint |

What sayst thou, heavenly one?

Azrael |

To the extreme bound
Of Light’s domain we chased the flying foe,
Who on the confines of the lower air
Once rallied at their leader’s stern command,
Whom more they fear, or seem to fear, than God.
They halted, formed, and faced us. I and mine,
As on we came in order, full career,
Exalted by success, hoped ardently
One more convincing contest; but in spite
Of future woe or the tempestuous threats
Of the great Fiend who marshalled them, each eyed
His neighbor pale; their trembling shook all air;
And each one lift his arm, but no one struck.
Awhile in dead throe-like suspense they stood,
Or like the irresolution of the sea
At turn of tide—then wheeled and fled amain,
And in one mass immense broke down from Heaven,
Cliff-like;—there let them lie! such fate have fiends.
And we returned, hoping to meet, as charge
To all was given, the Lord our glory here.

Archangel |

Let all the dead rejoice! their Saviour comes.

XXXV

Scene—The judgment of Earth.

The Son of God, the Archangel, Saints and Angels.
Archangel |

Let all the dead rejoice! their Saviour comes;
With clouds of angels circled like a sun,
Belted with light, and brighter than all light,
Lo! He descends and seats Him on His throne,
Alighting like a new made sun in Heaven.
The world awaits Thee, Lord! Rise, souls of men,
Buried beneath all ages from the first;
Ye numbered and unnumbered, loathed and loved,
Awake to judgment! Rise! the grave no more
Hath power upon ye than the ravening sea
Upon the stars of Heaven. Ye elements!
Give back your stolen dead. He claimeth them
Whose they both were and are, and aye shall be.

Son of God |

I come to repay sin with holiness,
And death with immortality; man’s soul
With God’s Spirit; all evil with all good.
All men have sinned; and as for all I died,
All men are saved. Oh! not a single soul
Less than the countless all can satisfy
The infinite triumph which to me belongs,
Who infinitely suffered. Ye elect!
And all ye angels, with God’s love informed,
Who reign with me o’er earth and Heaven, assume
Your seats of judgment. Judge ye all in love,
The love which God the Father hath to you—
For His Son’s sake, and all shall be forgiven.

Saints |

Lord! let us render back to Thee the love
Which is Thine own: none else is worthy Thee.

Son of God |

Behold this day I dwell with thee on earth,
E’en to the last; the next shall be in Heaven,
Where ye shall meet the Father, and remain
In the Eternal presence, He through me
Blessing all spirits overflowingly.

Saints |

Dear Lord, our God and Saviour! for Thy gifts
The world were poor in thanks, though every soul
Were to do nought but breathe them, every blade
Of grass and every atomie of earth
To utter it like dew. Thy ways are plain
Only in Thine own light. And this great day
Unveils all nature’s laws and miracles—
All to Thee all as one. Thy death was life;
Thy judgment is all mercy, Lord of Love!
The world’s incomprehensible no more
To man, but all is bright as new-born star.

Son of God |

The Book of Life is opened. Heaven begins.